<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE proceeding SYSTEM "proceeding.dtd">
<proceeding ver="6.0" ts="04/10/2010">
<conference_rec>
	<conference_date>
		<start_date>08/07/2011</start_date>
		<end_date>08/11/2011</end_date>
	</conference_date>
	<conference_loc>
		<city><![CDATA[Vancouver]]></city>
		<state>British Columbia</state>
		<country>Canada</country>
	</conference_loc>
	<conference_url></conference_url>
</conference_rec>
<series_rec>
	<series_name>
		<series_id>SERIES382</series_id>
		<series_title><![CDATA[International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques]]></series_title>
		<series_vol></series_vol>
	</series_name>
</series_rec>
<proceeding_rec>
	<proc_id>2019342</proc_id>
	<acronym>SIGGRAPH '11</acronym>
	<proc_desc>ACM SIGGRAPH 2011 Art Gallery</proc_desc>
	<conference_number>2011</conference_number>
	<proc_class>conference</proc_class>
	<proc_title></proc_title>
	<proc_subtitle></proc_subtitle>
	<proc_volume_no></proc_volume_no>
	<isbn13>978-1-4503-0964-6</isbn13>
	<issn></issn>
	<eissn></eissn>
	<copyright_year>2011</copyright_year>
	<publication_date>08-07-2011</publication_date>
	<pages>101</pages>
	<plus_pages></plus_pages>
	<price><![CDATA[]]></price>
	<other_source></other_source>
	<abstract>
		<par><![CDATA[<p>In the era of networked technology, the interplay of physical and virtual within our lived experience opens up portals and wormholes enabling simultaneous and discontinuous realities at the touch of a button, echo of a voice, or nudge of a sensor. The new dynamics not only reconfigures our relations with ourselves and with one another, but most importantly, it reshapes our sense of identity, belonging, and place. The SIGGRAPH 2011 Art Gallery: Tracing Home, presents exceptional digital and technologically mediated artworks that explore issues related to the concept of home in the networked age.</p>]]></par>
	</abstract>
	<publisher>
		<publisher_id>PUB27</publisher_id>
		<publisher_code>ACMNY</publisher_code>
		<publisher_name>ACM</publisher_name>
		<publisher_address>2 Penn Plaza, Suite 701</publisher_address>
		<publisher_city>New York</publisher_city>
		<publisher_state>NY</publisher_state>
		<publisher_country>USA</publisher_country>
		<publisher_zip_code>10121-0701</publisher_zip_code>
		<publisher_contact>Bernard Rous</publisher_contact>
		<publisher_phone>212 869-7440</publisher_phone>
		<publisher_isbn_prefix></publisher_isbn_prefix>
		<publisher_url>www.acm.org/publications</publisher_url>
	</publisher>
	<sponsor_rec>
		<sponsor>
			<sponsor_id>SP932</sponsor_id>
			<sponsor_name>ACM Special Interest Group on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques</sponsor_name>
			<sponsor_abbr>SIGGRAPH</sponsor_abbr>
		</sponsor>
	</sponsor_rec>
	<categories>
		<primary_category>
			<cat_node/>
			<descriptor/>
			<type/>
		</primary_category>
	</categories>
	<chair_editor>
		<ch_ed>
			<person_id>P2759704</person_id>
			<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487648212]]></author_profile_id>
			<orcid_id></orcid_id>
			<seq_no>1</seq_no>
			<first_name><![CDATA[Mona]]></first_name>
			<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
			<last_name><![CDATA[Kasra]]></last_name>
			<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
			<affiliation><![CDATA[]]></affiliation>
			<role><![CDATA[Conference Chair]]></role>
			<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
		</ch_ed>
	</chair_editor>
</proceeding_rec>
<content>
	<section>
		<section_id>2019343</section_id>
		<sort_key>10</sort_key>
		<section_seq_no>1</section_seq_no>
		<section_type>SESSION</section_type>
		<section_title><![CDATA[Art papers]]></section_title>
		<section_page_from>302</section_page_from>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019344</article_id>
		<sort_key>20</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>7</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>1</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Conserving digital art for deep time]]></title>
		<page_from>302</page_from>
		<page_to>308</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019344</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019344</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Displaying digital art in the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries is already proving to be a challenge. Exhibiting this same art in the distant future will depend upon new thinking and practices developed today by artists, conservators, and curators. Established software engineering methods for dealing with aging systems can provide a new model for the conservation of digital art, and a foundation for the enhancement of art-historical scholarship. Artists with an interest in a more refined approach to the programming that underpins their work will also be interested in software engineering concepts.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>I.3.8</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010497.10010504.10010507</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Document management and text processing->Document capture->Graphics recognition and interpretation</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010147.10010371</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Computing methodologies->Computer graphics</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Measurement</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759705</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100428111]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Francis]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[T.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Marchese]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Pace University, New York, New York]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[fmarchese@pace.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1780699</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1780653</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Becker, et al., "Preserving Interactive Multimedia Art: A Case Study in Preservation Planning," <i>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</i>, Vol. 4822, 257--266 (2007).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[NINCH Working Group on Best Practices, "The NINCH Guide to Good Practice in the Digital Representation and Management of Cultural Heritage Materials Online: The National Initiative for a Networked Cultural Heritage" (2002), retrieved January 10, 2011 from www.nyu.edu/its/humanities/ninchguide/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[J. Ippolito, "Accommodating the Unpredictable: The Variable Media Questionnaire," <i>Permanence Through Change: The Variable Media Approach</i> (New York: Guggenheim Museum Publications and Montr&#233;al: The Daniel Langlois Foundation for Art, Science, and Technology, 2003).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[ERPANET, "The Archiving and Preservation of Born-Digital Art Workshop: Briefing Paper," The ERPANET Workshop on Preservation of Digital Art (2004). Retrieved January 10, 2011 from www.erpanet.org/events/2004/glasgowart/briefngpaper.pdf.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[For a concise review of the current state of the problem, see T. A. Yeung, S. Carpendale, and S. Greenberg, "Preservation of Art in the Digital Realm," <i>The Proceedings of iPRES2008: The Fifth International Conference on Digital Preservation</i> (London: British Library, 2008).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[International Council of Museums Committee for Conservation, "The Conservator-Restorer: A Definition of the Profession, Section 2.1." Retrieved January 10, 2011 from www.icom-cc.org/47/about-icom-cc/definition-of-profession/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[P. Laurenson, "Authenticity, Change and Loss in the Conservation of Time-Based Media Installations," <i>Tate Papers</i>, Autumn (2006). Retrieved March 15, 2011 from www.tate.org.uk/research/tateresearch/tatepapers/06autumn/laurenson.htm.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1593918</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[R. S. Pressman, <i>Software Engineering: A Practitioner's Approach</i>, 6th Edition (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2005).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1558901</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1558897</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[R. K. Ko, "A Computer Scientist's Introductory Guide to Business Process Management (BPM)," <i>Crossroads</i>, Vol. 15, No. 4, 11--18 (2009).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>794999</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>522081</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[J. Ransom, I. Sommerville, and I. Warren, "A Method for Assessing Legacy Systems for Evolution," <i>Proceedings of the 2nd Euromicro Conference on Software Maintenance and Reengineering</i> (CSMR 98), March 8--11, 1998 (Washington, DC: IEEE Computer Society, 1998) 128.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1044919</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[For a complete discussion, see C. Larman, <i>Applying UML and Patterns: An Introduction to Object-Oriented Analysis and Design and Iterative Development</i>, 3rd Edition (Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall, 2005).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[J. Zellen, <i>Trigger</i>, Pace Digital Gallery, New York, NY, October 18--November 8, 2005. Retrieved March 15, 2011 from www.jodyzellen.com/pace2.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1154679</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1153927</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[F. T. Marchese, "The Making of Trigger and the Agile Engineering of Artist-Scientist Collaboration," <i>Proceedings of the Tenth International Conference on Information Visualization: IV'06</i>, London, July 2006 (Washington, DC: IEEE Press, 2006) 839--844.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>617498</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>616006</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Upson, et al., "The Application Visualization System: A Computational Environment for Scientific Visualization," <i>IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications</i>, Vol. 9, No. 4, 30--42 (1989).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Conserving Digital Art for Deep Time Francis T. Marchese ABSTRACT Displaying digital art in the late 
twentieth and early twenty-first centuries is already proving to be a challenge. Exhibiting this same 
art in the distant future will depend upon new thinking and practices developed today by artists, conservators, 
and curators. Established software engineering methods for dealing with aging systems can provide a new 
model for the conservation of digital art, and a foundation for the enhancement of art-historical scholarship. 
Artists with an interest in a more refined approach to the programming that underpins their work will 
also be interested in software engineering concepts. Introduction Consider the following scenario. It 
is the year 2511, and a museum curator of 21st century digital art plans an exhibition encompassing the 
first decade of the 21st century. This decade was a heady time for digital art. Relentless innovations 
in computer hardware and software, and nearly limitless access to information afforded by the World Wide 
Web, provided artists with the means to create singular and collaborative artworks. Works ranged from 
the purely ephemeral, such as performance, to those fixed to a specific physical substrate, such as an 
immersive installation. Independent web sites, such as Rhizome.org and Turbulence.org, commissioned and 
hosted digital art, complemented by online museum galleries, such as the Whitney Muse­um s AirPort. New 
York s Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) and the Tate Modern in London increased their rate of acquisition 
of digital art through the 21st century s first decade, although these entities were far outpaced by 
Ars Electronica, which by 2010 had amassed over 30,000 digital artworks [1]. By 2010 it had already been 
recognized that digital art would pose many challenges for museums, particularly in terms of maintaining 
its longevity. General approaches to digital preservation had been focused primarily at the institutional 
level, which considered an organization s goals, priorities, available resources, and management policies 
[2]. A digital object within this context became a discrete entity with well defined attributes that 
could be managed throughout its lifetime. The goal of the digital preservation community had been to 
create standards and develop best practices for the conversion of digital material into archival formats 
that could be manipulated and shared. Digital art conservators had taken a two-pronged approach to preserving 
digital art as explicit digital artifacts: technology preservation and document compilation. Technology 
preservation encompassed both physical and digital artifacts. In the former case, computer technology 
is stockpiled to support the artwork in the inevitable case that a component fails (e.g., CPU, hard drive, 
etc.). In the latter, digital artifacts such as computer programs or digital videos must be archived 
to durable media. Because any digital storage medium (e.g., tape, CD, DVD) ultimately either decays or 
becomes obsolete, all digital artifacts must be routinely refreshed to a new storage medium. In document 
compilation, an extended set of documentation is assembled to help define and contextualize the artwork 
with the express purpose of making the artwork displayable at some future date. Artist interviews, questionnaires 
[3], artist-conservator-curator collaborative discussions, conservation workshops [4], and outright documentation 
of a pro­gram s source code were all approaches that had been taken. Yet these procedures remained experimental 
in nature, and had not been integrated into the formal scientific activity of art conservation [5]. Meanwhile, 
computer technology continued to advance, with older technology fading into obsolescence. Concomitantly, 
the variety of computer languages and software employed by digital artists expanded. In 2010 alone, languages 
such as C/C++, Java, JavaScript, Flash, HTML, XML, Processing, Perl, and Max/MSP were in use with widespread 
exploitation of development libraries and environments for such things as mobile application development, 
sound composi­tion, virtual worlds, and computer games. Operating systems evolved, database formats changed, 
and globally accessible data disappeared or became redistributed. Hence, given the assured evolution 
or transience in even the simplest of digital entities (e.g., video file formats), it would be difficult 
to predict that a computer-based artwork created in 2010 would survive intact so it could be exhibited, 
as originally constructed, in the year 2060 certainly not in the year 2511! Digital Art Conservation 
Artworks collected by museums possess a particular magisterial quality. Because museums are the de facto 
keepers of cultural heritage, any work acquired by a museum is expected to become part of the canon. 
Preservation is an essential part of museum practice. Once an institution has decided to acquire an artwork, 
its evaluation and care is entrusted to the museum s conservators. The practice of art conservation is 
a formal scientific activity, defined in the following way by the International Council of Museums Committee 
for Conservation: The activity of the conservator-restorer (conservation) consists of technical examination, 
preservation, and conservation-restoration of cultural property: Examination is the prelimi­nary procedure 
taken to determine the documentary significance of an artifact; original structure and materials; the 
extent of its deterioration, alteration, and loss; and the docu­mentation of these findings. Preservation 
is action taken to retard or prevent deterioration of or damage to cultural properties by control of 
their environment and/or treatment of their structure in order to maintain them as nearly as possible 
in an unchanging state. Restoration is action taken to make a deteriorated or damaged artifact understandable, 
with minimal sacrifice of aesthetic and historic integrity. [6] Traditional conservation practice thus 
focuses on an artwork as an integrated physical whole, the integrity of which must be preserved. Change 
is defined as a process that will deleteriously affect the stability of an artwork, moving it away from 
its original reference state and altering its identity. Time-based digital artwork does not fit this 
definition because change is an intrinsic part of its nature. Museum conservators in charge of maintaining 
time-based media, that is, artwork whose aesthetic experience evolves over time, realize this and are 
attempting to expand the conservation paradigm to accommodate digital art. Pip Laurenson, Head of Time-based 
Media Conservation at the Tate Museum, has proposed a redefinition of conservation practice to accommodate 
time-based media, so that conservation becomes the means by which an artwork s essential properties are 
documented, understood, and maintained. Its aim is the preservation of the artwork s identity, so that 
it may be displayed in the future as different possible authentic installations [7]. For Laurenson, the 
identity of a digital work should be considered as a collection of properties which include: the artist 
s instructions, approved installations intended to act as models, an understanding of the context in 
which the art was made, and the degree to which the artist specifications reflect his or her practice 
at the time the art was created. For a 26th century conservator this means that if the standard methods 
of digital art conservation (e.g., migration and emulation) eventually fail, then the preservation strategy 
of reinterpretation, that is, the process of recreating part or all of the artwork utilizing this extended 
documentation, can be invoked. This expanded notion of an artwork s identity as a collection of concepts 
and artifacts may be used as a starting point for formal identification and documentation of an artwork 
employing the principles and practices from the field of software engineering. Software engineering is 
the process of applying a systematic, disciplined, quantifiable approach to problem analysis, system 
and software design, its development, operation, and maintenance [8]. Software engineering methodologies 
focus on both the software product and the process used to create and maintain it. In the latter case, 
the software life-cycle is an extension of the business life-cycle and is defined by the business process 
management model (BPM) [9]. As such, its tools and techniques may be integrated into a museum s conservation 
practice. In the former, software engineering artifacts may be adapted to the representation of a digital 
artwork. Software engineering as a process may engage all stakeholders who comprise an art museum s business 
practice, including artists, curators, conservators, installers, maintainers, museum directors, art historians, 
and viewers; and can reflect and integrate this process into a museum s current best practices. Finally, 
software engineering practices may be adapted to all digital conservation strategies, including refreshing, 
migration, emulation, and recreation. Documentation and Conservation When a museum acquires a digital 
artwork, it is usually assumed that the work will be in a form that will allow it to be exhibited as 
is, with no further developments, enhancements, or adaptations expected from the artist who created the 
work. This work, along with its underlying concepts and technologies, is now frozen in time. In computing 
this is known as a legacy system [10]. Assessing the state of a legacy artwork at some point in time 
may be difficult for any number of reasons. For example, the artwork s existing documentation may be 
incomplete. Or changing museum business processes (e.g., curatorial milieu) which supported the original 
acquisition and installation of the artwork may be directed in the future along other trajectories, thus 
making upkeep of some legacy artworks more difficult. The nature of the digital artwork itself may be 
difficult to assess. It may have been assembled from many diverse components without a consistent design 
or programming style. Or it may be in either executable form or written in an obsolete programming language. 
Strategically, there are four approaches for dealing with traditional legacy systems. The first is to 
scrap the system outright, as business practices have changed and the system is no longer needed. If 
the system continues to work well and can be easily adapted over time, continued mainte­nance of the 
software is possible. But if system performance or usability continues to degrade over time, then the 
system or its parts must be transformed to improve maintainability. Finally, a system must be replaced 
if obsolete hardware or software precludes further operation, or the new system can be built at reasonable 
cost. For conservators, each one of these approaches creates its own set of issues, with degrees of intervention 
from minimal adaptation to full restoration, many of which are related to the importance of the artwork 
 an importance that should be expected to change over time. This is why it is most important that the 
long-term process of conserving a digital artwork must be based on a thorough understanding of its structure 
or architecture, as represented by a breadth of documentation. Documentation is an intrinsic component 
of any system. Software engineering provides a systematic methodology for creating and maintaining documentation 
that supports communica­tion, preservation of system and institutional memory, and processes such as 
system auditing. Within this context a computer system s documentation should provide comprehensive informa­tion 
about its capabilities, architecture, design details, features, and limitations. It should encompass 
the following components: Requirements Statements that identify the capabilities and characteristics 
of a digital artwork. This is the conceptual foundation for what has been created. Architecture/Design 
 An overview of software that includes the software s relationship to its environment and construction 
principles used in design of the software components. Typically a system s architecture is documented 
as a collection of diagrams or charts that show its parts and their interconnections. Technical Source 
code, algorithms, and interfaces are documented. Comments may be embedded within the system s source 
code and/or parts of external documentation. End User Manuals are created (e.g., static documents, hypermedia, 
training videos, etc.) for the end-user, system administrators, and support staff. Supplementary Materials 
 Anything else related to the system. This includes: legal docu­ments, design histories, interviews, 
scholarly books, installation plans, drawings, models, documentary videos, web sites, etc. [11] Each 
component is important to the representation of a digital system. Each may operate at a different level 
of abstraction or within a particular context. Requirements documentation presents the conceptual view 
of what the system is expected to do. It is written to be understood by all the stakeholders who comprise 
the art museum s business practice. Architecture/Design documentation functions very much like an architect 
s sketch of a building, showing all its components and how they fit together. Technical documentation 
represents the bricks-and- mortar of the artwork, conveying information about how the artwork is constructed. 
Besides facilitating an artwork s conservation, this documentation could also support scholarship, enabling 
art historians to understand an artist s working process and evolution of practice. A computer system 
s structure is a reflection of the conceptual space the artist had been working in at the time the art 
was created. The number of software components, their hierarchy, and the interconnections among them 
should give an idea of how the artist viewed a representation problem, and how it was transformed into 
a computer system. An analysis of documentation should yield answers to questions about: Authorship 
Who wrote what? (Was it by the hand of the artist, or was it built by others?) Educational/Cultural Context 
 Who influenced the artist conceptually or technologically? Craftsmanship How well was the program written 
and system built? Aesthetics How well conceived and designed is the software? Does it possess an elegance 
and refinement comparable to any other beautifully created object? Development Process What were the 
design strategies used by the artist? Technical Context What were the development tools available at 
the time the artwork was created? Theoretical Foundation What theories of computing did the artist use? 
Documentation and Digital Artists Documentation is a fundamental part of a digital artwork. A program 
s source code and the data it uses are de facto documentation, along with directions for its installation. 
The question remains how much more documentation is required to provide a sufficient representation 
of a digital artwork? This is an open question for any software engineering project, as it is for a digital 
artwork, and depends on factors such as project size, complexity, and expected system lifespan. It may 
be argued that it is not the artist s responsibility to provide sufficient documenta­tion for an artwork, 
but if contemporary curatorial practice is an indication of what the distant future will hold, the following 
scenario is most likely for a year 2511 exhibition. Artwork selec­tion will not only be based on its 
importance to the canon, but also the availability of resources (e.g., staffing, time, funds) required 
for its installation. An artwork that may be the best example of a theme or idiom may need to be replaced 
in an exhibition by a lesser work, because its own documentation proves insufficient for its recreation. 
It is posited here that a digital artist shares a certain responsibility for the long-term preservation 
of an artwork. Traditional artists who employ archival media and follow well established best practices 
for creating a stable physical artwork produce works with a high probability of standing the test of 
time. For those artists who consciously choose to work in a non-archival way, the long-term preservation 
and ultimate exhibition of their works is a problem with an indetermi­nate solution. It should be remembered 
that major museums possess culturally significant artworks that cannot be exhibited because of their 
fragility or degree of deterioration. Digital artists have choices analogous to their traditional counterparts 
for maintaining their artwork s longevity. Best practices exist for the development of computer software 
in different ways. For example, the use of standard programming styles, data structures, algorithms, 
and the selective insertion of comments into source code represent programming best practices. Software 
engineering best practices work at a different level. The software engineering conceptual process of 
analyze-design-build is consistent with artistic practice. And the tools used by software engineers during 
the analysis and design phases of software development allow software design­ers literally to sketch 
out a system s architectural design. Including these design representations with an artwork s source 
code expands its representational details to encompass the Requirements, Analysis/Design, and Technical 
documentation categories discussed above. It should provide as well a sufficient description of the artwork 
s identity to allow it to be recreated at some future time if all other conservation strategies fail. 
Back to the Future One of the works selected for the 2011 retrospective by the 26th century curator was 
Trigger, a site-specific, sensor-activated, immersively projected, interactive art installation by Jody 
Zellen that debuted at the Pace Digital Gallery in the fall of 2005 [12]. Zellen created Trigger to explore 
the transient stories that emerge from our relationships with urban spaces. The gallery was filled with 
overlapping videos from seven projectors and infused with transient sounds. When visitors passed through 
motion sensors, sounds and videos changed, evoking the ephemeral nature of urban space, and the fleeting 
and shifting perceptions of it. Neither Trigger s original hardware nor software made it to the year 
2011, much less to 2511; the system was disassembled and repurposed at show s end. The documentation 
available to the 26th century curator included: the artwork s original videos, a video walkthrough of 
the artwork, images of the installation, a catalog, and a short technical paper about the artwork [13]. 
The technical paper provided key information for Trigger s recreation its functional requirements, architecture, 
and design. The artwork s functional requirements identified its capabilities and characteristics, simply 
put: what the artwork was supposed to do. They were recorded in the technical paper as: The artwork would 
support a large number of projectors, sensors, and speakers. The artwork s sensors would capture viewer 
motion. Captured motions would trigger events. Events would be communicated to the artist s multimedia 
programs. The multimedia programs would change the content of the displays and alter sounds. Trigger 
s architecture communicated the high-level interrelationships among its components without specifying 
the processing details. Trigger possessed a simple architecture of three loosely coupled components: 
a microcontroller-sensor system, application software, and interface software linking the sensor system 
to the application. Each of these components worked independently, communicating by simple message passing. 
Such a relationship exhibited the attribute of low coupling, a fundamental software design paradigm. 
Finally, the technical paper briefly described each component s responsibilities. In all, Trigger s technical 
discussion covered no more than a page, but, combined with its supplemental materials (e.g., video walkthrough 
and installation images), that was sufficient for the 26th century recreation of the artwork to maintain 
its identity and reflect Zellen s artistic practice. Trigger s clearly defined functional requirements 
and simple architecture made its recreation possible. It afforded the curator s team the flexibility 
of selecting the best computer method for reconstructing the artwork. In contrast, if Trigger had been 
conserved at the source code level, the curator s team would have had to sift through the code to extract 
its internal workings, and then either adapt the code to its 26th century environment, or reconstruct 
its architectural representation. In the end, recreation of Trigger became a trivial matter, utilizing 
a 26th century equivalent of a 21st century data-flow programming language for multimedia applications 
like Cycling 74 s Max/MSP. Data-flow programming languages have had a long history, evolving from workstation-based 
scientific visualization systems such as AVS [14] in the late 1980s. Recognized for their ease and versatility 
in defining parallel event-based systems, these visual programming languages continued to evolve over 
time. Indeed, the original developers of Trigger had considered using Max/MSP in 2005, but were constrained 
from doing so. Ultimately, the retrospective s curator capitalized on each artwork s unique documentation 
to craft a cogent story of early 21st century art. From Trigger s high-level designs to another artwork 
s creatively commented source code, all of the artworks documentation acted in concert to help recreate 
a sense of what digital art was like at the dawn of the 21st century. In Sum The display of contemporary 
digital art at some distant future time remains an open problem, the solution to which will come from 
efforts by artists, conservators, and curators. It has been proposed here that the use of software engineering 
practices will provide a new jumping-off point for transitioning from the conservation practices used 
for traditional art to methods more appropriate for time-based media. This process will aid digital art 
scholarship as well, by organizing an artwork s components in such a way as to enhance accessibility 
by art historians. Finally, digital artists who choose to adapt software engineering practice to their 
artistic process will be able to extend the lifespan of their artwork. References and Notes 1. C. Becker, 
et al., Preserving Interactive Multimedia Art: A Case Study in Preservation Planning, Lecture Notes in 
Computer Science, Vol. 4822, 257 266 (2007). 2. NINCH Working Group on Best Practices, The NINCH Guide 
to Good Practice in the Digital Representation and Management of Cultural Heritage Materials Online: 
The National Initiative for a Networked Cultural Heritage (2002), retrieved January 10, 2011 from www.nyu.edu/its/humanities/ninchguide/. 
3. J. Ippolito, Accommodating the Unpredictable: The Variable Media Questionnaire, Permanence Through 
Change: The Variable Media Approach (New York: Guggenheim Museum Publications and Montréal: The Daniel 
Langlois Foundation for Art, Science, and Technology, 2003). 4. ERPANET, The Archiving and Preservation 
of Born-Digital Art Workshop: Briefing Paper, The ERPANET Workshop on Preservation of Digital Art (2004). 
Retrieved January 10, 2011 from www.erpanet.org/events/2004/glasgowart/briefingpaper.pdf. 5. For a concise 
review of the current state of the problem, see T.A. Yeung, S. Carpendale, and S. Greenberg, Preservation 
of Art in the Digital Realm, The Proceedings of iPRES2008: The Fifth International Conference on Digital 
Preservation (London: British Library, 2008). 6. International Council of Museums Committee for Conservation, 
The Conservator-Restorer: A Definition of the Profession, Section 2.1. Retrieved January 10, 2011 from 
www.icom-cc.org/47/about-icom-cc/definition-of-profession/. 7. P. Laurenson, Authenticity, Change and 
Loss in the Conservation of Time-Based Media Installations, Tate Papers, Autumn (2006). Retrieved March 
15, 2011 from www.tate.org.uk/research/tateresearch/tatepapers/06autumn/laurenson.htm. 8. R.S. Pressman, 
Software Engineering: A Practitioner s Approach, 6th Edition (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2005). 9. R.K. Ko, 
A Computer Scientist s Introductory Guide to Business Process Management (BPM), Crossroads, Vol. 15, 
No. 4, 11 18 (2009). 10. J. Ransom, I. Sommerville, and I. Warren, A Method for Assessing Legacy Systems 
for Evolution, Proceedings of the 2nd Euromicro Conference on Software Maintenance and Reengineering 
(CSMR 98), March 8 11, 1998 (Washington, DC: IEEE Computer Society, 1998) 128. 11. For a complete discussion, 
see C. Larman, Applying UML and Patterns: An Introduction to Object-Oriented Analysis and Design and 
Iterative Development, 3rd Edition (Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall, 2005). 12. J. Zellen, Trigger, 
Pace Digital Gallery, New York, NY, October 18 November 8, 2005. Retrieved March 15, 2011 from www.jodyzellen.com/pace2.html. 
13. F.T. Marchese, The Making of Trigger and the Agile Engineering of Artist-Scientist Collaboration, 
Proceedings of the Tenth International Conference on Information Visualization: IV'06, London, July 2006 
(Washington, DC: IEEE Press, 2006) 839 844. 14. C. Upson, et al., The Application Visualization System: 
A Computational Environment for Scientific Visualization, IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, Vol. 
9, No. 4, 30 42 (1989). Francis T. Marchese Educator, Gallery Director Pace University Computer Science 
Department New York, New York 10038 USA fmarchese@pace.edu  &#38;#169; 2011 Francis T. Marchese | 
 Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 302 308, 2011 302  Conserving Digital Art for Deep Time |  Marchese 
 303  Marchese  |  Conserving Digital Art for Deep Time 304  Conserving Digital Art for Deep Time 
 |  Marchese 305  Marchese  |  Conserving Digital Art for Deep Time 306  Conserving Digital Art 
for Deep Time |  Marchese 307  Marchese  |  Conserving Digital Art for Deep Time 308  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019345</article_id>
		<sort_key>30</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>8</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>2</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Art and code]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[the aesthetic legacy of Aldo Giorgini]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>309</page_from>
		<page_to>316</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019345</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019345</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>In 1975 Aldo Giorgini developed a software program in FORTRAN called FIELDS, a numerical visual laboratory devoted entirely to art production. Working extensively as both artist and scientist, Giorgini was one of the first computer artists to combine software writing with early printing technologies, leaving an aesthetic legacy in the field of the digital arts. His individual process was innovative in that it consisted of producing pen-plotted drawings embellished by the artist's hand with painting, drawing, and screen-printing. This paper is the product of a multi-year study of Giorgini's primary source materials provided by his estate. The authors examine the methods used by Giorgini during the 1970s that allowed him to create computer-aided art, in the hope that publishing this work will ensure that future generations of digital artists, technologists and scientists can be educated in Giorgini's contribution to the history of the digital arts.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.2</cat_node>
				<descriptor>People</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10003456.10003457.10003521.10003522</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Social and professional topics->Professional topics->History of computing->Historical people</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Human Factors</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759706</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487643025]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Esteban]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Garc&#237;a]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Purdue University, Lafayette, Indiana]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[garcia0@purdue.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759707</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81466648217]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[David]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Whittinghill]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Purdue University, Lafayette, Indiana]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[davewhit@purdue.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[M. Giorgini, <i>Aldo Giorgini: 1934--1994</i>. Unpublished manuscript.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Faculty and Staff, <i>Giorgini, Aldo Vertical File</i>, Archives and Special Collections, Purdue Libraries. Accessed October 2009.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Burbano, "Between Punched Film Stock and the First Computers: The Work of Konrad Zuse" (2010).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[P. Trachtman, "Charles Csuri Is an `Old Master' in a New Medium." Retrieved December 8, 2010 from www.siggraph.org/artdesign/profile/csuri/index.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Csuri, "Charles Csuri," <i>Artist and Computer</i>, R. Leavitt, ed. (New York: Creative Computing Press, 1976) 85--87.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Giorgini and W. C. Chen, <i>Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS</i> (West Lafayette, IN: School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 3.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ibid., p. 4.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ibid., p. 3.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Reas, C. McWilliams, and J. Barendse, <i>Form and Code in Design, Art, and Architecture</i> (New York: Princeton Architectural Press, 2010) 21.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Reas, "{Software} Structures" (2004). Retrieved December 8, 2010, from artport.whitney.org/commissions/softwarestructures/text.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[G. Garrells, ed., <i>Sol LeWitt: A Retrospective</i> (London: Yale University Press, 2000).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Giorgini, "Computer Art Symposium at Purdue" {tape recording} (Lafayette, IN: Aldo Giorgini's personal collection, March 24, 1975).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Giorgini and W. C. Chen, <i>Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS</i> (West Lafayette, IN: School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 1.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ibid., p. 5.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Giorgini, "Aldo Giorgini," <i>Artist and Computer</i>, R. Leavitt, ed. (New York: Creative Computing Press, 1976) 9--12.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Giorgini and W. C. Chen, <i>Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS</i> (West Lafayette, IN: School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 6.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ibid., p. 2.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[M. A. Giorgini, personal communication, October 23, 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[L. Livermore, "My Last Column for Maximum Rocknroll," <i>Maximum Rocknroll</i>, No. 133 (April 1994).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>20</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Giorgini and W. C. Chen, <i>Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS</i> (West Lafayette, IN: School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 4.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Art and Code: The Aesthetic Legacy of Aldo Giorgini Esteban García and David Whittinghill ABSTRACT In 
1975 Aldo Giorgini developed a software program in FORTRAN called FIELDS, a numerical visual laboratory 
devoted entirely to art production. Working extensively as both artist and scientist, Giorgini was one 
of the first computer artists to combine software writing with early printing technologies, leaving an 
aesthetic legacy in the field of the digital arts. His individual process was innovative in that it consisted 
of producing pen-plotted drawings embellished by the artist s hand with painting, drawing, and screen-printing. 
This paper is the product of a multi-year study of Giorgini s primary source materi­als provided by his 
estate. The authors examine the methods used by Giorgini during the 1970s that allowed him to create 
computer-aided art, in the hope that publishing this work will ensure that future generations of digital 
artists, technologists and scientists can be educated in Giorgini s contribution to the history of the 
digital arts. Introduction Aldo Giorgini (1934 1994) was a professor in the School of Civil Engineering 
at Purdue University. During the 1970s, he adopted the use of computers to visualize simulated terrains. 
His scientific visualizations as a civil engineer led him to pursue a creative artistic practice, which 
combined the use of mathematical models, computer graphics, and painting (Figure 1). In 1975 Giorgini 
developed a software program called FIELDS, a numerical visual laboratory devoted entirely to art production. 
In FIELDS, FORTRAN instructions were loaded in a CalComp plotter and later printed on paper rolls. Giorgini 
incorporated handmade art techniques to fill in the lines printed by a CalComp 563 plotter. Some of these 
images were reproduced through an elaborate silk-screen printing process. His versatile technique combined 
high numerical computation with large-scale silk-screen printing. Working as both artist and scientist, 
Giorgini developed innovative techniques that left an aesthetic legacy in the field of digital arts. 
Giorgini was one of the first computer artists to combine software writing with early computer printing 
technologies to produce artistic images. His creative process consisted of the production of computer-aided 
images, which were embellished by the artist s hand with painting, drawing and screen-printing. This 
research is the result of the analysis of primary sources found at Giorgini s residence in Lafayette, 
Indiana, and the Purdue University Archives and Special Collections. The sampled documents include manuscripts, 
letters, publications, clippings, printed code, cassette tapes, and CalComp prints related to the FIELDS 
project. This paper will unveil the methods used by Giorgini to produce his computer-aided art. Artist 
and Scientist Aldo Giorgini was born in Voghera, Italy, in 1934. He was influenced by Ambrogio Casati, 
an artist who was part of the Italian Futurist movement and who took Giorgini as an apprentice. As a 
young man in the 1950s, Giorgini helped Casati restore frescoes and oil paintings from the old masters 
that had been damaged during World War II. Giorgini developed expertise in painting as a result of his 
work with Casati. This apprenticeship provided him with a solid groundwork in fine arts training. At 
age eighteen, Giorgini received a full scholarship to the University of Pavia where he finished his undergraduate 
studies in engineering. After this period, he commenced work on a doctorate in mechanical engineering, 
which he completed in 1959. Giorgini was an associate professor of hydraulics at the Polytechnic University 
of Torino from 1959 to 1961. Subsequently, Giorgini won a Fullbright Grant as an exchange scholar at 
the Colorado State University in Fort Collins. There, Giorgini completed a second doctorate in civil 
engineering in 1966. In 1967 he moved to West Lafayette, Indiana, to work as a professor in the School 
of Civil Engineering at Purdue University [1]. At Purdue s School of Civil Engineering, Giorgini experimented 
with software production and pen-plotter printers. From 1967 to 1976, he developed an interest in the 
visualization of numerical data in a graphic form. While a professor of civil engineering, he completed 
a third doctorate in Physics. Most importantly for this paper, Giorgini developed an extensive body of 
work as a computer artist from 1974 until his death in 1994. His artistic practice was not limited to 
art production, but included participation in early computer art exhibitions, publications, symposiums, 
and conferences. Giorgini was an advocate for this new field in the arts and he organized two symposiums: 
Computers and the Design Process in 1974, and Computer Art in 1975 [2]. Art with Computers The use of 
the computer as a tool for artistic experimentation dates back to the first program­mable computers. 
The Z3 computer built by Konrad Zuse in 1941 is considered the first binary, electromechanical, programmable 
computer. In a recent paper, Andrés Burbano explains Zuse s double role as scientist and artist: While 
his work includes the creation of the first program­ming language, the Plankalkül, he was also an active 
visual artist for most of his life, and he himself defined his approach to the world as highly visual 
[3]. Another example of early computer art is the work of Charles Csuri, who was a professor at Ohio 
State University and is known for his early experiments in the field of computer graphics. Csuri began 
exploring digital art in 1964, inspired by a computer-generated image he saw in a publica­tion from Ohio 
State University s Department of Electrical Engineering [4]. Csuri used visualization software to produce 
the first computer-aided film in 1965. Like Csuri, Aldo Giorgini incorporated the use of computers in 
his artistic practice. However, Csuri s and Giorgini s approaches to computer graphics were fundamentally 
different. In the case of Csuri, the artist was not required to have the knowledge of the numbers and 
codes which produced the desired form. It was through the GUI that the digital image was produced. In 
the words of Csuri: Additional software capabilities provide the user with the ability to modify system 
parameters through interactive devices and to alter curvilinear relationships without ever having to 
think of numbers [5]. In contrast, Giorgini argued that a user who plays with a program by changing the 
value of the parameters at random is hardly intentionally producing the drawing. Giorgini used the term 
canned program to describe software in which a pleasant drawing could be produced without the intention 
of the user. Furthermore, Giorgini defined intentional computer art as only achieved when the user acknowledges 
all of the parameters of the program. According to his definition, if the user understands the mechanism 
of the program and what all of its parameters mean, it might be assumed the result was intentional [6]. 
Giorgini explained that art is defined by the intentionality of the artist. This allowed him to include 
software writing as part of his creative process. He gave priority to the artist's ideas over the tools 
[7]. Ideas as Art Giorgini questioned the role of the artist as merely a producer of images. In his writings, 
he illustrates that the artist is the ideator of the drawing, and that several intermediate steps lay 
between the idea and the final product. In his own words, he explains the relationship between software 
and artist: The program is more than a medium: It is a programme with built-in directions which, no matter 
how open, still compel the artist to move with some constraints or on along [sic] some perspective, that 
are part of the original idea of the program. [8] Visual artists from the 1960s shared similar thoughts 
about art, idea, and process. Emphasis on the work of art as an idea was a common characteristic of conceptual 
art in the 1960s. During this period, many artists explored the aesthetics of programmatic thought and 
execution. Reas, McWilliams, and Barendse explain how artists and musicians of this era created a different 
type of work that included writing instructions as a form of art [9]. Sol LeWitt s work is reminiscent 
of this program-natured visual art. In his writing entitled {Software} Structures, Casey Reas argues 
that LeWitt s instructions for his wall drawings can be compared to computer code [10]. For his wall 
drawings, LeWitt wrote a set of instructions for draftpersons who produced the physical piece. For example, 
the instructions for Wall Drawing #366 read as follows: Black arcs using the height of the wall as a 
radius, and black arcs using the midpoints of the wall as radius. The arcs are filled in solid and drawn 
in india ink [11]. Although it is unknown how aware Giorgini was of the conceptual art tendencies of 
the 1960s, he certainly was interested in programmatic explorations in the visual arts. At the Computer 
Art conference entitled Computer Art held at Purdue University in 1975, Charles and Colette Bangert, 
Richard Helmick, George Chaikin, and Giorgini discussed computational aesthetics. As heard on the audio 
tape recording from this event, the works of Mondrian were described as compositional programs. According 
to Charles Bangert, Mondrian s use of the golden section to produce a composition is comparable to the 
algorithms used in computer art [12]. The computer-aided art pieces of Giorgini provide evidence of his 
unique array of talents. While at first glance writing software and art making did not seem to have a 
relationship, a few artists of that time, such as Giorgini and Csuri, sought to explore the aesthetic 
possibilities of new technologies. In Giorgini s words, Each output device has its own graphical characteristics 
which, once fully understood and fully exploited, may yield an incredible amount of possible forms [13]. 
In this section we described the context in which Giorgini produced his computer-aided art and how he 
theorized about the role of software in artistic practice. Giorgini s approach to aesthetics consists 
of the artist s intentionality and ideas to produce the artwork. Giorgini s focus on the idea as the 
most important value for the definition of visual forms connected his art to the conceptual art tendencies 
of the 1960s. His ideas in programmable aesthetics resulted in FIELDS, a program intentioned for artistic 
production. Giorgini established a conceptual separation between tools and ideas, giving more importance 
to the ideas. FIELDS: A Numerical Visual Laboratory In a report published by Purdue s School of Civil 
Engineering entitled Interfaces , Giorgini defined FIELDS as a numerical visual laboratory. The use of 
the words numerical visual laboratory reflects Giorgini s approach to the production of images by changing 
parameters of the program. These numerical parameters were not just variables of a math­ematical equation, 
they were the ingredients to produce lines, points, and ellipses. Giorgini explains the relationship 
between geometry, form and experimentation: Families of lines have a strong appeal to the imagination 
of anybody with [sic] inclination to geometrization. The gradual variation of curvature along each line 
from the other lines, constitutes an infinite source of aesthetic possibilities for exploitation. [14] 
Giorgini s ability to visualize forms from mathematical functions allowed him to create lines and shapes 
from numerical values. Several manuscripts found in the Giorgini residence present evidence of his mathematical 
approach to graphics (Figure 2). Visualizing the Z Dimension: A Mathematical Model Giorgini s background 
in civil engineering and physics allowed him to use equipotential lines to produce contour lines. His 
research, particularly in terrain visualization while at Purdue, greatly influenced the aesthetics of 
his work. The computer-aided visual research from the civil engineering work awoke Giorgini s interest 
in aesthetics. Giorgini explains: I started playing around with some of the computer drawings that were 
made as illustration of the research done. From here to the purposeful use of the computer as an art 
tool the pace was very short [15]. Some of the parameters of FIELDS are formulated in topographic terms. 
A piece produced by FIELDS can be described as a map view of mountains and valleys. A topographical representa­tion 
in these two dimensions suggests a third dimension through the use of successive contour lines, which 
wrap around the different heights. In FIELDS, the fictitious value of depth was named Z, a highly three-dimensional 
concept. FIELDS simulated physical fields by producing a gradiation of lines between surfaces of differ­ing 
depth. The surfaces in FIELDS were named boundaries and they could be defined as points, ellipses, or 
circles. The program would create a field simulation that produced a series of contours around the tallest 
boundary towards the lowest. The value of Z at the boundaries was 0 or 1. The contour lines were produced 
as a transition from these two values. In the words of Giorgini, the end product of the operations performed 
on the elementary potential surfaces will closely resemble the geometrical representation of a physical 
field [16]. The result was an image that represented the top view of simu­lated fields (Figures 3 and 
4). The composition was defined by sets of points in Cartesian coordinates to produce geometric shapes. 
These shapes were considered to be at Z=1 and would gradually transition to the boundary at Z=0, producing 
the effect of the rippled contours. In FIELDS, the boundary at Z=0 was typically a square that defined 
the aspect and border of the piece. Giorgini was aware of technological advances for scientific visualization 
and had access to them through his laboratory at Purdue. His lab had a CalComp pen plotter, an instrument 
which draws lines on paper at the execution of a computer code. Giorgini envisioned the creative potential 
of CalComp as a new medium for art production. His strong background in mathematical concepts allowed 
him to formulate the visualization of numerical models. In 1974, Aldo Giorgini asked his colleague at 
Purdue, Wei-Chung Chen, for assistance in developing a FORTRAN code of his mathematical model. This software 
was presented in the report entitled Interfaces, containing 884 lines of code over 14 pages. The implementation 
of the mathematical model into FORTRAN code and its further interface with CalComp is the essence of 
Giorgini s numerical visual laboratory. Originally, the CalComp pen-plotter in his lab was used to create 
visual simulations of terrain. Giorgini used mathematical models to visualize real geographical topography. 
Later, he used this technology to make large-scale artworks with a topographical aesthetic. In FIELDS, 
the piece is algorithmically produced from initial numerical values and printed in paper at run time. 
The numerical values defined the geometric boundaries of the initial shapes and the relationships between 
the different fields (Figures 5 and 6). A CalComp 563 plotter was loaded with bond paper rolls and drew 
the contour lines in black ink. The standard width of the available paper rolls for CalComp 563 was fifteen 
inches. However, Giorgini created the large-scale art pieces by printing in separated modules and mounting 
them together. Examples of his use of modularity in large-scale artwork can be appreciated in Fiat Lux 
and Sculptural Forms, found at the Potter Engineering Center at Purdue. His studio in the basement of 
his former residence holds hundreds of CalComp prints. It is important to remark that the prints themselves 
are not the work of art, because it was through Giorgini s process that these prints became art. Code 
and Ink After printing on paper, Giorgini started an elaborate handmade process for the completion of 
the art piece. He was interested in complement­ing the computer work with paint. In Interfaces he explains: 
In the case where the output needs further interven­tion by the artist in order to produce the final 
art piece, the term of computer-aided art will apply [17]. CalComp could produce only lines and Giorgini 
chose to fill in the shapes formed by the line intersections with checkerboard patterns. These often 
produced optical illusions such as Moiré patterns. One of the defining characteristics of Giorgini s 
works with FIELDS is that he only used black acrylic paints or inks to create these patterns. In the 
appendix of Interfaces , he explains the perceptual visual qualities of Moiré and checkerboard patterns, 
however he does not explain the reasons for choosing these patterns. The work is reminiscent of Op Art, 
such as the work of Victor Vasarelly and René Parola, and it can be surmised that Giorgini had an interest 
in these artists. Giorgini used high contrast reproductions of his work to produce the negatives for 
a silk-screen printing process. Silk-screen printing uses photographic emulsions and negative images 
printed on transparency paper to produce a template for image reproduction. Many of these silk-screen 
frames and negatives remain at Giorgini s former residence in Lafayette, where his son Massimil­iano 
Adelmo now lives. In an interview, Massimiliano recalled that it took his father a great deal of time 
to master the silk-screening technique for the large-format prints he produced in his studio. Aldo Giorgini 
also experimented with inks of different colors, but he remained interested in high-contrast color combinations 
[18]. Giorgini also liked to screenprint T-shirts and sweatshirts and often wore them to teach classes 
or gave them away to friends. Aldo Giorgini s charismatic and interdisciplinary personality led him to 
influence the lives of many friends and students. In a dedicated column for the Maxi­mum Rock and Roll 
magazine, record producer Lawrence Livermore explains: I would like to tell you about one very special 
man, who, though I ve only spent a few hours in his company, has illuminated my life in a way only a 
very tiny handful of people have been able to [19]. Giorgini spent the rest of his days working as an 
artist and a scientist. Giorgini left an inspiring testimony to early computer-aided art practice, which 
constitutes an important landmark in the history of the digital arts. Discussion and Future Work In an 
effort to preserve the aesthetic legacy of Aldo Giorgini, it is important to consider solutions for the 
preservation of his FIELDS software. One such solution entails the digitization of the 884 lines of FORTRAN 
code and implementation in Xcode, a modern-day compiler. Many compilers can read FORTRAN code through 
the installation of the widely available gfortran library. In the future, we seek to explore a fully 
functional code that reproduces the functionality of FIELDS by producing an output image. In Interfaces, 
Giorgini precisely formulated a question of author­ship in relation to software art, which still remains 
unanswered today: A computer drawing might have been made by a person with a program formulated by another 
person and programmed by another person again. Who is the artist? [20] In Giorgini's case, the work consists 
of these six steps: creating the software, defining the geometric boundaries of the composition, computation, 
printing, painting, and screen-printing. Giorgini used FIELDS to produce graphics which would be extremely 
difficult to calculate without the aid of a computer. The preservation of Giorgini s FIELDS software 
in the form of a functional implementation in a contemporary system will allow future generations to 
revisit his innovative work. In recent years, there has been a rise of code-based toolkits for artists 
and designers, such as Processing, open­Frameworks, Cinder, and Cing. Artistically oriented programmers 
have released a variety of software and libraries to allow artists to experiment in the realm of digital 
art. FIELDS consti­tutes a landmark in code-based art practices. The study of Giorgini's contribution 
presents a historical framework for artists who use programming as a medium. Conclusion This research 
explains the importance of Aldo Giorgini s work in the field of the digital arts. The work of Aldo Giorgini 
is of historical significance because he adopted early computer technolo­gies to produce computer-aided 
artworks. FIELDS constitutes an important precedent to software art. The documents found at the Giorgini 
s former residence in Lafayette possess historical value, and we consider the importance of the preservation 
of these materials for future generations. Preservation of these materials will capture some of the early 
methods and tech­niques used to produce digital art. Acknowledgments The authors of this paper would 
like to thank Massimiliano Giorgini for his generous help in granting access to Aldo Giorgini's materials. 
We would also like to thank Rosanne Altstatt and Stephanie Schmitz for their help in editing the text. 
References 1. M. Giorgini, Aldo Giorgini: 1934 1994. Unpublished manuscript. 2. Faculty and Staff, Giorgini, 
Aldo Vertical File, Archives and Special Collections, Purdue Libraries. Accessed October 2009. 3. A. 
Burbano, Between Punched Film Stock and the First Computers: The Work of Konrad Zuse (2010). 4. P. Trachtman, 
Charles Csuri Is an Old Master in a New Medium. Retrieved December 8, 2010 from www.siggraph.org/artdesign/profile/csuri/index.html. 
5. C. Csuri, Charles Csuri, Artist and Computer, R. Leavitt, ed. (New York: Creative Computing Press, 
1976) 85 87. 6. A. Giorgini and W.C. Chen, Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS (West Lafayette, 
IN: School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 3. 7. Ibid., p.4. 8. Ibid., p.3. 9. C. Reas, 
C. McWilliams, and J. Barendse, Form and Code in Design, Art, and Architecture (New York: Princeton Architectural 
Press, 2010) 21. 10. C. Reas, {Software} Structures (2004). Retrieved December 8, 2010, from artport.whitney.org/commissions/softwarestructures/text.html. 
11. G. Garrells, ed., Sol LeWitt: A Retrospective (London: Yale University Press, 2000). 12. A. Giorgini, 
Computer Art Symposium at Purdue [tape recording ] (Lafayette, IN: Aldo Giorgini s personal collection, 
March 24, 1975). 13. A. Giorgini and W.C. Chen, Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS (West 
Lafayette, IN: School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 1. 14. Ibid., p.5. 15. A. Giorgini, 
Aldo Giorgini, Artist and Computer, R. Leavitt, ed. (New York: Creative Computing Press, 1976) 9 12. 
16. A. Giorgini and W.C. Chen, Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS (West Lafayette, IN: 
School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 6. 17. Ibid., p.2. 18. M. A. Giorgini, personal 
communication, October 23, 2010. 19. L. Livermore, My Last Column for Maximum Rocknroll, Maximum Rocknroll, 
No. 133 (April 1994). 20. A. Giorgini and W.C. Chen, Interfaces, Computer-aided Art: The Program FIELDS 
(West Lafayette, IN: School of Civil Engineering, Purdue University, 1974) 4. Esteban García Artist 
and PhD Student Computer Graphics Department Purdue University 1204 Columbia Street Lafayette, Indiana 
47901 USA garcia0@purdue.edu David Whittinghill Assistant Professor Computer Graphics Department Purdue 
University Knoy Hall 401 N. Grant Street West Lafayette, Indiana 47907 USA davewhit@purdue.edu  Figure 
1. Aldo Giorgini installing his installation Fiat Lux. &#38;#169; 1980 Aldo Giorgini. Courtesy of Massimiliano 
Giorgini.  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 309 316, 2011  |  &#38;#169; 2011 Esteban García and David 
Whittinghill 309  García and Whittinghill  |  Art and Code: The Aesthetic Legacy of Aldo Giorgini 
 310  Art and Code: The Aesthetic Legacy of Aldo Giorgini |  García and Whittinghill 311  Figure 
2. Manuscript. &#38;#169; 1974 Aldo Giorgini.  García and Whittinghill  |  Art and Code: The Aesthetic 
Legacy of Aldo Giorgini 312  Figure 3. Top view of simulated fields. From Giorgini and Chen [6]. &#38;#169; 
1974 Aldo Giorgini.  Figure 4. 3D representation of Figure 3, rendered by the authors. &#38;#169; 2011 
Esteban García.  Art and Code: The Aesthetic Legacy of Aldo Giorgini |  García and Whittinghill 313 
 Figure 5. Geometric formulation of Claustrophobia. From Giorgini and Chen [6]. &#38;#169; 1974 Aldo 
Giorgini.  García and Whittinghill  |  Art and Code: The Aesthetic Legacy of Aldo Giorgini 314  
Figure 6. Claustrophobia. Acrylic and paint on paper, from Interfaces by Giorgini and Chen. From Giorgini 
and Chen [6]. &#38;#169; 1974 Aldo Giorgini.  Figure 7. Example of one of Giorgini s CalComp prints. 
&#38;#169; 1979 Aldo Giorgini.  Art and Code: The Aesthetic Legacy of Aldo Giorgini |  García and 
Whittinghill 315  García and Whittinghill  |  Art and Code: The Aesthetic Legacy of Aldo Giorgini 
 316  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019346</article_id>
		<sort_key>40</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>8</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>3</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[<i>The Readers Project</i>]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[procedural agents and literary vectors]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>317</page_from>
		<page_to>324</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019346</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019346</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p><i>The Readers Project</i> is an aesthetically oriented system of software entities designed to explore the culture of human reading. These entities, or "readers," navigate texts according to specific reading strategies based upon linguistic feature analysis and real-time probability models harvested from search engines. As such, they function as autonomous text generators, writing machines that become visible within and beyond the typographic dimension of the texts on which they operate. Thus far the authors have deployed the system in a number of interactive art installations at which audience members can view the aggregate behavior of the readers on a large screen display and also subscribe, via mobile device, to individual reader outputs. As the structures on which these readers operate are culturally and aesthetically implicated, they shed critical light on a range of institutional practices -- particularly those of reading and writing -- and explore what it means to engage with the literary in digital media.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Linguistics</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>I.7.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor></descriptor>
				<type></type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010497</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Document management and text processing</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010147.10010178.10010179</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Computing methodologies->Artificial intelligence->Natural language processing</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010473</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Language translation</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Human Factors</gt>
			<gt>Measurement</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759708</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100308687]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Daniel]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[C.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Howe]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[City University, Hong Kong, China]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[daniel.c.howe@gmail.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759709</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100521226]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[John]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Cayley]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Brown University, Providence, Rhode Island]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[john_cayley@brown.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[This paper is largely concerned with the details of our project's analytical and computational methods. However these are pursued as integral to a practice of digital literary art, fully within the context of long-standing discussions concerning the interrelation of digital media and "the literary." There is an extensive critical literature on this subject, recently summarized and extended, although from a relatively theoretical perspective, in N. Katherine Hayles, <i>Electronic Literature: New Horizons for the Literary</i> (Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame, 2008).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[M. Gardner, "The Fantastic Combinations of John Conway's New Solitaire Game of `Life'," <i>Scientific American</i>, 223, 120--123 (1970).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[In fact, this is historically/culturally determined, a function of the fact that the z-dimension happens to have had little or no significance for the graphic representation of language, or at best only marginal significance, for reasons associated with the media-support for graphic language that have been available to date. This situation could change and, arguably, is now changing as it becomes ever easier to make the z-dimension perceptible within devices that represent graphic language. Note also that in sign language the z-dimension is significant, "phonologically" in the technical linguistic sense, and in other grammatical ways as well.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[This phrase is intended to invoke both the natural language processing research that underlies our project and also the concept of "expressive processing" as vital aspects of much contemporary aesthetic practice, including literary practice, as elaborated by Noah Wardrip-Fruin, <i>Expressive Processing: Digital Fictions, Computer Games, and Software Studies</i> (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2009).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1690045</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1689599</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[See D. Ashlock and J. Tsang, "Evolved Art Via Control of Cellular Automata," <i>Proceedings of the Eleventh Conference on Congress on Evolutionary Computation</i> (Piscataway, NJ: IEEE Press, 2009) 3338--3344; D. Burraston and E. Edmonds, <i>Cellular Automata in Generative Electronic Music and Sonic Art: Historical and Technical Review</i> (Sydney: Creativity and Cognition Studios, Faculty of Information Technology, University of Technology, 2005); Kenneth E. Perry, "Abstract Mathematical Art," <i>Byte</i>, December 1986, 181--190 (1986); and Mitchell Whitelaw, <i>Metacreation: Art and Artificial Life</i> (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2004).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[One might also pre-process texts so as to be able to extract other cellular properties that are not regularly represented in traditional orthography, such as phonemes, morphemes, syllables, etc. As will be clear from our description, while the identity of cells is based on traditional orthographic and typographic distinctions, the strategies and behaviors of particular readers are often based on features extracted by computational analysis of the supply texts. Rhyme, which is based on phonemic analysis, represents one of many such examples.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Although we would appreciate connecting our aesthetic research more rigorously with, for example, studies of reading in cognitive science, such relations are only loosely suggested here. The authors are nonetheless involved with UK ARHC-funded research network Poetry Beyond Text, based at the Universities of Dundee and Kent, in which both cognitive scientists concerned with reading and even cognitive aestheticians have a role. See: projects.beyondtext.ac.uk/poetrybeyondtext/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[We use "vector" in a figurative sense, related to its definition as: a quantity (e.g., of directed force or attention) that can be resolved into components. "Vector" also provides us with a noun that can refer to what is really, in this case, a potential direction for the choice of a next word to be read.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[The term "poetics" is used here to encompass any property or method of language that may be composed for rhetorical or aesthetic effect.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[We are aware that there is much sophisticated discussion of the interrelation between typography and semantics, typography and literary aesthetics, and so on. Johanna Drucker's work is exemplary in this regard. Nonetheless, we believe that the distinction proposed here is both novel and critically generative. J. Drucker, <i>The Visible Word: Experimental Typography and Modern Art, 1909--1923</i> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1994).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[For precise details of the current definition, please see: thereadersproject.org?p=contents/neighborhood.html. In our scheme -- as a refection of traditional left-to-right reading in the West -- the NE and SE neighbors will not be null where there are lines of type above or below the current word. The NW, N, SW, and S positions may, however, be null, depending on relative word-lengths.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[E. F. Moore, "Machine Models of Self-Reproduction," <i>Proceedings of Symposia in Applied Mathematics</i>, The American Mathematical Society, Volume 14, 17--33 (1962).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. A. Markov, "Classical Text in Translation: An Example of Statistical Investigation of the Text <i>Eugene Onegin</i> Concerning the Connection of Samples in Chains," trans. David Link, <i>Science in Context</i>, 19.4, 591--600 (2006). Online: journals.cambridge.org/production/action/cjoGetFulltext?fullt extid=637500.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[See thereadersproject.org/?p=contents/readers.html. We might also count as implemented a subtle variation of a simple reader, the "writing to be found" reader that was deployed in the <i>Read for us</i> installation, described here: thereadersproject.org/?p=installations/readforus/readforus.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Note that the preprocessed identification of perigrams for a text is carried out chiefly for reasons of efficiency. Often, depending on network constraints, the frequencies of particular phrases are cached in advance rather than being searched in real-time. The extraction of perigrams means that considerably fewer word combinations need be considered and processed.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1640265</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1640233</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[
<i>The Readers Project</i> is written, chiefly, in Processing (processing.org) and Java, and makes use of the RiTa natural language processing library (www.rednoise.org/rita/) developed by Daniel C. Howe. See D. C. Howe, "RiTa: Creativity Support for Computational Literature," <i>C&C '09: Proceeding of the 7th ACM Conference on Creativity and Cognition</i>, Berkeley, October 26--30, 2009 (New York: ACM, 2009) 205--210, retrieved from doi.acm.org/10.1145/1640233. This library also provides objects designed to mine natural language data, in real time, from indexed repositories -- those built by certain of the main internet search engines -- that represent the most extensive corpus of natural language that has ever been available to language art practitioners. The phrases searched are enclosed in double quotes, providing a rough relative frequency for exact word sequences. There are problems with the way that search engines handle punctuation -- whether or not punctuation is considered to break a sequence. (Google, for example, treats punctuation differently in different search portals: all of Google vs. Books.) These problems have been bracketed for the time being.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[We are also able to constrain our searches to, for example, the indices of Google "books," thus disregarding much of the commercially or technically implicated Internet text.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[We believe that the existence of "services" (or pretended cultural vectors) such as those provided by Google, combined with a burgeoning, aesthetically motivated "use" of these services, has profound implications for contemporary artistic practice. Such use also allows artists to engage critically and productively with important socio-economic and political developments in an unprecedented manner. We are unable to address these crucial issues within the scope of this paper, but plan to do so in future contributions.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[For us, one of the attractions of this approach and these procedures is that they may visualize and perform the workings of protosemantic and sublexical linguistic properties -- both traditional poetic properties like rhyme and less-frequently acknowledged properties such as mesostic relations -- highlighting their contribution to literary aesthetics. The role of the protosemantic in <i>The Readers Project</i> must wait for fuller treatment in the future. See: S. McCaffery, <i>Prior to Meaning: The Protosemantic and Poetics</i> (Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 2001).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 The Readers Project: Procedural Agents and Literary Vectors Daniel C. Howe and John Cayley ABSTRACT 
The Readers Project is an aesthetically oriented system of software entities designed to explore the 
culture of human reading. These entities, or readers, navigate texts according to specific reading strategies 
based upon linguistic feature analysis and real-time probability models harvested from search engines. 
As such, they function as autonomous text generators, writing machines that become visible within and 
beyond the typographic dimension of the texts on which they operate. Thus far the authors have deployed 
the system in a number of interactive art installations at which audience members can view the aggregate 
behavior of the readers on a large screen display and also subscribe, via mobile device, to individual 
reader outputs. As the structures on which these readers operate are culturally and aesthetically implicated, 
they shed critical light on a range of institutional practices par­ticularly those of reading and writing 
 and explore what it means to engage with the literary in digital media. Introduction The Readers Project 
was begun in 2009 in response to the question, How might cellular automata play out a game of life or 
rather a game of reading on the (complex) surface of a text? [1] In the best-known form of the game 
of life [2], the grid on which the cellular automata live and die maps out generations of binary distinctions. 
(Figure 1) This grid and the automata s behaviors are one and the same. By contrast, a textual grid is 
inherently complex, bearing all the structure of natural language, despite remaining as graphic representation 
 unambiguously two-dimensional and, indeed, both grid-like and cellular [3]. While certain 2D characteristics 
of visible language may have inspired us to ask our question about reading and cellular automata (CAs), 
we do not claim any regular or formal relationship between CAs and our expressive natural language processing 
[4]. In fact, while cellular automata have proven a productive formalism in a range of art contexts [5], 
there has been surprisingly little experimentation with CAs in the domain of literary art. The Readers 
Project thus represents an initial foray into this interesting and problematic space. The Framework Because 
of the layered and discrete structures of natural language, it is possible to implement cell-based procedural 
readers at any number of levels. A cell might correspond to a letter, a word, a phrase, a sentence, and 
so on, each an atomic unit of a particular structural layer [6]. We chose the typographic word as our 
cellular unit. We define the current word or word being read as a live cell [7]. If a traditional Western 
linear reading is expressed in terms of cellular rules, then we might say that a live word-cell will, 
in each generation, bring to life the cell directly to its right while, itself, dying. A simple reader, 
defined in this way, could be arbitrarily placed on a textual grid and, generation by generation, would 
seem to move from left to right through the text. But what happens when such a reader reaches the rightmost 
word in a line of type on the grid? We may seem to be over-articulating the most simple of operations, 
but even here we discover an interesting and problematic encounter between natural language and the formalized 
vectors of reading [8]. The rules of our simplest automata are determined by a left-to-right culture 
of reading. However, the definition of to the right must be further formalized such that when a live 
cell is at the end of a line, the cell to its right will be the first word of the next line of text 
far to its graphical, if not its literal left. In prose, the notion of end of a line is determined by 
typography, not by grammar or any other aspect of linguistic structure. In poetry, the composition of 
the line and thus the choice of a final word is generally deliberate, represent­ing a correspondence 
between some aspect of poetics (minimally: lineation) and typography. On an arbitrary prose grid however, 
even our simple automaton must be taught to behave in a manner that implies no less than a poetics of 
prose reading, a poetics that allows it (and ourselves) to move from line to line without breaking the 
process of reading itself [9]. The Typographic Dimension As the project has progressed, considerations 
such as these have suggested a distinction between those aspects of typography that are properly the 
concern of graphic design and what we will characterize as the typographic dimension. The latter might 
be thought of as the typographically embodied space necessarily shaped and structured within which 
reading occurs. Another way to recognize this proposed distinction might be to consider typography in 
the graphic design sense as guaranteeing the visual legibility (or visual aestheticization) of linguistic 
elements, whereas the typographic dimension constitutes the space for reading formed from the gathering 
together of all those typographic elements required by a particular piece of written language. Design 
in the service of legibility drives typography as is it usually addressed in graphic design, whereas 
language-as-writing gives rise to a dimension of reading that is necessarily typographic [10]. These 
considerations impressed themselves upon us as we implemented a formal definition of typographic neighborhood. 
In order for procedural readers to navigate, they need to be formally aware of the space within which 
they read. Precisely which words nearby a current live word-cell should be treated as its formal neighbors? 
In answer to this question, we identified, as in the game of life, eight potential neighbors for each 
live word-cell, four of which may be null [11]. We say that this definition is an aspect of the text 
s typographic dimension. It is set out in terms of graphic proximities that are dependent on typographic 
design, but the procedural consequences of the definition are inflections of reading, not graphics. Vectors 
of Reading The first major gesture of The Readers Project is a re-conception of typography as a dimension 
for a cellular automata like game of reading. The project s second significant move is the elabora­tion 
of forces that drive the various vectors of reading for its automata. A majority of these forces are 
derived from the engines of relatively straightforward text analysis and generation, e.g., Markov-chains 
[13], context-free grammars, feature analysis, etc. Effectively, we are re-placing and re-contextualizing 
such engines within, rather than apart from, the structures of their own supply texts. This requires 
our processes to remain responsive to conventional reading and writing even as they disrupt it, since 
the structures within which they operate are culturally and aesthetically implicated. To date, apart 
from the simple reader, five readers with distinct behaviors have been coded and implemented for public 
installations of the Project, with a number of others currently in development [14]. Here we will introduce 
only the Perigram Reader in detail. Nonetheless, this reader highlights both the Project s exploration 
of generative reading in terms of the typographic dimension of visible language, and also the use of 
live or near-live natural language data-mining to animate and direct its vectors of reading. The Perigram 
Reader is a left-to-right reader that also pays attention to its northeast and southeast neighbors, in 
addition to its immediate neighbor to the right. It was designed to be a reader that would progress through 
a text with a broadly traditional trajectory but that might, on occasion, be deflect­ed from a simple 
linear path. It looks in particular at the neighbors (NE and SE) that are ahead of it but on the lines 
above or below. Thus, overall, it maintains a forwards reading impetus. As its game of reading unfolds, 
should either of its non-null neighbors (NE or SE) complete a phrase that is what we call a perigram, 
then that word-cell may be selected, instead of the word to the right. We have defined a perigram as 
a special variety of word-based n-gram (or Markov chain). In a standard word-based n-gram, all possible 
word combinations in the text may be considered and ranked for frequency. Here we define the perigrams 
for a given text to be a subset of these phrases that take typograph­ic neighborhood into account. Our 
current algorithm collects only those combinations of n-words that can be found within a variable reading 
window, generally around 20 words, around the selected word. This definition is intended to include the 
selected word and all words that might possibly be set adjacently, according to standard typographic 
practice [15]. An n-gram sequence composed of perigrams will contain probabilistically assembled phrases 
with a vocabu­lary constrained by the typographic neighborhood, as defined above. It will, thus, contain 
language tending to be more sensitive to the context of the particular passage from which it is assembled. 
As the Perigram Reader moves through a text, it remembers each previously read word and checks its NE 
and SE neighbors as potential next words. (Figure 3) If it finds that a combination of these three words 
(previous, current, and potential next, in order) constitutes a phrase with a frequency above a certain 
threshold (i.e., it has been used previously in natural language to some extent) then its reading path 
may diverge, effectively also generating an alternative text that is, as it were, perigrammatic (See 
Figure 2b). As currently implemented, the Perigram Reader is probabilistically weighted to tend rightwards 
and to proceed steadily through a text, although it does so more quickly than a simple reader would (since 
it tends to jump down to the line below more frequently than it jumps up to the line above). Rather than 
deriving perigrammatic frequency informa­tion solely from the domain of the supply text, for existing 
Readers Project works, we have collected counts from Google and other search engines [16]. This gives 
us a loose but near real-time relative frequency for the phrase, or else an indication, in cases where 
there are no hits, that the phrase searched is not yet within the domain of natural language as currently 
indexed on the Internet [17]. Further, it enables reader behavior to change over time (from installation 
to installation), reflecting continuous changes to the corpus as updated by search engine crawlers [18]. 
Reader Networks Finally, we have developed a mechanism for distributing the readings of each reader. 
Often, when a text has more than one or two readers moving through it, following a particular reader 
s path can become quite difficult for human observers. To address this, each of the words selected by 
a reader can be sent to a server process listening on a local or remote network port. Browsers and other 
custom web clients may then subscribe to particular readers and receive a relatively straightforward, 
linear presentation of their chosen reader on the device they used to subscribe. In this context, any 
of the project s readers can manifest as a relatively straightforward text generator. For human readers 
present at an installation, subscribing to a reader allows them to clarify and focus the reader s generated 
text stream, and to compare this distinct text with the reader s traversal of the original text as visible 
in the main display. The features described above were realized for an installation in the fall of 2010. 
As illustrated in Figures 4 and 5, a large screen with the text laid out in book-like opening displayed 
up to four distinct readers traversing the text. The viewer was provided with an interactive console 
which allowed them to select a specific reader for focus, ensuring its presence on the display, even 
as it traversed remote sections of the text. Addi­tionally, at each time-step, all readers sent their 
current words to the server. Audience members with web-enabled devices could then subscribe to any of 
the four available streams. At the installation site, these four streams were shown on four wall-mounted 
iPad displays, as seen in Figures 6 and 7. Further developing the project s relationship to cellular 
automata, we have also experimented with what we call Spawning Readers. A Spawn­ing Reader is a reader 
that, in addition to the capabilities described above, can spawn other readers in its neighborhood. Whether 
it spawns or not can depend on any number of criteria. For example, we have implemented a reader that 
spawns when individual words in its neighborhood complete a perigram. This may happen in any direction 
except the direction in which the spawning reader is itself moving. So far we have implemented a Simple 
Spawning Reader, one that moves through the text like the Simple Reader described above. In prin­ciple, 
readers of any type might be generated by a Spawning Reader, and its spawned readers, in turn, might 
be fertile, that is, capable themselves of spawning. (Figure 8) This would quickly produce a highly complex 
visual display. Thus, spawned readers may be configured to live only for a limited number of time-steps 
before dying. For example, our current Simple Spawning Reader produces infertile Perigram Readers that 
are constrained to move in the direction in which they were spawned. They can only continue to exist 
if they find further perigrams in this direction. In the typographic space of conventional prose this 
means that they will usually die within three generations or less. Discussion The attempt to apply a 
formal construct like cellular automata to the act of reading has forced us to rethink the nature and 
complexities of the inscribed surface. The requirement to map this surface onto a cellular grid has led 
us to the perhaps surprising realization that it is structured, in the first instance, typographically 
 not stylistically, and not grammatically. Further, our articulation of the behaviors for our readers, 
even simple readers, has forced us to recall that the typographic dimension of inscribed language is 
structured by its material cultural history, leading us to derive somewhat counter-intuitive notions 
of properties such as proximity and neighborhood, when speaking of typeset words. It appears that the 
possibility of playing off typographic relations between words and their other linguistic, stylistic, 
and poetic relations offers much in the way of literary aesthetic potential. For example, consider the 
relationship between linguistic collocation and typographic neighborhood. Collocation and simple reading 
not only correspond in typography; typography is, precisely, one of the primary mecha­nisms wherein the 
collocations of conventional written text are constituted. If readers look for alternative collocations 
in the typographic neighbor­hood of a word, the conventional correspondences will be challenged and new 
sequences with collocational, and perhaps even literary, momentum are proposed. Even the slight divergences 
of the Perigram Reader generate tensions and literary potentials between the collocations of simple reading 
and the alternates that it discovers. The Project s readers can, and do, look for other relations between 
words alliteration, assonance, rhyme, grammatical or semantic features, shared letters, indeed any stylistic 
feature or linguistic property that are within a word-cell s visible range, allowing each reader to 
discern a vast number of potential reading paths through the typographic space of the text. This process 
amounts to no less than a dynamic visualization of poetics [19]. Conclusions The Readers Project is explicit 
in its address to the institution of reading. By visualizing alternative vectors for reading, it both 
celebrates and critiques this institution. As described above, it also reveals and articulates a relatively 
neglected but vital aspect of this institution, the typographic dimension. The project focuses on typography 
as a space for reading and writing rather than on what it usually signifies: those far less neglected 
niceties surrounding the graphical representation of linguistic substance; that is to say, typographic 
design. The Readers Project asserts the impor­tance of typography in the practices of reading and writing, 
rather than simply illustrating how the traces of these practices are manifest in the world. Less explicitly, 
the Project also concerns itself with the institution and practices of writing, both presenting an alternative 
vision of text generation and reflecting on writing that may be discovered within or as emergent from 
prior writing that is, with writing as performative reading. References and Notes 1. This paper is largely 
concerned with the details of our project s analytical and computational methods. However these are pursued 
as integral to a practice of digital literary art, fully within the context of long-standing discussions 
concerning the interrelation of digital media and the literary. There is an extensive critical literature 
on this subject, recently summarized and extended, although from a relatively theoretical perspective, 
in N. Katherine Hayles, Electronic Literature: New Horizons for the Literary (Notre Dame: University 
of Notre Dame, 2008). 2. M. Gardner, The Fantastic Combinations of John Conway s New Solitaire Game of 
Life , Scientific American, 223, 120 123 (1970). 3. In fact, this is historically/culturally determined, 
a function of the fact that the z-dimension happens to have had little or no significance for the graphic 
representation of language, or at best only marginal significance, for reasons associated with the media-support 
for graphic language that have been available to date. This situation could change and, arguably, is 
now changing as it becomes ever easier to make the z-dimension perceptible within devices that represent 
graphic language. Note also that in sign language the z-dimension is significant, phonologically in the 
technical linguistic sense, and in other grammatical ways as well. 4. This phrase is intended to invoke 
both the natural language processing research that underlies our project and also the concept of expressive 
processing as vital aspects of much contemporary aesthetic practice, including literary practice, as 
elaborated by Noah Wardrip-Fruin, Expressive Processing: Digital Fictions, Computer Games, and Software 
Studies (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2009). 5. See D. Ashlock and J. Tsang, Evolved Art Via Control of Cellular 
Automata, Proceedings of the Eleventh Conference on Congress on Evolutionary Computation (Piscataway, 
NJ: IEEE Press, 2009) 3338 3344; D. Burraston and E. Edmonds, Cellular Automata in Generative Electronic 
Music and Sonic Art: Historical and Technical Review (Sydney: Creativity and Cognition Studios, Faculty 
of Information Technology, University of Technology, 2005); Kenneth E. Perry, Abstract Mathematical Art, 
Byte, December 1986, 181 190 (1986); and Mitchell Whitelaw, Metacreation: Art and Artificial Life (Cambridge: 
MIT Press, 2004). 6. One might also pre-process texts so as to be able to extract other cellular properties 
that are not regularly represented in traditional orthography, such as phonemes, morphemes, syllables, 
etc. As will be clear from our description, while the identity of cells is based on traditional orthographic 
and typographic distinctions, the strategies and behaviors of particular readers are often based on features 
extracted by computational analysis of the supply texts. Rhyme, which is based on phonemic analysis, 
represents one of many such examples. 7. Although we would appreciate connecting our aesthetic research 
more rigorously with, for example, studies of reading in cognitive science, such relations are only loosely 
suggested here. The authors are nonetheless involved with UK ARHC-funded research network Poetry Beyond 
Text, based at the Universities of Dundee and Kent, in which both cognitive scientists concerned with 
reading and even cognitive aestheticians have a role. See: projects.beyondtext.ac.uk/poetrybeyondtext/. 
8. We use vector in a figurative sense, related to its definition as: a quantity (e.g., of directed force 
or attention) that can be resolved into components. Vector also provides us with a noun that can refer 
to what is really, in this case, a potential direction for the choice of a next word to be read. 9. The 
term poetics is used here to encompass any property or method of language that may be composed for rhetorical 
or aesthetic effect. 10. We are aware that there is much sophisticated discussion of the interrelation 
between typography and semantics, typography and literary aesthetics, and so on. Johanna Drucker s work 
is exemplary in this regard. Nonetheless, we believe that the distinction proposed here is both novel 
and critically generative. J. Drucker, The Visible Word: Experimental Typography and Modern Art, 1909 
1923 (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1994). 11. For precise details of the current definition, 
please see: thereadersproject.org?p=contents/neighborhood.html. In our scheme as a reflection of traditional 
left-to-right reading in the West the NE and SE neighbors will not be null where there are lines of 
type above or below the current word. The NW, N, SW, and S positions may, however, be null, depending 
on relative word-lengths. 12. E. F. Moore, Machine Models of Self-Reproduction, Proceedings of Symposia 
in Applied Mathematics, The American Mathematical Society, Volume 14, 17 33 (1962). 13. A. A. Markov, 
Classical Text in Translation: An Example of Statistical Investigation of the Text Eugene Onegin Concerning 
the Connection of Samples in Chains, trans. David Link, Science in Context, 19.4, 591 600 (2006). Online: 
journals.cambridge.org/production/action/cjoGetFulltext?fulltextid=637500. 14. See thereadersproject.org/?p=contents/readers.html. 
We might also count as implemented a subtle variation of a simple reader, the writing to be found reader 
that was deployed in the Read for us installation, described here: thereadersproject.org/?p=installations/readforus/readforus.html. 
15. Note that the preprocessed identification of perigrams for a text is carried out chiefly for reasons 
of efficiency. Often, depending on network constraints, the frequencies of particular phrases are cached 
in advance rather than being searched in real-time. The extraction of perigrams means that considerably 
fewer word combinations need be considered and processed. 16. The Readers Project is written, chiefly, 
in Processing (processing.org) and Java, and makes use of the RiTa natural language processing library 
(www.rednoise.org/rita/) developed by Daniel C. Howe. See D. C. Howe, RiTa: Creativity Support for Computational 
Literature, C&#38;C '09: Proceeding of the 7th ACM Conference on Creativity and Cognition, Berkeley, 
October 26 30, 2009 (New York: ACM, 2009) 205 210, retrieved from doi.acm.org/10.1145/1640233. This library 
also provides objects designed to mine natural language data, in real time, from indexed repositories 
 those built by certain of the main internet search engines that represent the most extensive corpus 
of natural language that has ever been available to language art practitioners. The phrases searched 
are enclosed in double quotes, providing a rough relative frequency for exact word sequences. There are 
problems with the way that search engines handle punctuation whether or not punctuation is considered 
to break a sequence. (Google, for example, treats punctuation differently in different search portals: 
all of Google vs. Books.) These problems have been bracketed for the time being. 17. We are also able 
to constrain our searches to, for example, the indices of Google books, thus disregarding much of the 
commercially or technically implicated Internet text. 18. We believe that the existence of services (or 
pretended cultural vectors) such as those provided by Google, combined with a burgeoning, aesthetically 
motivated use of these services, has profound implications for contemporary artistic practice. Such use 
also allows artists to engage critically and productively with important socio-economic and political 
developments in an unprecedented manner. We are unable to address these crucial issues within the scope 
of this paper, but plan to do so in future contributions. 19. For us, one of the attractions of this 
approach and these procedures is that they may visualize and perform the workings of protosemantic and 
sublexical linguistic properties both traditional poetic properties like rhyme and less-frequently acknowledged 
properties such as mesostic relations highlighting their contribution to literary aesthetics. The role 
of the protosemantic in The Readers Project must wait for fuller treatment in the future. See: S. McCaffery, 
Prior to Meaning: The Protosemantic and Poetics (Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 2001). 
 Daniel C. Howe City University, Hong Kong City University Hong Kong China daniel.c.howe@gmail.com John 
Cayley Brown University Providence, Rhode Island USA john_cayley@brown.edu  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, 
pp. 317 324, 2011  |  &#38;#169; 2011 Daniel C. Howe and John Cayley 317  Figure 1. Created by Daniel 
C. Howe using Conway s Game of Life. &#38;#169; 2010 Daniel C. Howe.  Figure 2: The layout (a) of the 
traditional Moore neighborhood [12] as generally employed in the game of life, contrasted with the typo­graphic 
neighborhood (b) for a textual grid. Note that neither eyes nor and are included in the neighborhood 
due to their lack, in this example, of vertical overlap with the selected word below. The word others 
is considered to occupy the NE neighbor position, while the NW position is null. &#38;#169; 2010 Daniel 
C. Howe.  Howe and Cayley  |  The Readers Project 318  Figure 3: A Perigram Reader moving (a) through 
Poetic Caption, a text written as a caption for the project. Sample output (b) from the reader moving 
through this same text. As even 2D cellular automata generally have simple visual characteristics, our 
read­ers are coded with a variety of configurable visual behaviors that have become an im­portant aspect 
of the Project s aesthetics. For the Perigram Reader (a), we highlight its divergent path through the 
text in a distinct color and shading, with a gradual return to full color and opacity over time. &#38;#169; 
2010 John Cayley.  The Readers Project |  Howe and Cayley 319  Figure 4: Read for us, an installation 
from The Readers Project at the David Winton Bell Gallery, Brown University, December 2010. &#38;#169; 
2010 Danny Cannizzaro.  Figure 5: A networked Mesostic Reader s output displayed on an iPhone. This 
reader is reading through a text, looking beyond its neighborhood in order to find words from the text 
that spell out, mesostically, the phrase It s over, it s done, [in aligned capitalized letters] I ve 
had the image. &#38;#169; 2010 John Cayley.  Howe and Cayley  |  The Readers Project 320  Figure 
6: Main display, console, and iPad displays at the installa­tion from The Readers Project at Pixilerations 
[v.7], Providence, Rhode Island, October 2010. &#38;#169; 2010 John Cayley.  Figure 7: The output of 
three separate Readers, presented on networked iPad displays. &#38;#169; 2010 John Cayley.  The Readers 
Project |  Howe and Cayley 321  Figure 8: Poetic Caption (see Figure 2) with a Perigram Reader (white) 
moving through it and a fertile Simple Reader (ochre) that is spawning infertile Directional Perigram 
Readers (gray) in all neighboring directions, except west and east (the Simple Reader s preceding and 
following) words. &#38;#169; 2010 Daniel C. Howe.  Howe and Cayley  |  The Readers Project 322  
The Readers Project |  Howe and Cayley 323  Howe and Cayley  |  The Readers Project 324  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019347</article_id>
		<sort_key>50</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>9</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>4</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Shadow awareness]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[enhancing theater space through the mutual projection of images on a connective slit screen]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>325</page_from>
		<page_to>333</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019347</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019347</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>This study discusses media technology that enables the continuous creation of performers' physical improvisation as inspired by the refection of imagery evoked from the audience. To realize this, the authors have focused on "shadow media," which promote the continuous creation of imagery through "bodily awareness." The authors have developed a system that can project shadows of the performers in various ways, which are then transformed into various shapes and colors. The shadows are connected to the performers' feet and projected on a "passable" slit screen set up between the stage and the audience. As a result, the interactive and mutual creation of imagery by performers and audience can form an "empathetic" stage. To demonstrate its validity, the authors applied the system to a dance performance at Festival della Scienza in Genoa, Italy.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>I.4.9</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010147.10010178.10010224.10010225</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Computing methodologies->Artificial intelligence->Computer vision->Computer vision tasks</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Human Factors</gt>
			<gt>Measurement</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759710</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100275090]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Yoshiyuki]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Miwa]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Educator/Researcher, Okubo, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo, Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[miwa@waseda.jp]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759711</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81460641341]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Shiroh]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Itai]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Researcher, Okubo, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo, Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[itai@fuji.waseda.jp]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759712</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81442609823]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Takabumi]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Watanabe]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Researcher, Okubo, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo, Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[takabumi@fuji.waseda.jp]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759713</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81442612017]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Hiroko]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Nishi]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Educator/Researcher, Mihocho, Midori-ku Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[hiroko@toyoeiwa.ac.jp]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[E. Huhtamo, "Elements of Screenology: Toward an Archaeology of the Screen," <i>International Studies of the Modern Image</i>, Vol. 7, 31--82 (2004).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[B. James, <i>On Thrones of Gold: Tree Javanese Shadow Plays</i> (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1970).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[L. Danforth, "Humour and Status Reversal in Greek Shadow Theatre," <i>Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies</i>, Vol. 2, 99--111 (1976).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1601186</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1601159</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Y. Miwa, et al., "Shadow Awareness: Bodily Expression Supporting System with Use of Artificial Shadow," <i>Human-Computer Interaction, HCII 2009, Part II</i>, LNCS 5611, 226--235 (2009).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[K. Iida, et al., "Supporting for Creation of Bodily Expression in a Group Activity with Shadow Media," <i>Proceedings of HIS 2010</i> (2010) 91--94.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>796118</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>520809</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[S. Fels and K. Mase, "Iamascope: A Musical Application for Image Processing," <i>Proceedings of FG1998</i> (1998) 610--615.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Nicolai and M. Peljhan, "Polarm," <i>YCAM</i> (2010) polar-m.ycam.jp/index_en.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[W. Muench and K. Furukawa, "Bubbles," <i>ZKM</i> (2000) hosting.zkm.de/wmuench/bubbles.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[J. Lewis, et al., "Night Lights" (2010) yesyesno.com/night-lights.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[MSNBC, "NewsBreaker" (2007) www.msnbc.msn.com/id/24114408/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[L. Candy and E. Edmonds, "Interaction in Art and Technology," <i>Crossings: Electronic Journal of Art and Technology</i>, Vol. 2, Issue 1 (2002) crossings.tcd.ie/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[M. Krueger, <i>Artificial Reality 2</i> (Boston: Addison-Wesley Professional, 1991).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[K. Vincs and J. McCormick, "Touching Space: Using Motion Capture and Stereo Projection to Create a `Virtual Haptics' of Dance," <i>Leonardo</i>, Vol. 43, No. 4, 359--366 (2010).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[D. Manabe, "True," <i>YCAM</i> (2007) www.youtube.com/watch?v=xG6rBB4VYJ0&feature=player_embedded#at=44.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[J. Watanabe, et al., "Test-patches" (2001) www.66bcell.com/test-patches-1/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Camurri, et al., "Mappe per Affetti Erranti: A Multimodal System for Social Active Listening and Expressive Performance," <i>Proceedings of New Interfaces for Musical Expression</i> (2008).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1031685</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1031607</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Y. Miwa and C. Ishibiki, "Shadow Communication: System for Embodied Interaction with Remote Partners," <i>Proceedings of CSCW 2004</i> (2004) 467--476.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[J. Bitton, "Flirting Across a Distance: How a Screen Creates Intimacy with the Shadow," <i>Ambidextrous</i>, Fall 2008, 32--33 (2008).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[R. Wechsler, F. Wei&#223;, and P. Dowling, "EyeCon -- A Motion Sensing Tool for Creating Interactive Dance, Music and Video Projections," <i>Proceedings of the Society for the Study of Artificial Intelligence and the Simulation of Behavior and Cognition</i> (Leeds: University of Leeds, 2004).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>20</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[M. Fern&#225;ndez, "Illuminating Embodiment: Rafael Lozano-Hemmer's Relational Architectures," <i>4dsocial: Interactive Design Environments</i>, ed. L. Bullivant, AD Architectural Design, 78--87 (2007).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Shadow Awareness: Enhancing Theater Space Through the Mutual Projection of Images on a Connective Slit 
Screen Yoshiyuki Miwa, Shiroh Itai, Takabumi Watanabe, Hiroko Nishi ABSTRACT This study discusses media 
technology that enables the continuous creation of performers physical improvisation as inspired by the 
reflection of imagery evoked from the audience. To realize this, the authors have focused on shadow media, 
which promote the continuous creation of imagery through bodily awareness. The authors have developed 
a system that can project shadows of the performers in various ways, which are then transformed into 
various shapes and colors. The shadows are con­nected to the performers feet and projected on a passable 
slit screen set up between the stage and the audience. As a result, the interactive and mutual creation 
of imagery by performers and audience can form an empathetic stage. To demonstrate its validity, the 
authors applied the system to a dance performance at Festival della Scienza in Genoa, Italy. Introduction 
We know from experience that stage performers can express a very evocative narrative by integrating reactions 
from the audience. Specifically, the audience s participation can inform and expand the continuity of 
a piece in cases where performers use physical improvisation. However, the relationship between performers 
and audience has not been fully studied in the field of media technology for interactive art and other 
uses. This paper describes the authors work on media that allow performers and audience to interactively 
create a relationship through the use of body and image and the expression of both together during physical 
improvisation. We have experience working on technologies that support physical improvisation. While 
improvising, performers must continuously create new images with their movements. We are interested in 
presenting medium incompleteness, because it is difficult for performers to stimu­late the audience s 
imagination with ever-changing motion unless the media provide incomplete elements, which encourage the 
audience s imaginative participation. In other words, the spatial blanks (yohaku, a Japanese cultural 
concept of incompleteness) create a space for the audience s imagination within the motion. Good examples 
of these are those observed in suiboku-ga (Japanese ink paintings) and Utsushi-e (the Japanese version 
of a magic lantern) in Eastern culture [1], and shadow puppetry [2, 3], which exists in many cultures. 
We also considered the awareness of one s own body to be an important element in the process of continuous 
imagery generation. All this led us to consider the body s shadow. Shadows themselves are incomplete 
media which provide less information than general video media. Another important element of shadows (related 
to the concept of body awareness) is that they are always connected to bodies. A body always casts a 
shadow, yet we are often unaware of our own shadows. Shadows are incom­plete embodied media. In order 
to externalize the effects of the shadows, we devised a means of changing their forms and colors in various 
ways to allow continuous creation of the image and to raise awareness of the performers own bodies. Figure 
1 shows various transformed shadow media we developed (we call this an artificial shadow, which is transformed 
from a real shadow into shadow media ). The interaction between the performers own bodies and the shadow 
media causes them to move naturally in conjunction with soaring images. Also, when a gap between the 
shadow media and their own bodies emerges, the performers become aware of their own inner selves. And 
they can use this gap as the starting point for a new series of physical expressions. Through experiments 
conducted with expert dancers and pre-school children as part of their physical expression education, 
we found various effects of the shadow media [4, 5]. Previous studies have not been concerned with the 
relationship between performers and audi­ence through shadow media. Therefore, in this study, we tried 
to help performers and audience to create a mutual relationship through both body and image. The method 
we used to achieve this was to place a screen that performers can pass through (Figure 2b) at the border 
between the stage and the audience, and to project the performers shadow media on this screen. The audience 
encounters the performers shadow media before encountering the actual performers, and the audience can 
create images in reaction to the performers physical expressions while appreciating the performers shadow 
media. This shadow media projection offers two benefits to the performers as well. First, the performers 
can simultaneously see the audience and their shadow media projected on the screen; in other words, the 
performers can create physical expressions through the shadow media partially in response to the audience. 
This offers a solution to the conventional system shown in Figure 2a, in which performers cannot see 
the screen media and the audience simultaneously. The second benefit is that the performers can use the 
space in front of the audience as well as the space on the stage, which expands the perform­ers physical 
range of expression. The following section describes the details of the system used to project the shadow 
media on the slit screen placed at the border between the stage and the audience. This system was exhibited 
at the Festival della Scienza in Genoa, Italy, and was used in our dance performances and co-cre­ative 
physical expressions shown there. The results of those performances will also be discussed. Slit Screen 
Connecting Audience and Performers This study discusses technology that promotes an interactive relationship 
between performers and their audience; enables performers to create physical expressions while expanding 
their range of imagery through reference to their shadows and in reaction to the audience s existence 
and influence; and enables the audience to generate their own imagery through the shadow media while 
reacting to the performers existence and influence. In order to achieve such results (Figure 2b), it 
is necessary for performers and audience to face each other so that each of them can share the shadow 
media. In order to maintain the inseparable relationship between a body and its shadow media, the projected 
shadow media is connected to the performers feet so that it looks like their actual shadows. Projecting 
a silhouette image on the screen, disconnected from the body, would not be enough. One method by which 
the audience and the performers can share the shadow media while facing each other is to install a transmissive 
screen, which is made of a material, such as scrim or fabric, that allows the background of the stage 
to be seen, at the border between the stage and the audience. However, this method has a few problems: 
the projection on the screen shines through the screen itself and gets cast on the stage floor, and the 
shadow media that is intended to be projected only on the stage floor to show shadows con­nected to the 
performer s feet (for maintaining the inseparable relationship between body and shadow) appears on the 
screen. Therefore, we used a screen with vertical slits (Figure 2) to project the shadow media from the 
audience s side. This slit screen allows the projection of each indi­vidual image to be cast separately 
on the reed-textured screen (slit screen) and the floor (passing through the slits), which solves the 
problems mentioned above. This shadow media projection method also offers the following three advantages: 
(1) The audience can not only see the per­formers projected shadow media, but also their bodies through 
the slit screen. (2) Performers and audience can move back and forth on each side of the stage through 
the physical gaps in the slit screen. This enables the inseparable integration between performers and 
audience. (3) Perceptual completion enables performers and audience to see the incomplete image on the 
slit screen as one cohesive shadow medium, although the image of the shadow media is frag­mented (sliced) 
by the splits. As shown in Figures 3a and 3b, thermal cameras and projectors placed on both sides of 
the slit screen to generate shadow media enable performers to pass through the slit screen and to create 
physical expressions through the shadow media generated on the auditorium and the stage floors. The audience 
can also participate in an ongoing performance (or enter the stage of physical expressions created by 
performers shadow media space ) with their own shadows. This means that performers and audience can 
encounter and interact with each other through the use of shadow media. This system also makes it possible 
to project an image across the entire theater, including the walls and the ceilings above the stage and 
the auditorium enclosing the entire stage and auditorium in the image (Figure 3c). The slit screen can 
expand the stage to the entire theater. Finally, the stage and the auditorium can be integrated. Furthermore, 
as seen in Figure 3d, not only the shadow media, but also the performers actual shadows can be simultaneously 
projected on the screen. Additionally, by projecting different shadow media from two projectors, the 
superimposed (dual) shadow media can be projected on the screen (Figure 3e). In comparison to the existing 
system (Figure 2a), our method expands the range of physical expressions through the use of shadow media. 
Thus, this system can be considered as an example of Eastern interac­tive media art. It projects shadow 
media on the slit screen which will bring about a spatial expansion and a sense of depth. In other words, 
this system provides yohaku, which is often seen in suiboku-ga Japanese ink paintings, enabling the audience 
and performers to create imagery together. In general, interactive art that invites audience participation 
has focused on supporting direct interaction between an audience and a fixed artwork [6-10]. It has focused 
attention on the relationship between audience and artwork [11]. Myron Krueger, the famous researcher 
of interactive art, originated the focus on the relationship between performers and audience [12]. He 
argues that art s future direction is art created by the interaction between performers and audience. 
He proposes that performers interact with the audience by projecting silhouettes of both performers and 
audience in the shared visual environment of the video space he developed. However, in his concept, the 
space where performers and audience interact is virtual shared, but only virtual not a shared real 
environment. There are many technologies, such as those often used in traditional stage settings, that 
heighten performers expressions by applying a special effect to either the stage space or the performer 
[13-16]; or that inseparably enhance the audience s rapport with the performers, such as waving penlights 
at concerts. In contrast, our new system, which enhances the relationship between performers and audience 
through their physical interactions in a real space, is the first attempt of its kind in the technological 
media field. This study attempts to apply technology to achieve interaction through shadow media that 
can stimulate the audience and performers to create images collaboratively. Shadow media are widely used 
in the human-interaction field to support interaction between humans. For example, there is the remote 
communication system (WSCS) [17] that enables the positioning of oneself and a remote partner in one 
s own physical location by exchanging the physical shadow of both participants between remote locations, 
and projecting the mutual shadows from each partici­pant s location. The WSCS interaction system generates 
a situation where, in effect, the participants are actually talking to each other face-to-face. There 
are also several research programs, such as Passages (Bitton), that attempt to support remote communication 
by project­ing the shadow silhouettes of remote participants on a screen [18]. The Palindrome dance company 
has conducted performances using performers shadows to enhance their physical expression [19]; and Lozano-Hemmer 
has presented an installation in which a video image emerges from one s own shadow in an outdoor space 
[20], demonstrating that participants can play improvisationally with the help of their shadows. As a 
result, he successfully transformed a space that people pass through into a space where they meet and 
play. Among these projects in other arts, our research will be the first use of shadow media to position 
an audience on the stage and support the co-creation of the image, focusing on the relationship between 
performer and audience. System for Generating and Projecting Shadow Media on Slit Screen This section 
describes the system used for projecting the shadow media on the slit screen. As seen in Figure 3, this 
system can project shadow media on the slit screen in a variety of ways. The basic shadow media projection 
method projects the shadow media of a person standing in the performer s stage space. The system s structure 
is shown in Figure 4. First, the system creates the shadow media by acquiring a thermal image via a thermal 
camera located at the back of the stage, extracting the body s region, which has a different temperature 
from the surroundings, and processing this image with a computer. Assuming that the shadow media s light 
source is located in the position of the thermal camera, projecting this shadow media onto the performer 
s feet ensures a geometric consistency between the body shape and the shadow media. In this case, to 
avoid having the performer s actual shadows projected on the slit screen, the projector is situated on 
the side of the audience, and the shadow media stretching from the performer s feet must be projected 
onto the screen as well as the stage floor beyond the screen. The projected image must be divided into 
two sections: one projected onto the screen, and the other onto the stage floor. Each section is subjected 
to projective transformation for projecting on the screen or on the stage floor. In other words, the 
projected image is a composite of two images with alternate vertical stripes (Figure 4). This composite 
shadow is projected from the audience s side. The slit screen is made of polyester, which enables rear 
projection. Thus, this system can simulta­neously project shadow media on the floor (to recreate a shadow 
stretching from the performer s feet) and on the slit screen. Although the shadow media system developed 
in the past had to be installed on the ceiling as a projecting source, the current projecting method 
does not require installation of projectors on the ceiling. This is quite beneficial because it halves 
the number of projectors required. Furthermore, as mentioned above, we can project the audience s shadow 
media by bilaterally and symmetrically arranging the new shadow media projection system with a central 
focus on the slit screen. Exhibiting the System This system was exhibited at the Festival della Scienza 
in Genoa (October 29 to November 7, 2010). This festival showcases communication through science, boasts 
participants of all ages and nationalities, and offers an opportunity for scientists and artists to create 
communities of practice. The Palazzo della Borsa, where the system was exhibited, was a circular space 
with a flat floor 25 meters in diameter. We set up the slit screen, which was four meters high and 10 
meters wide, in the center of this space, making one part of the space a stage for the performers and 
the other a space for the audience. The opaque elements and the slits were, respectively, 10 and 12 centimeters 
wide. Each width was determined by conducting several experiments to see if audiences could see both 
shadow media projected on the slit screen and the performers behind the slit screen. We produced a performance 
titled Dual 2010, which integrated shadow media and physical expression with the theme Ancestors plant 
trees, descendants rest under the trees. We also conducted lectures on the system s technology. The system 
was open to the public, and we offered visitors an opportunity to experience this system freely. The 
dance performance and the lectures on the technology, as well as several scenes from participatory exhibitions, 
can be seen in Figures 5 and 6. It was recognized that this system can project the shadow media of people 
on either the near or far side of the slit screen. Figures 5 and 6 also show that the shadow media are 
connected to the performers feet. During the actual dance performance, we observed that the motion of 
children in the audience was elicited while performers showed physical expressions through the change 
of shadow media. And, at the end of the dance performance, the audience entered the shadow media stage 
space and created an embracing stage with the performers. Comments from the audiences included remarks 
such as, I could feel a sense of involvement with the scene expressed through the shadow media, which 
yielded an exchange of minds among the performers and the audience members, along with the storyline 
of the performance. During our exhibition, we observed interactions between per­formers and audience 
across the slit screen. Children in particular often ran between the stage and the audience area, playing 
in an improvisational way through the shadow media (Figure 7). We have been discussing our dance performance 
and exhibitions in Genoa so far. Their results indicate that the shadow media projected on the slit screen 
can work as a stage setting to create a scene where the performers and the audience can feel as if they 
were integrated as one large expression. Therefore, we think that this system has the potential to support 
empathic interac­tions between performers and audience. More than 2,500 people visited the shadow system 
exhibition at the Festival della Scienza in Genoa. It was extremely well received, and the Dual 2010 
performance was featured on the festival s official web site and in the local media. Conclusion The present 
study discusses media technology that enables performers and audience to interac­tively create a mutual 
relationship through both body and image, and mutual expression through physical improvisation. Specifically, 
this study invents and implements the method of projecting shadow media through a transmissive slit screen 
placed at the border between the stage and the auditorium, transforming a body s shadow form. We have 
developed the system in which performer and audience face each other, and in which the shadow media and 
the perform­ers themselves can be seen simultaneously. We have also applied our newly invented method 
of projecting the shadow media onto the slit screen with the shadow media connected to the performers 
feet. In addition, projecting shadow media from both sides of the slit screen can accommodate the audience 
s shadow media as well as the performers , enabling the audience and the performers to share a common 
stage with the help of the projections on the screen. This system can also be used to project shadow 
media across the entire theater space. At the public exhibition of this system at Festival della Scienza 
in Genoa, which attracted considerable attention, performers and audience interacted to create a series 
of continuous narrative physical expressions, while the performers became aware of their own bodies and 
the effect of the audience. From these observations, we conclude that this system has potential as an 
interactive expressive media system that achieves co-creative physical expression. Acknowledgments This 
study was conducted as part of the project Generation and Control Technology of Human-Entrained Embodied 
Media, and is supported by CREST of JST; the research project Principle of Emergence for Empathetic Ba 
and its Applicability to Communication Technology by RISE (Waseda University); and the GCOE program Global 
Robot Academia. We would like to express our sincere thanks to Professor T. Watanabe (Okayama Prefectural 
University), Professor S. Hashimoto (Waseda University), Dr. H. Harashima (Professor Emeritus, University 
of Tokyo), Associate Professor A. Camurri (University of Genoa), and Professor M. Kusahara (Waseda University). 
Thanks are also due to K. Iida, H. Watanabe, and R. Okiyama, graduate students at Miwa Laboratory (Waseda 
University), for their support. References 1. E. Huhtamo, Elements of Screenology: Toward an Archaeology 
of the Screen, International Studies of the Modern Image, Vol. 7, 31 82 (2004). 2. B. James, On Thrones 
of Gold: Three Javanese Shadow Plays (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1970). 3. L. Danforth, Humour 
and Status Reversal in Greek Shadow Theatre, Byzantine and Modern Greek Studies, Vol. 2, 99 111 (1976). 
4. Y. Miwa, et al., Shadow Awareness: Bodily Expression Supporting System with Use of Artificial Shadow, 
Human-Computer Interaction, HCII 2009, Part II, LNCS 5611, 226 235 (2009). 5. K. Iida, et al., Supporting 
for Creation of Bodily Expression in a Group Activity with Shadow Media, Proceedings of HIS 2010 (2010) 
91 94. 6. S. Fels and K. Mase, Iamascope: A Musical Application for Image Processing, Proceedings of 
FG1998 (1998) 610 615. 7. C. Nicolai and M. Peljhan, Polarm, YCAM (2010) polar-m.ycam.jp/index_en.html. 
8. W. Muench and K. Furukawa, Bubbles, ZKM (2000) hosting.zkm.de/wmuench/bubbles. 9. J. Lewis, et al., 
Night Lights (2010) yesyesno.com/night-lights. 10. MSNBC, NewsBreaker (2007) www.msnbc.msn.com/id/24114408/. 
11. L. Candy and E. Edmonds, Interaction in Art and Technology, Crossings: Electronic Journal of Art 
and Technology, Vol. 2, Issue 1 (2002) crossings.tcd.ie/. 12. M. Krueger, Artificial Reality 2 (Boston: 
Addison-Wesley Professional, 1991). 13. K. Vincs and J. McCormick, Touching Space: Using Motion Capture 
and Stereo Projection to Create a Virtual Haptics of Dance, Leonardo, Vol. 43, No. 4, 359 366 (2010). 
14. D. Manabe, True, YCAM (2007) www.youtube.com/watch?v=xG6rBB4VYJ0&#38;feature=player_embedded#at=44. 
15. J. Watanabe, et al., Test-patches (2001) www.66bcell.com/test-patches-1/. 16. A. Camurri, et al., 
Mappe per Affetti Erranti: A Multimodal System for Social Active Listening and Expressive Performance, 
Proceedings of New Interfaces for Musical Expression (2008). 17. Y. Miwa and C. Ishibiki, Shadow Communication: 
System for Embodied Interaction with Remote Partners, Proceedings of CSCW 2004 (2004) 467 476. 18. J. 
Bitton, Flirting Across a Distance: How a Screen Creates Intimacy with the Shadow, Ambidextrous, Fall 
2008, 32 33 (2008). 19. R. Wechsler, F. Weiß, and P. Dowling, EyeCon A Motion Sensing Tool for Creating 
Interactive Dance, Music and Video Projections, Proceedings of the Society for the Study of Artificial 
Intelligence and the Simulation of Behavior and Cognition (Leeds: University of Leeds, 2004). 20. M. 
Fernández, Illuminating Embodiment: Rafael Lozano-Hemmer s Relational Architectures, 4dsocial: Interactive 
Design Environments, ed. L. Bullivant, AD Architectural Design, 78 87 (2007). Yoshiyuki Miwa Educator/Researcher 
3-4-1 Okubo, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo, Japan miwa@waseda.jp Shiroh Itai Researcher 3-4-1 Okubo, Shinjuku-ku, 
Tokyo, Japan itai@fuji.waseda.jp Takabumi Watanabe Researcher 3-4-1 Okubo, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo, Japan 
takabumi@fuji.waseda.jp Hiroko Nishi Educator/Researcher 32 Mihocho, Midori-ku Yokohama-shi, Kanagawa 
Japan hiroko@toyoeiwa.ac.jp  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 325 333, 2011  |  &#38;#169; 2011 Yoshiyuki 
Miwa, Shiroh Itai, Takabumi Watanabe, Hiroko Nishi 325  Figure 1. Generation of bodily expression through 
the shadow media. &#38;#169; 2010 Yoshiyuki Miwa et al.  Figure 2. The method of projecting the shadow 
media. &#38;#169; 2011 Yoshiyuki Miwa et al.  Miwa et al.  |  Shadow Awareness 326  Shadow Awareness 
 |  Miwa et al. 327  Figure 3. The new method for projecting shadow media images (concept). &#38;#169; 
2011 Yoshiyuki Miwa et al.  Miwa et al.  |  Shadow Awareness 328  Figure 4. The method of projecting 
the shadow media on the slit screen. &#38;#169; 2011 Yoshiyuki Miwa et al.  Shadow Awareness  |  Miwa 
et al. 329  Figure 5. Scenes from Dual 2010 at Festival della Scienza in Genoa. &#38;#169; 2010 Yoshiyuki 
Miwa et al.  Figure 6. Scenes from our public exhibit at Festival della Scienza in Genoa. &#38;#169; 
2010 Yoshiyuki Miwa et al.  Figure 7. Participants going back and forth through the slit screen. &#38;#169; 
2010 Yoshiyuki Miwa et al.  Miwa et al.  |  Shadow Awareness 330  Shadow Awareness |  Miwa et 
al. 331  Miwa et al.  |  Shadow Awareness 332  Shadow Awareness |  Miwa et al. 333  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019348</article_id>
		<sort_key>60</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>12</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>5</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Collaboration with the future]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[an infrastructure for Art+Technology at the San Jos&#233; International Airport]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>334</page_from>
		<page_to>345</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019348</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019348</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>This paper summarizes the development and implementation of a three-part infrastructure for the ongoing program of technology-based public artwork at Silicon Valley's newly expanded airport. The physical, technological, and human infrastructure provides flexibility and opportunities for future artists and future technologies while providing a robust framework for the ongoing maintenance and evolution of the program and mediating between the needs of artists and the constraints of an airport.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>I.3.8</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>I.4.9</cat_node>
				<descriptor></descriptor>
				<type></type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010147.10010178.10010224.10010225</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Computing methodologies->Artificial intelligence->Computer vision->Computer vision tasks</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010147.10010371</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Computing methodologies->Computer graphics</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010497.10010504.10010507</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Document management and text processing->Document capture->Graphics recognition and interpretation</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Human Factors</gt>
			<gt>Measurement</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759714</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100590046]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Matt]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Gorbet]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Educator Gorbet Design, Inc.]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[matt@gorbetdesign.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759715</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487654008]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Susan]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[Lk]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Gorbet]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Educator Gorbet Design, Inc.]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[susan@gorbetdesign.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759716</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81484642241]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Banny]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Banerjee]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Educator Stanford University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[banny@stanford.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Troika, <i>Cloud</i> (2008), retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.troika.uk.com/cloud?image=17.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Moeller, <i>Daisy</i> (2008), retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.christian-moeller.com/display.php?project_id=60.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[C. Janney, <i>Circling</i> (2005), retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.dfwairport.com/art/P1_017254.php.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Electroland, <i>Connection</i> (2008), retrieved March 22, 2011, from electroland.net/projects/connection.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[ARS Electronica Center, retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.aec.at/center_exhibitions_en.php.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Center for Art and Media (ZKM), retrieved January 13, 2011, from on1.zkm.de/zkm/e/about.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[phaeno, retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.phaeno.de/en/index-en.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[NTT InterCommunication Center (ICC), retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.ntticc.or.jp/About/introduction.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[The Rome Group and the San Jos&#233; Office of Cultural Affairs, <i>Norman Y. Mineta San Jos&#233; International Airport Public Art Master Plan</i> (2004), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/SJA_ MasterPlan.pdf.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[
<i>Ibid</i>., p. ii.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[
<i>Ibid</i>., p. 13.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[
<i>Ibid</i>., p. 27.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[
<i>Ibid</i>., p. 26.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Gorbet+Banerjee and the San Jos&#233; Office of Cultural Affairs, <i>Norman Y. Mineta San Jos&#233; International Airport Art Activation Research Report</i> (2005), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/ArtActivationTeamResearchReport805.pdf.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Climate Clock Initiative, City of San Jos&#233; Public Art Program, retrieved March 22, 2011, from sj-climateclock.org/sjpublicart.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Gorbet+Banerjee and the San Jos&#233; Office of Cultural Affairs, <i>Norman Y. Mineta San Jos&#233; International Airport Art Activation Design Development Proposal</i> (2006), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/Mineta_AAAP.pdf.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Gorbet+Banerjee and the San Jos&#233; Office of Cultural Affairs, <i>Norman Y. Mineta San Jos&#233; International Airport Art Activation Design Development Proposal #2 TAIP: Terminal B Phase I/Terminal A</i> (2005), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/AATDDOct07.pdf.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Richmond Sound Design Ltd., Audiobox II, retrieved January 11, 2011, from www.richmondsounddesign.com/audiobox-ii.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Django Software Foundation, Django Web Framework, retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.djangoproject.com/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>20</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Amazon Web Services LLC, Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud, retrieved January 13, 2011, from http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>21</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Twilio, Inc., Twilio Cloud Communications, retrieved January 12, 2011, from www.twilio.com/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>22</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Wikimedia Foundation, Mediawiki, retrieved January 12, 2011, from www.mediawiki.org/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>23</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[S. Dietz, "Collecting New-Media Art: Just Like Anything Else, Only Different," <i>Collecting the New: Museums and Contemporary Art</i>, ed. B. Altshuler (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2005) 85--101, retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.neme.org/524/collecting-new-media-art.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>24</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[A. Depocas, J. Ippolito, and C. Jones, eds., <i>Permanence Through Change: The Variable Media Approach</i> (New York: The Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation and Montr&#233;al: The Daniel Langlois Foundation for Art, Science, and Technology, 2003), retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.variablemedia.net/e/preserving/html/var_pub_index.html.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>25</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[M. Kwon, <i>One Place After Another</i> (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2002), MIT Press paperback edition, 2004, p. 8.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>26</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Brown and Keener Bressi, Via Partnership, and the San Jos&#233; Office of Cultural Affairs, <i>Public Art NEXT! San Jos&#233;'s New Public Art Master Plan</i> (2007), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/PA_Next031307.pdf.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 335 334 Collaboration with the Future: An Infrastructure for Art+Technology at the San José International 
Airport Matt Gorbet, Susan LK Gorbet, Banny Banerjee ABSTRACT This paper summarizes the development and 
implementation of a three-part infrastructure for the ongoing program of technology-based public artwork 
at Silicon Valley s newly expanded airport. The physical, technological, and human infrastructure provides 
flexibility and opportunities for future artists and future technologies while providing a robust framework 
for the ongoing maintenance and evolution of the program and mediating between the needs of artists and 
the constraints of an airport. Introduction The City of San José s Office of Cultural Affairs has established 
an ongoing, rotating program of technology-based and technology-themed public art in conjunction with 
the revitalization of Silicon Valley s Norman Y. Mineta International Airport (SJC). Three major permanent 
art­works and ten short-term (18 24 month) rotating installations make up the first round of Art+Technology 
commissions, launched with the opening of the airport s new terminal in June 2010. Airports that include 
technology-based artwork typically have a small number of individual works [1 4] within more traditional 
public art collections, and any infrastructure installed to support them is designed specifically for 
those pieces. When more general, building-wide infrastructures have been created to support evolving 
collections of technology artwork, these are found in facilities that are dedicated to technology art 
as their primary purpose, such as museums, galleries, and exhibition centers [5 8]. San José Airport 
s Art Activation project brought these two directions together. We created an architecturally integrated 
infrastructure consisting of physical, technological, and human systems to enable the SJC Art+Technology 
program to be robust and extensible within the constraints of a functioning airport. Background Master 
Planning The Airport Public Art Master Plan [9], completed in 2004, defined a framework for a unified 
program of Art+Technology, showcasing the innovation, diversity, and change that defines San José and 
Silicon Valley. The Art+Technology program: Aims to give travelers an immediate sense of San José as 
a place where ideas are born, and reinforce its stature as a creative and tech-savvy city. [10] Art+Technology 
is defined in the Master Plan as: Art that uses technology Art that is inspired by technology Art that 
is developed with technology Art that comments on technology [11] Airport Art Activation The planners 
recognized the need for activating the airport buildings to enable Art+Technology work: Architectural 
Infrastructure A qualified team of artists will be selected to work with the architectural design team 
to identify sites and integrate appropriate accommodations for a program of Art+Technology. [12] The 
City put out a call for artists to form the Airport Art Activation Team. Of 24 qualified international 
submissions, our team was chosen in May 2005. Our mandate was threefold: 1. Work with the airport s design 
team to analyze the architecture, discover opportunities, and integrate the public art infrastructure. 
2. Design and install flexible technological platforms to enable a rotating program of commissioned works. 
The Master Plan established that: Sites within the architecture and/or landscape will be designed as 
flexible Art+Technology platforms to incorporate dynamic projects that rotate over time. [13] 3. Create 
three pilot artworks (of the initial 10) to showcase and test these platforms. Initial Research We investigated 
the airport art program context, speaking with many types of people to gain insight on the role of art 
in an airport and the goals for an enabling infrastructure. The research [14] included: San José Public 
Art Program: Understand public art processes with respect to the commu­nity and to economic development 
plans for San José. Airport Design &#38; Operations: 13 meetings with over 35 airport staff and stakeholders, 
including architects, IT, maintenance, landside and airside operations staff. Art and Technology Field 
Research: Field trips and online research exploring emerging technologies and their use in art and design. 
Airport Observations and Research: Observations and interviews of airport users at SJC, and observations 
at other airports: PHX, YYZ, YYC, DEN, SFO, ORD, BUR, LAS. Artists Input: Research visits to Art+Technology 
shows, public community visioning groups for both traditional and technology artists, an invited roundtable, 
and one-on-one artist interviews. Guiding Principles Collaboration with the Future The most significant 
challenge of activating the airport for technology-based artwork is that technology changes rapidly, 
and there is no way of knowing what tools, media, or genres future artists will be working with. Every 
activation must be thought of as a collaboration with the future: the infrastructure will be part of 
each artist s piece, and therefore must contribute functionally while allowing the largest possible aesthetic 
and thematic flexibility. Integration with Airport Function and Passenger Experience Because this is 
a highly functional space, the art should enhance the existing experience of travelers through the airport 
rather than requiring a detour to view artwork or to visit a gallery. This also means that the infrastructure 
must integrate tightly with the airport architecture, disappearing when not in use. Physical, Technology, 
&#38; Human Systems To create a flexible and sustainable program, the Art+Technology infrastructure must 
provide physical systems, technology systems, and human systems, further detailed in the Curatorial Process 
section of this paper. Platforms Technology Art and Public Art In our research, it became clear that 
in the context of traditional, permanent public art, working with technology is a challenge because it 
is a constantly changing, somewhat ephemeral medium. The flexible platforms are a way to bridge this 
gap and allow artists to create public art with technology. Mediation Between Airport and Artist The 
Art Activation infrastructure enables artists to create art within the airport environment by mediating 
interactions between artists and the airport (Figure 1). Unlike a museum or gallery, many aspects of 
the airport are inflexible, from strict data access and security concerns to physical needs such as wall 
space or power outlets. Negotiating for these needs in advance provides opportunities as well as constraints 
for future artists. (Re-)Defining Platforms While the Master Plan introduced the concept of flexible 
technological platforms, the term was originally understood in the context of media systems that could 
be installed and reused for a variety of content, e.g., screens and playback systems for video art. Rethinking 
the meaning of platform, it became clear that specialized display equipment should be avoided wherever 
possible. These are the most visible and fastest-changing technolo­gies, so they are likely to constrain 
the expression of future artists and quickly obsolesce. Instead, activations focus on the mostly invisible 
infrastructure that connects artworks to airport systems. To give both the art program and the artists 
flexibility, the platforms are conceived of as a kit of parts supplied to artists. These parts take the 
form of simple infrastructure elements located at specified sites within the airport, like hooks and 
power sources, as well as universal elements like flight data and camera inputs. These can then be combined 
in the curatorial process to create the platforms for which art is commissioned. Curatorial Process Though 
this paper focuses on the supporting infrastructure and not the motivations or processes of the overall 
program, it may be useful to understand the curatorial process that led to the current round of commissions. 
The City of San José has a well-defined ideological approach to its public art program: The San José 
Public Art Program strives to select artists versus specific artworks, so that each artwork that is added 
to the City s collection is unique and specifically designed for its site. Community outreach is extensive 
and involvement is encouraged at all levels. [15] Within this framework there is flexibility around the 
specific curatorial approach to take for any given commission. For the first rotating commissions, guest 
curators were invited by the Public Art program to select artists for specific platforms and sites after 
the infrastructure and platforms had been finalized. The artists were selected from a pre-qualified pool 
of artists that is main­tained with a rolling open call. Once commissioned, the airport artists were 
asked to reflect on issues of concern to travelers and the local community and, where possible, to engage 
with the local community in the development of their artworks. As designers of the infrastructure, we 
contributed general curatorial guidelines to this process. We also proposed three of the platforms for 
our own pilot artworks, to showcase the possibili­ties and explore the limits of the infrastructure we 
had designed. The Infrastructure Physical Systems Physical systems such as mounts, power and data ports, 
space for equipment, and display cases provide both ready-made opportunities and guidance for artists 
in their approach to the air­port environment. The physical activations that comprise the Art Activation 
Program are fully detailed in public design development documents [16, 17] created for the project. Following 
are illustrative examples of physical systems in specific locations: Gate Seating Areas In the gate seating 
areas, passengers await their departing aircraft. Power and data are provided in the floors of gate seating 
areas to accommodate custom display cases or sculptural artwork. Ceilings in three of the nineteen gate 
areas include equipment storage and concealed mounting points above the tiles for hanging artwork, projectors, 
sensors, displays, etc. Among the program s first ten rotating commissions are two gate seating area 
works. Dreaming F.I.D.S., by Ben Hooker and Shona Kitchen, is a custom-built aquarium with live fish 
and submerged video displays showing custom graphics and fish-tracking software from underwater cameras 
(Figure 2). The piece uses floor-mounted power and a concealed data jack to remain connected to the network 
for monitoring and maintenance. Another gate seating area features Chronos &#38; Kairos, a ceiling-mounted 
robotic sculpture consisting of 130 paired aluminum arcs that move in choreographed patterns and respond 
to the movement of people below via video tracking (Figure 3). Concealed in the ceiling are power supplies, 
a control computer, and a rigid mounting system. Passenger Bridges Six-channel speakers, data connections, 
audio equipment, and sensors are integrated into the ceilings of passenger boarding bridges, driven by 
a digital audio distribution system [18] to enable context-specific soundscapes (reflecting a particular 
flight s destination or origin, for instance) to be experienced by boarding or deplaning travelers. Curved 
Concourse Wall Large sections of a curved overhead concourse wall are activated with simple, architecturally 
integrated mounting points, enabling art to play a prominent role in creating interest over long distances. 
Standardized threaded inserts provide hanging opportunities. Space for equipment and power are accessible 
from a catwalk behind the wall, and cabling can be passed through distributed openings in the wall. Dedicated 
IP-based video cameras ( ArtCams ) can be flexibly repositioned along the wall, allowing input for active 
artwork located anywhere in the airport, plus visual monitoring of artwork for maintenance. Baggage Claim 
Projection As travelers await their bags, their attention is focused on the moving belt. Projectors and 
a video tracking system integrated into the ceiling allow artists to augment the flowing stream of luggage 
with projected interventions that respond to the presence of the bags. Reactive Wall Centrally located 
between arrivals and departures on the main level is a space outside the restrooms where people often 
stand and wait with their travel companions bags. It is also the wall with the least natural light in 
the airport, due to the low ceiling. Two edge-blended projectors are concealed in the ceiling, and a 
removable front wall with access behind it for equip­ment and sensors enables projected images to react 
to passersby. The first reactive wall commission is a piece by Camille Utterback, Shifting Time. The 
artwork uses tracking from a camera mounted in the ceiling to detect a viewer s location. Video images 
of San José s past and present are juxtaposed in response to people s movements (Figure 4). Showcases 
Two very large showcases (15 long x 5 wide x 8 tall) were designed for the non-ticketed area between 
the ticketing lobby and arrivals. This is the only space where both departing and arriving passengers 
come together. Viewable from all sides, these glass cases (Figure 5) use an architectural support column 
to support the weight of the ceiling, which also provides concealed space for equipment, power and data, 
and lighting controls. They include a false floor and ceiling for cable management, as well as removable 
sliding panels and rails for flexible display opportunities. Another long and shallow display case (48 
long x 8 high x 1 deep) is integrated into the long wall leading to security. This case also incorporates 
concealed, ventilated storage with power and data, as well as removable rear panels and floor for cable 
management. Technology Systems An IT infrastructure enables artworks to connect to data sources for input, 
as well as providing tools for monitoring and maintenance. Art VLAN The SJC airport s integrated network 
is divided into virtual local area networks (VLANs) for the departments and tenants of the facility (e.g., 
airlines, operations, security, concessions). The public art program has its own VLAN that is monitored 
by airport IT staff but configured and maintained by the program to suit the specific needs of artists. 
Access, security and network protocol restrictions were negotiated with the airport IT department during 
the design phase. Every artwork-specific terminal location incorporates CAT-6 data connections to the 
art VLAN, sometimes in unusual places, such as behind ceiling tiles or walls, supporting installation 
of concealed equipment and sensors. Art Server At the heart of the Art VLAN is a Linux-based server aggregating 
data from various sources, including weather data from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration 
(NOAA) and flight information from the Airport Operations Database (AODB). APIs and open-source sample 
scripts for artists use (Figure 6) are provided in multiple programming languages. The Art Server also 
plays a vital maintenance role, controlling peripherals such as IP video cameras and network-enabled 
power switches for easy troubleshooting and remote control of lighting and projectors. Access to the 
Art Server is available on-site or remotely via VPN. A browser-based interface to its functionality has 
been implemented using the Django web framework [19]. Art Cloud To provide flexible functionality without 
full knowledge of future requirements, a second server is implemented using Amazon s EC2 [20] service. 
This server provides access to data about each piece, including regular status-monitoring heartbeats 
(Figure 7). In addition, the Art Cloud provides a gateway between the highly secured on-site Art VLAN 
and third-party web services such as the Twilio [21] telephony application, enabling artists to build 
external application controls for their artwork. Finally, the Art Cloud also hosts a Wiki-based handbook 
for artists, an inventory system, and other documentation for use in administering the Art Program. Human 
Systems An essential part of the Art Activation infrastructure is the human element. Human systems maintain 
and enhance the infrastructure and its capabilities, ensuring the long-term viability of this complex 
and dynamic program in the real-world context of the Airport. Art Technician The Art Technician is an 
individual with a technical background and an understanding of art practice who acts as support for planning, 
installation, and ongoing maintenance of the artwork. This part-time contract position has full understanding 
of the art program IT infrastructure and works to maintain and extend it as the program grows. The Art 
Technician s role includes: Working with artists in advance to help them navigate the airport tech environment 
Helping artists plan technology decisions for easier maintenance and better fit with the airport systems 
Acting as liaison between the art program and the airport IT, Facilities, and Operations Helping with 
installation logistics Monitoring day-to-day status of airport artwork Responding to on-site problems 
with artwork, and contacting artists for troubleshooting Maintaining the Airport Art Program infrastructure, 
including troubleshooting and making changes as needed Updating the inventory system for pieces of the 
Airport Art infrastructure, including current location and status The Art Technician has dedicated office, 
storage, and workbench space at the airport. Airport Art Handbook The Airport Art Handbook informs participating 
artists and other stakeholders, such as program staff, about the infrastructure. From receiving a commission 
to guidelines for creating work in the airport to installation to maintenance, all parts of the process 
are documented. The Hand­book is implemented using MediaWiki [22] to act as an ongoing repository for 
experience gained as the program grows. It is editable by the Art Technician, the OCA staff, and the 
artists. Close Cooperation with Airport Operations The program can only succeed into the future if airport 
staff such as IT personnel, groundside operations, security, and maintenance staff remain aware of the 
artwork, understand its intent and functioning, and know how to work with and around it. The OCA staff 
actively maintain relationships with key advocates at the airport in order to foster a sense of ownership 
and pride in the collection, meaning it will be looked after and promoted. Reflections Though the infrastructure 
and the Art+Technology program are still very new and designed to evolve over time, it is worth noting 
some of the successes and surprises encountered so far. As of this writing, the airport has been open 
for nine months and has been through only one initial round of commissions, so several of the elements, 
such as the integrated API for mobile device interaction and the mounting system on the large Curved 
Concourse Wall, have not yet been used by artists. The first ten rotating and three permanent artworks 
were installed simultaneously with the completion of the building, and in parallel with the final implementation 
of the technology infrastructure. One drawback of this was that maintenance documentation was not initially 
available for all artworks (and is still being compiled for some). Further, the Art Technician was hired 
after installation of the first round of artworks had begun, so he had a lot of learning to do very quickly. 
The collection has experienced understandable maintenance issues with several pieces, in particu­lar 
those with moving parts or water. This was anticipated, and the presence of the Art Technician has been 
enormously helpful, as has the presence of ArtCams and the ArtVLAN for monitoring and remotely diagnosing 
the work. The experimental and dynamic nature of much of the work means that some of the artists have 
continued to contribute, tweaking software parameters and making adjustments to the behavior of their 
pieces. This ongoing relationship is facilitated by the artworks being online and soft­ware-based, and 
raises logistical, contractual, and theoretical questions about when a work is complete. See [23, 24] 
for further general discussion of these issues. In addition to the artworks that are currently installed, 
three other artists were originally offered commissions in the initial round. One artwork was not completed 
due to the artist s lack of time to engage appropriately with the demands of the infrastructure. One 
artwork was not approved by the Public Art Commission in the design development phase due to difficulty 
designing within the required constraints of the platform, and one commissioned work has been delayed 
due to unforeseen technical issues with the artwork. One of the pilot artworks in the collection is also 
likely to undergo revisions, as its impact on the travelling public has not been as strong as desired 
by the artist or by the Public Art program. Such conditions illustrate the need for commissioned artists 
to be aware of the infrastructure s specific constraints, the importance of strong oversight during the 
commissioning and design process, as well as flexibility with man­agement of the work once installed. 
Now that the constraints and possibilities of the infrastructure have become more tangible, it will be 
easier for future curatorial teams to match artists to the platform opportunities. Going forward, there 
are many possible ways for the San José Public Art program to approach commissioning new rounds of artwork 
for the airport (guest curatorial teams can be established, proposals can be solicited, residencies can 
be created, etc.). Every approach has its own ideologi­cal, political, procedural, and practical ramifications. 
We view this as a healthy situation, as curatorial practices, notions of site-specificity and community 
are continuously shifting in public art discourse. Art historian Miwon Kwon describes the resilience 
of the concept of site-specificity, as indicated by its many permutations [25]. In fact, during the course 
of the Art Activation project, San José s Office of Cultural Affairs produced a new master plan for the 
city s Public Art program [26] which recommends new approaches to such issues as site-specificity and 
community engagement. By integrating closely with the architecture, while providing abundant potential 
for bold com­missioning opportunities, the SJC Art Activation infrastructure is designed to accommodate 
flexibility of curatorial and stylistic strategies in addition to ever-changing technological opportunities. 
Conclusions Technology presents artists with ever-evolving opportunities for creative expression, demanding 
a flexible art program that can easily evolve. The practical constraints of a functioning airport, on 
the other hand, demand a high level of standardization, forethought, and structure. The Art Activation 
infrastructure at SJC bridges these two worlds, offering a simple and flexible kit of parts that mediates 
between the structures and systems of the airport and the creative potential of artists. This enables 
new opportunities to enhance the experience of the airport while providing a robust framework for the 
ongoing maintenance and evolution of the program. As the San José Airport Public Art Program evolves 
and embraces different curatorial and aesthetic approaches, we are hopeful and confident that the activation 
infrastructure at the airport will evolve as well, continuing to support meaningful, engaging, and groundbreaking 
work in collaboration with the future. Acknowledgments Special thanks to Mary Rubin, Senior Project 
Manager with the City of San José Office of Cultural Affairs, without whose dedication and creative problem-solving 
the Art Activation project would not have been possible. Thanks also to Barbara Goldstein and to members 
of the Airport Art Program Oversight Committee for their faith in the project s vision and their critical 
input. References 1. Troika, Cloud (2008), retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.troika.uk.com/cloud?image=17. 
2. C. Moeller, Daisy (2008), retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.christian-moeller.com/display.php?project_id=60. 
3. C. Janney, Circling (2005), retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.dfwairport.com/art/P1_017254.php. 4. 
Electroland, Connection (2008), retrieved March 22, 2011, from electroland.net/projects/connection. 5. 
ARS Electronica Center, retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.aec.at/center_exhibitions_en.php. 6. Center 
for Art and Media (ZKM), retrieved January 13, 2011, from on1.zkm.de/zkm/e/about. 7. phaeno, retrieved 
March 22, 2011, from www.phaeno.de/en/index-en.html. 8. NTT InterCommunication Center (ICC), retrieved 
March 22, 2011, from www.ntticc.or.jp/About/introduction.html. 9. The Rome Group and the San José Office 
of Cultural Affairs, Norman Y. Mineta San José International Airport Public Art Master Plan (2004), retrieved 
from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/SJA_MasterPlan.pdf. 10. Ibid., p. ii. 11. Ibid., p. 13. 12. Ibid., 
p. 27. 13. Ibid., p. 26. 14. Gorbet+Banerjee and the San José Office of Cultural Affairs, Norman Y. Mineta 
San José International Airport Art Activation Research Report (2005), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/ArtActivationTeamResearchReport805.pdf. 
15. Climate Clock Initiative, City of San José Public Art Program, retrieved March 22, 2011, from sj-climateclock.org/sjpublicart. 
16. Gorbet+Banerjee and the San José Office of Cultural Affairs, Norman Y. Mineta San José International 
Airport Art Activation Design Development Proposal (2006), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/Mineta_AAAP.pdf. 
17. Gorbet+Banerjee and the San José Office of Cultural Affairs, Norman Y. Mineta San José International 
Airport Art Activation Design Development Proposal #2 TAIP: Terminal B Phase I / Terminal A (2005), retrieved 
from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/AATDDOct07.pdf. 18. Richmond Sound Design Ltd., Audiobox II, retrieved 
January 11, 2011, from www.richmondsounddesign.com/audiobox-ii.html. 19. Django Software Foundation, 
Django Web Framework, retrieved January 13, 2011, from www.djangoproject.com/. 20. Amazon Web Services 
LLC, Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud, retrieved January 13, 2011, from http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/. 21. Twilio, 
Inc., Twilio Cloud Communications, retrieved January 12, 2011, from www.twilio.com/. 22. Wikimedia Foundation, 
Mediawiki, retrieved January 12, 2011, from www.mediawiki.org/. 23. S. Dietz, Collecting New-Media Art: 
Just Like Anything Else, Only Different, Collecting the New: Museums and Contemporary Art, ed. B. Altshuler 
(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2005) 85 101, retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.neme.org/524/collecting-new-media-art. 
24. A. Depocas, J. Ippolito, and C. Jones, eds., Permanence Through Change: The Variable Media Approach 
(New York: The Solomon R. Guggenheim Foundation and Montréal: The Daniel Langlois Foundation for Art, 
Science, and Technology, 2003), retrieved March 22, 2011, from www.variablemedia.net/e/preserving/html/var_pub_index.html. 
25. M. Kwon, One Place After Another (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2002), MIT Press paperback edition, 2004, 
p. 8. 26. Brown and Keener Bressi, Via Partnership, and the San José Office of Cultural Affairs, Public 
Art NEXT! San José s New Public Art Master Plan (2007), retrieved from www.sanjoseculture.org/downloads/PA_Next031307.pdf. 
 Matt Gorbet Designer, Artist, Educator Gorbet Design, Inc. matt@gorbetdesign.com www.gorbetdesign.com 
Susan LK Gorbet Designer, Artist, Educator Gorbet Design, Inc. susan@gorbetdesign.com www.gorbetdesign.com 
Banny Banerjee Designer, Artist, Educator Stanford University banny@stanford.edu dschool.stanford.edu 
 &#38;#169; 2011 Matt Gorbet, Susan LK Gorbet, Banny Banerjee |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 334 
345, 2011 Collaboration with the Future  |  Gorbet et al.  Figure 1. Platforms mediate between the 
constraints of the airport and the needs of the artist. &#38;#169; 2010 Matt Gorbet et al. Gorbet et 
al.  |  Collaboration with the Future Collaboration with the Future  |  Gorbet et al.  Figure 2. 
Dreaming F.I.D.S. by Ben Hooker and Shona Kitchen. Collection of the City of San José. &#38;#169; 2010 
Ben Hooker and Shona Kitchen. Photo &#38;#169; 2010 Daniel Brown. Gorbet et al.  |  Collaboration 
with the Future  Figure 3. Chronos &#38; Kairos by Banny Banerjee, Matt Gorbet, Susan LK Gorbet, and 
Margaret Orth. Collection of the City of San José. &#38;#169; 2010 Banny Banerjee et al. Photo &#38;#169; 
2010 James Lin.  Figure 4. Shifting Time by Camille Utterback. Collection of the City of San José. &#38;#169; 
2010 Camille Utterback. Photo &#38;#169; 2010 Camille Utterback/Creative Nerve.  Figure 5. One of two 
large showcases, featuring Small Wonders, curated by ZeroOne. Collection of the City of San José. &#38;#169; 
2010 ZeroOne. Photo &#38;#169; 2010 Matt Gorbet. Collaboration with the Future  |  Gorbet et al. 
 Figure 6. eCloud, a permanent artwork by Nik Hafermaas, Dan Goods, and Aaron Koblin, uses real-time 
weather data from around the world (provided by the Art Server) to render cloud forms in thousands of 
glass pixels suspended over the concourse. Collection of the City of San José. &#38;#169; 2010 Nik Hafermaas 
et al. Photo &#38;#169; 2010 Ben Blackwell. Gorbet et al.  |  Collaboration with the Future  Figure 
7. Space Observer, a permanent work by Björn Schülke, sends status heartbeats to the Art Cloud. Every 
active artwork can be monitored in this way. Collection of the City of San José. &#38;#169; 2010 Björn 
Schülke. Collaboration with the Future  |  Gorbet et al.  Gorbet et al.  |  Collaboration with 
the Future 342  Collaboration with the Future  |  Gorbet et al. 343  Gorbet et al.  |  Collaboration 
with the Future 344  Collaboration with the Future  |  Gorbet et al. 345  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	</section>
	<section>
		<section_id>2019349</section_id>
		<sort_key>70</sort_key>
		<section_seq_no>2</section_seq_no>
		<section_type>SESSION</section_type>
		<section_title><![CDATA[Tracing home]]></section_title>
		<section_page_from>350</section_page_from>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019350</article_id>
		<sort_key>80</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>1</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Wait]]></title>
		<page_from>350</page_from>
		<page_to>351</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019350</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019350</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>The human-companion species relationship is the starting point for the critique explored in <i>Wait. Wait</i> is part of the larger <i>Animal Lover</i> body of work, which is situated within a developing area of artistic practice referred to as "interspecies collaboration." Contemporary cultures for the most part consider animals in terms of consumption: as food source, experimental subject, eco-logical resource, entertainment, etc. Critical to <i>Animal Lover</i> are questions and critiques addressing human relations with non-humans, particularly companion species. These works reconsider the animal as conscious, expressive, and creative, with complex states of being different from, but potentially as rich as, those of humans. In <i>Wait</i>, human and canine communication methodsare brought to bear within an interactive video installation. The piece uses interactive technologies that track the physical presence and movement of visitors to the work, allowing for direct contribution to the creation of meaning. Taking cues from the movements of the visitor, the dog (as imaged in the video) points to the relationship of control. The dog appears to be waiting for direction -- looking directly at the visitor, implying a state of suspended urgency. Visitors are compelled to ask questions about their relationship to the dog. In this way, the piece depicts the complex relationship between humans and companion species who share the domestic space. For the most part, companions such as dogs, cats, and birds are subject to conditions of human dwelling (home) and the systems and codes of power, space, and communication associated with it. <i>Wait</i> was produced in partnership with Banff New Media Institute, The Banff Centre, Banff, Canada.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759717</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81384608992]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Julie]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Andreyev]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Emily Carr University of Art + Design Vancouver, British Columbia Canada]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[julie@animallover.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759718</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81548038266]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Simon]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Overstall]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Emily Carr University of Art + Design Vancouver, British Columbia Canada]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Julie Andreyev and Simon Overstall Wait The human companion species relationship is the starting point 
for the critique explored in Wait. Wait is part of the larger Animal Lover body of work, which is situated 
within a developing area of artistic practice referred to as interspecies collaboration. Contemporary 
cultures for the most part consider animals in terms of consumption: as food source, experimental subject, 
eco­logical resource, entertainment, etc. Critical to Animal Lover are questions and critiques address­ing 
human relations with non-humans, particularly companion species. These works reconsider the animal as 
conscious, expressive, and creative, with complex states of being different from, but potentially as 
rich as, those of humans. In Wait, human and canine communication methods are brought to bear within 
an interactive video installation. The piece uses interactive technolo­gies that track the physical presence 
and movement of visitors to the work, allowing for direct contribution to the creation of meaning. Taking 
cues from the movements of the visitor, the dog (as imaged in the video) points to the relationship of 
control. The dog appears to be waiting for direction looking directly at the visitor, implying a state 
of suspended urgency. Visitors are compelled to ask questions about their relationship to the dog. In 
this way, the piece depicts the complex relationship between humans and companion species who share the 
domestic space. For the most part, companions such as dogs, cats, and birds are subject to conditions 
of human dwelling (home) and the systems and codes of power, space, and communication associated with 
it. Wait was produced in partnership with Banff New Media Institute, The Banff Centre, Banff, Canada. 
Julie Andreyev is an artist involved in two areas of practice: Four Wheel Drift (www.fourwheel­drift.com) 
examines the social and spatial character of the city using mobility, performance, and participatory 
engagement; Animal Lover (www.animallover.com) explores animal consciousness and creativity through interactive 
installation, interspecies collaboration, and video. Andreyev s work has been shown across Canada and 
in the US, Europe, and Japan in galleries and at media arts festivals. Her work is supported by The Canada 
Council for the Arts, The British Columbia Arts Council, Foreign Affairs Canada, and The Social Sciences 
and Humanities Research Coun­cil of Canada. She is an associate professor at Emily Carr University of 
Art + Design in Vancou­ver and artistic director of Interactive Futures (www.interactivefutures.ca). 
Simon Lysander Overstall is an artist working in digital arts and new media, in particular audio art 
and music. He has a BFA in music composition from the School for Contemporary Arts at Simon Fraser University 
and an associate s diploma in music (jazz) from Malaspina University-College. He has produced sound designs 
and compositions for dance, theater, and installations. In addition, he designs software for both performance 
systems and installations. Currently, he is a research technician at Intersections Digital Studios at 
Emily Carr University of Art + Design in Vancouver. Julie Andreyev Simon Overstall Emily Carr University 
of Art + Design Vancouver, British Columbia Canada julie@animallover.ca www.animallover.ca   Animal 
Lover logo. &#38;#169; 2011 Julie Andreyev. &#38;#169; 2011 Julie Andreyev and Simon Overstall  | 
 Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 350 351, 2011  Wait. &#38;#169; 2011 Julie Andreyev. Wait  |  Andreyev 
and Overstall  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019351</article_id>
		<sort_key>90</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>2</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Oh!m1gas]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[biomimetic stridulation environment]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>352</page_from>
		<page_to>353</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019351</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019351</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p><i>Oh!m1gas: biomimetic stridulation environment</i> is an installation-based exploration of a socially responsible art form, drawing on sustainable organic materials (in this case, a live ant colony) and stimulating interspecific interactions. As artist Kuai Shen Auson first observed at home in Ecuador, ants represent a natural superorganism which stands out due to its emergent social structure and self-organization. They generate bottom-up structures in order to solve problems by means of a complex network of local interactions. Kuai Shen explores the social similarities and differences between humans and ants through four key areas: cybernetics, autopoiesis, self-organization, and emergence. In this piece, the activity of an ant colony is observed, archiving the ants' movements and sounds inside a digital matrix. A pair of turntables constantly reacts to the changes that emerge from the colony (e.g., recruiting units for defense, task allocation when rebuilding the nest, organizing the harvesting of vegetation), thus spinning vinyl records that produce scratching sounds similar to the original stridulations of some ants. Leafcutter ants use the stridulatory organ, human DJ's use the turntable: a reactive soundscape, which reveals the connection between scratching as an aesthetic expression created by human culture, and the stridulation phenomena of leafcutter ants as a modulation mechanism for communication. Kuai Shen believes we can learn from the way the ants construct their miniature ecosystems. Like them, we can apply an experi-mental design approach based on organic architecture, where sounds and physical interaction, instead of divided living spaces, promote and consolidate the interaction of life.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759719</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487653030]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Kuai]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[Shen]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Auson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Kunsthochschule f&#252;r Medien K&#246;ln, Cologne, Germany]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[yo@kuaishen.tv]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Kuai Shen Auson 0h!m1gas: biomimetic stridulation environment Oh!m1gas: biomimetic stridulation environment 
is an installation-based exploration of a socially responsible art form, drawing on sustainable organic 
materials (in this case, a live ant colony) and stimulating interspecific interactions. As artist Kuai 
Shen Auson first observed at home in Ecuador, ants represent a natural superorganism which stands out 
due to its emergent social structure and self-organization. They generate bottom-up structures in order 
to solve problems by means of a complex network of local interactions. Kuai Shen explores the social 
similarities and differences between humans and ants through four key areas: cybernetics, autopoiesis, 
self-organization, and emergence. In this piece, the activity of an ant colony is observed, archiving 
the ants movements and sounds inside a digital matrix. A pair of turntables constantly reacts to the 
changes that emerge from the colony (e.g., recruiting units for defense, task allocation when rebuilding 
the nest, organizing the harvesting of vegetation), thus spinning vinyl records that produce scratching 
sounds similar to the original stridulations of some ants. Leafcutter ants use the stridulatory organ, 
human DJ s use the turntable: a reactive soundscape, which reveals the connection between scratching 
as an aesthetic expression created by human culture, and the stridulation phenomena of leafcutter ants 
as a modulation mechanism for communication. Kuai Shen believes we can learn from the way the ants construct 
their miniature ecosystems. Like them, we can apply an experi­mental design approach based on organic 
architecture, where sounds and physical interaction, instead of divided living spaces, promote and consolidate 
the interaction of life. Kuai Shen Auson was born in Guayaquil, Ecuador. He holds a BA in digital arts 
and an MA in media arts with honors from the Kunsthochschule für Medien Köln. He has brought his work 
exploring the cybernetic emergence of ants into new territories, from Quito to New York and now to Cologne. 
His current research focuses on game design and theory based on his interdisciplinary artistic/scientific 
work with ants at Cologne Game Lab of the University of Applied Sciences. Kuai Shen Auson Kunsthochschule 
für Medien Köln Cologne, Germany yo@kuaishen.tv www.kuaishen.tv/0hm1gas  0h!m1gas: biomimetic stridulation 
environment. &#38;#169; 2010 Kuai Shen Auson. &#38;#169; 2011 Kuai Shen Auson  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, 
No. 4, pp. 352 353, 2011  0h!m1gas: biomimetic stridulation environment. &#38;#169; 2010 Kuai Shen Auson. 
 0h!m1gas: biomimetic stridulation environment  |  Kuai Shen Auson  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019352</article_id>
		<sort_key>100</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>3</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[MOSTON]]></title>
		<page_from>354</page_from>
		<page_to>355</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019352</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019352</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Ideas and observations stemming from bicultural experience and the larger issues of identity, immigration, and globalization are central to Anya Belkina's work. She fuses art with inquiry in the areas of biology, physics, and computer science. <i>MOSTON</i>, a 12-foot-tall suspended inflat-able sculpture, embodies an internal conception of home and the cyberfusion of two geographically distant locales: Moscow and Boston. Its surface design of printed artwork and documentary footage projection explores visual and historical commonalities of the two cities, commonalities that are more easily researched, documented, and shared in the era of instant global networking. While <i>MOSTON</i>'s three-dimensional form references ethnically specific artifacts, the visual appeal and conceptual ingenuity of <i>matryoshkas</i> reach audiences beyond Russia and the Russian diaspora. A universally understood symbol of sequential creation, these toys offer a fitting framework for evoking the concentric evolution of Moscow's and Boston's city armatures. The implied nestedness of <i>MOSTON</i> is also congruent with the layered mental construct of "home," especially as perceived by individuals with multicultural backgrounds. Belkina describes the scale of the project as essential, not only because her motherland is the largest country in the world, with an impressive record of pursuing hopeless megalomaniac ventures, but also because "there is no place like home."</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759720</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81466643550]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Anya]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Belkina]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Emerson College, Boston, Massachusetts]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[anya_belkina@emerson.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Anya Belkina MOSTON Ideas and observations stemming from bicultural experience and the larger issues 
of identity, immigration, and globalization are central to Anya Belkina s work. She fuses art with inquiry 
in the areas of biology, physics, and computer science. MOSTON, a 12-foot-tall suspended inflat­able 
sculpture, embodies an internal conception of home and the cyberfusion of two geographically distant 
locales: Moscow and Boston. Its surface design of printed artwork and documentary footage projection 
explores visual and historical commonalities of the two cities, commonalities that are more easily researched, 
documented, and shared in the era of instant global networking. While MOSTON s three-dimensional form 
references ethnically specific artifacts, the visual appeal and conceptual ingenuity of matryoshkas reach 
audiences beyond Russia and the Russian diaspora. A universally understood symbol of sequential creation, 
these toys offer a fitting framework for evoking the concentric evolution of Moscow s and Boston s city 
armatures. The implied nestedness of MOSTON is also congruent with the layered mental construct of home, 
especially as perceived by individuals with multicultural backgrounds. Belkina describes the scale of 
the project as essential, not only because her motherland is the largest country in the world, with an 
impressive record of pursuing hopeless megalomaniac ventures, but also because there is no place like 
home. Anya Belkina is assistant professor of new media at Emerson College in Boston. Prior to joining 
Emerson in 2007, she held the position of assistant professor in the practice of art at Duke University. 
Belkina received her MFA from the University of California, San Diego, and her BFA from the Rhode Island 
School of Design. In Russia, she studied at the Moscow Art College in Memory of 1905. Belkina s work 
in the area of new media has been presented nationally and abroad at conventional exhibition venues, 
as well as in the form of large-scale site-specific installations, video projections, broadcast media, 
and cover art for literary journals. Her award-winning animated shorts have screened at numerous national 
and international venues, including SIGGRAPH, ANIMATOR, RIIFF, the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and The 
Light Factory Museum in Charlotte, North Carolina. Anya Belkina Emerson College Boston, Massachusetts 
USA anya_belkina@emerson.edu www.anyabelkina.com  MOSTON. &#38;#169; 2011 Anya Belkina. &#38;#169; 
2011 Anya Belkina  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 354 355, 2011  MOSTON. &#38;#169; 2011 Anya Belkina. 
 MOSTON. &#38;#169; 2011 Anya Belkina. MOSTON  |  Anya Belkina  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019353</article_id>
		<sort_key>110</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>4</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[The Garden of Error and Decay]]></title>
		<page_from>356</page_from>
		<page_to>357</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019353</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019353</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p><i>The Garden of Error and Decay</i> is a poetic visualization of real-time world catastrophes. It reflects on the network media reality of the 21<sup>st</sup> century through a continuous story of current world disasters, expressed by animated pictograms. Every time a disaster-related topic is discussed on Twitter, a new animation appears. Stock exchange information also influences the storytelling. Users interacting with the Garden have the opportunity to either eliminate or multiply the disaster scenes with a shooting device. However, it is not the user who actually has the power to decide in which direction the story develops once an event is triggered. As in real life, everything is driven by stock exchange dynamics; these dictate whether disasters proliferate or die down. This innovative moving image format is not a film, not a game, and not a nonlinear interactive story, but instead a real-time, data-driven narrative.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759721</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487654390]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Michael]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bielicky]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[HFG/ZKM Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe, Germany]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[mbielicky@hfg-karlsruhe.de]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759722</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487643693]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Kamila]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[B.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Richter]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[HFG/ZKM Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe, Germany]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Michael Bielicky and Kamila B. Richter The Garden of Error and Decay The Garden of Error and Decay is 
a poetic visualization of real-time world catastrophes. It reflects on the network media reality of the 
21st century through a continuous story of current world disasters, expressed by animated pictograms. 
Every time a disaster-related topic is discussed on Twitter, a new animation appears. Stock exchange 
information also influences the storytelling. Users interacting with the Garden have the opportunity 
to either eliminate or multiply the disaster scenes with a shooting device. However, it is not the user 
who actually has the power to decide in which direction the story develops once an event is triggered. 
As in real life, everything is driven by stock exchange dynamics; these dictate whether disasters proliferate 
or die down. This innovative moving image format is not a film, not a game, and not a nonlinear interactive 
story, but instead a real-time, data-driven narrative. Michael Bielicky founded and was a professor in 
the New Media department at the Academy of Fine Arts in Prague. Since 2006 he has been a professor of 
digital media art at the Staatliche Hochschule für Gestaltung Karlsruhe and the Zentrum für Kunst und 
Medientechnologie Karlsruhe. Over the past 25 years, he has participated in many international exhibitions, 
festivals, and symposia. His work uses communication, navigation, video, and VR technologies and, most 
recently, real-time web-based information technologies. He has exhibited at ZKM Karlsruhe, Ars Electronica 
Linz, High Tech Center Berlin-Babelsberg, Centre Pompidou Paris, MoMA New York, the National Gallery 
in Prague, Kunsthaus Zürich, and many other venues around the world. Born in Olomouc, Czechoslovak Socialist 
Republic, Kamila B. Richter earned her MFA (2001) and PhD (2010) at the Academy of Fine Arts in Prague. 
From 2000 to 2002, she lived in the Republic of South Africa (Durban, Johannesburg) and studied at Technikon 
Natal, Durban. Richter has participated in many national and international exhibitions since 1999. She 
now lives in Düsseldorf, Germany, and operates in public spaces through the media of print and inter-active 
urban screenings. Michael Bielicky HFG/ZKM Karlsruhe Karlsruhe, Germany mbielicky@hfg-karlsruhe.de Kamila 
B. Richter HFG/ZKM Karlsruhe Karlsruhe, Germany Programmer: Dirk Reinbold Sound: Lorenz Schwarz www.gardenoferroranddecay.net 
 The Garden of Error and Decay. &#38;#169; 2011 Michael Bielicky and Kamila B. Richter. &#38;#169; 
2011 Michael Bielicky and Kamila B. Richter  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 356 357, 2011  The Garden 
of Error and Decay. &#38;#169; 2011 Michael Bielicky and Kamila B. Richter. The Garden of Error and 
Decay |  Bielicky and Richter  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019354</article_id>
		<sort_key>120</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>5</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[tele-present wind]]></title>
		<page_from>358</page_from>
		<page_to>359</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019354</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019354</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>David Bowen's work is concerned with aesthetics that result from interactive, reactive, and generative processes as they relate to intersections between natural and mechanical systems. <i>tele-present wind</i> consists of a field of x/y tilting devices connected to thin, dried plant stalks installed in the gallery, and a dried plant stalk connected to an accelerometer installed outdoors. When the wind blows, it causes the stalk outside to sway. The accelerometer detects this movement, transmitting it in real time to the grouping of devices in the gallery. The stalks in the gallery space move in unison, based on the movement of the wind outside. Bowen says of his work, "I produce devices and situations that are set in motion to create drawings, movements, compositions, sounds, and objects based on their perception of and interaction with the space and time they occupy. The devices I construct often play the roles of both observer and creator, providing limited and mechanical perspectives of dynamic situations and living objects. The work is a result of the combination of a particular event and the residue left after the event." His work thus offers an imperfect and revealing transposition of data. "In some ways, the devices are attempting, often futilely, to simulate or mimic a natural form, system, or function. When the mechanisms fail to replicate the natural system, the result is a completely unique outcome. It is these unpredictable occurrences that I find most fascinating. These outcomes are a collaboration between the natural form or function, the mechanism, and myself. This combination can be seen as an elaborate and even absurd method of capturing qualified data. I see the data collected in this manner as aesthetic data."</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759723</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487647271]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[David]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bowen]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Minnesota, Duluth, Minnesota]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[dwbowen@hotmail.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 David Bowen tele-present wind David Bowen s work is concerned with aesthetics that result from interactive, 
reactive, and generative processes as they relate to intersections between natural and mechanical systems. 
tele-present wind consists of a field of x/y tilting devices connected to thin, dried plant stalks installed 
in the gallery, and a dried plant stalk connected to an accelerometer installed outdoors. When the wind 
blows, it causes the stalk outside to sway. The accelerometer detects this move­ment, transmitting it 
in real time to the grouping of devices in the gallery. The stalks in the gallery space move in unison, 
based on the movement of the wind outside. Bowen says of his work, I produce devices and situations that 
are set in motion to create drawings, movements, compositions, sounds, and objects based on their perception 
of and interaction with the space and time they occupy. The devices I construct often play the roles 
of both observer and creator, providing limited and mechanical perspectives of dynamic situations and 
living objects. The work is a result of the combination of a particular event and the residue left after 
the event. His work thus offers an imperfect and revealing transposition of data. In some ways, the devices 
are attempting, often futilely, to simulate or mimic a natural form, system, or function. When the mechanisms 
fail to replicate the natural system, the result is a completely unique outcome. It is these unpredictable 
occurrences that I find most fascinating. These outcomes are a collaboration between the natural form 
or function, the mechanism, and myself. This combination can be seen as an elaborate and even absurd 
method of capturing qualified data. I see the data collected in this manner as aesthetic data. David 
Bowen is a studio artist and educator. He received his BFA from the Herron School of Art and Design in 
1999, and his MFA from the University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, in 2004. He is currently associate professor 
of sculpture and physical computing at the University of Minne­sota, Duluth. His work has been featured 
in numerous group and solo exhibitions, including Brainwave at Exit Art, New York City; The Japan Media 
Arts Festival at The National Art Center, Tokyo; if/then at Vox Populi, Philadelphia; Artbots at Eyebeam, 
New York City; and Data + Art at The NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena. His work has been featured 
in such publications as Art in America, Leonardo, and Sculpture Magazine. He was recently awarded Grand 
Prize in the Art Division at The Japan Media Arts Festival and Third Prize at the Vida 12.0 Art and Artificial 
Life International Awards.  David Bowen University of Minnesota Duluth, Minnesota USA dwbowen@hotmail.com 
www.dwbowen.com  tele-present wind. &#38;#169; 2011 David Bowen. &#38;#169; 2011 David Bowen  |  
Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 358 359, 2011  tele-present wind. &#38;#169; 2011 David Bowen. Photo &#38;#169; 
2011 Shannon Di. tele-present wind  |  David Bowen  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019355</article_id>
		<sort_key>130</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>6</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Tomorrow will get better]]></title>
		<page_from>360</page_from>
		<page_to>361</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019355</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019355</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p><i>Tomorrow will get better</i> is a graphite drawing and laser-cut paper series of homes destroyed by various natural and man-made disasters. The images become ephemeral portraits of the houses that artist Matthew Cox has been "collecting" and using as drawing subjects. He describes them as characters in a narrative, similar to a gothic noir film. This series exhibits the final moments of a home before it is sent to a landfill, a premature burial that no one ever expects. Cox suggests that a relationship between the house and its inhabitants develops and evolves through daily events that take place within the confines of a home. A tragic event will jeopardize the physical stability of the home, resulting in the emotional instability of its inhabitants. The home has the potential to live and die just like its inhabitants, instead of remaining a solid structure built to survive through generations. A home develops character from its exterior surroundings as well as from its interior dialogue with the characters, who create a bond through memories and interactions. What are our attachments to our physical surroundings? How do they strengthen or weaken us? Houses, taken for granted as private property with equity and security, have the potential to reveal our vulnerability when their stability is subtracted from our lives.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759724</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487644010]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Matthew]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Cox]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Independent Artist, New York, New York]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[xocttam@gmail.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Matthew Cox Tomorrow will get better Tomorrow will get better is a graphite drawing and laser-cut paper 
series of homes destroyed by various natural and man-made disasters. The images become ephemeral portraits 
of the houses that artist Matthew Cox has been collecting and using as drawing subjects. He describes 
them as characters in a narrative, similar to a gothic noir film. This series exhibits the final moments 
of a home before it is sent to a landfill, a premature burial that no one ever expects. Cox suggests 
that a relationship between the house and its inhabitants develops and evolves through daily events that 
take place within the confines of a home. A tragic event will jeopardize the physical stability of the 
home, resulting in the emotional instability of its inhabitants. The home has the potential to live and 
die just like its inhabitants, instead of remaining a solid structure built to survive through generations. 
A home develops character from its exterior surroundings as well as from its interior dialogue with the 
characters, who create a bond through memories and interac­tions. What are our attachments to our physical 
surroundings? How do they strengthen or weaken us? Houses, taken for granted as private property with 
equity and security, have the potential to reveal our vulnerability when their stability is subtracted 
from our lives. Matthew Cox was born in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, and grew up in Miami, Florida, where 
he attended Florida International University, receiving a BFA in drawing in 2002. In 2006 he graduated 
from the University of Miami with an MFA in film. He currently lives and works in New York City.  Matthew 
Cox Independent Artist New York, New York  USA  xocttam@gmail.com www.mjcox.com   Tomorrow will get 
better. &#38;#169; 2007 Matthew Cox. &#38;#169; 2011 Matthew Cox  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 
360 361, 2011  Tomorrow will get better. &#38;#169; 2007 Matthew Cox. Tomorrow will get better  | 
 Matthew Cox  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019356</article_id>
		<sort_key>140</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>7</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[RolyPoly]]></title>
		<page_from>362</page_from>
		<page_to>363</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019356</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019356</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p><i>RolyPoly</i> is a networked installation designed to enable two individuals to "sense" the presence of each other, even though they may be physically apart. The mirrored movements in a pair of RolyPolys is such that a soft tap to rock one will simultaneously rock its partner to the same degree, instantly creating a corresponding reaction in the other. While the Internet provides a vast array of text messaging and video interaction options, <i>RolyPoly</i> offers a unique, spontaneous, and subtle mode of instant communication, exclusively between two individuals. <i>RolyPoly</i> addresses the phenomenon of people living apart and examines gesture as a different mode of communi-cation from speech and text. Through gestures, one is able to bring intimate familiarity to the other party, even when miles apart.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759725</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487652762]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Design Incubation Centre]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[National University of Singapore, Singapore]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[info@designincubationcentre.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Design Incubation Centre RolyPoly RolyPoly is a networked installation designed to enable two individuals 
to sense the presence of each other, even though they may be physically apart. The mirrored movements 
in a pair of RolyPolys is such that a soft tap to rock one will simultaneously rock its partner to the 
same de­gree, instantly creating a corresponding reaction in the other. While the Internet provides a 
vast array of text messaging and video interaction options, RolyPoly offers a unique, spontaneous, and 
subtle mode of instant communication, exclusively between two individuals. RolyPoly addresses the phenomenon 
of people living apart and examines gesture as a different mode of communi­cation from speech and text. 
Through gestures, one is able to bring intimate familiarity to the other party, even when miles apart. 
The Design Incubation Centre is a design research laboratory that investigates and develops innovative 
tools to find new possibilities for the practice of design through projects that analyze emerging and 
evolving human needs, technologies, and social trends. The Design Incubation Centre is part of the Division 
of Industrial Design at the School of Design and Environment, National University of Singapore. Design 
Incubation Centre Division of Industrial Design School of Design and Environment National University 
of Singapore Singapore info@designincubationcentre.com www.designincubationcentre.com  RolyPoly. &#38;#169; 
2011 National University of Singapore. &#38;#169; 2011 National University of Singapore  |  Leonardo, 
Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 362 363, 2011  RolyPoly. &#38;#169; 2011 National University of Singapore. RolyPoly 
 |  National University of Singapore  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019357</article_id>
		<sort_key>150</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>8</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Hildapromenade 4]]></title>
		<page_from>364</page_from>
		<page_to>365</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019357</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019357</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Philipp Engelhardt's <i>Hildapromenade</i> 4 installation visualizes the magical "in-between" of a set of photographs from a photo album he found on the street. The piece combines 3D technology and animations with the eight original Polaroid images to allow the spectator to enter the world of the woman shown in the pictures, narrating her story in a new context. Engelhardt uses his own graphical material in combination with the existing images to create his effects. In this way, the images are combined, reconstructed, and repeated so they can be seen in a new context on their own. To the observer, the visible alterations in the pictures are not immediately apparent; the manipulation is seen as the reality which the interface superposes. Engelhardt describes the piece's impact: "<i>Hildapromenade</i> 4 reflects upon the value of the memories brought together in a photo album. At a time when photographs are increasingly stored on hard drives, and thus seem ever more elusive and intangible, it raises the question of which stories are able to be discovered in such often-unstructured visual material."</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759726</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487654644]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Philipp]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Engelhardt]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[HfG Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe, Germany]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[pengelhar@hfg-karlsruhe.de]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Philipp Engelhardt Hildapromenade 4 Philipp Engelhardt s Hildapromenade 4 installation visualizes the 
magical in-between of a set of photographs from a photo album he found on the street. The piece combines 
3D technology and animations with the eight original Polaroid images to allow the spectator to enter 
the world of the woman shown in the pictures, narrating her story in a new context. Engelhardt uses his 
own graphical material in combination with the existing images to create his effects. In this way, the 
images are combined, reconstructed, and repeated so they can be seen in a new context on their own. To 
the observer, the visible alterations in the pictures are not immediately apparent; the manipulation 
is seen as the reality which the interface superposes. Engelhardt describes the piece s impact: Hildapromenade 
4 reflects upon the value of the memories brought together in a photo album. At a time when photographs 
are increasingly stored on hard drives, and thus seem ever more elusive and intangible, it raises the 
question of which stories are able to be discovered in such often-unstructured visual material. Philipp 
Engelhardt is from Calw, Germany. From 2006 to 2011, he studied media art at the HfG Karlsruhe with Professors 
Elger Esser, Michael Bielicky, and Isaac Julien. He is a freelance artist. Philipp Engelhardt HfG Karlsruhe 
Karlsruhe, Germany pengelhar@hfg-karlsruhe.de www.piripi.de  Hildapromenade 4. &#38;#169; 2011 Philipp 
Engelhardt. Photo &#38;#169; 2010 We Find Wildness, Sophie Yerly. &#38;#169; 2011 Philipp Engelhardt 
 |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 364 365, 2011  Hildapromenade 4. &#38;#169; 2011 Philipp Engelhardt. 
 Hildapromenade 4  |  Philipp Engelhardt  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019358</article_id>
		<sort_key>160</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>9</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Memoirs]]></title>
		<page_from>366</page_from>
		<page_to>367</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019358</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019358</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p><i>Memoirs</i> is an interactive installation piece. It is a memoir of humanity's struggle to invent home appliances in pursuit of happiness. The piece is composed of a brown TV tube panel with a Polaroid camera on top. Its antique look stimulates a sense of nostalgia for old-fashioned home appliances. As you come close to the piece, a custom-made Polaroid camera automatically recognizes your face and takes a picture of you, and a physically simulated photo paper falls down and hits the pile of photos inside the virtual interior of the piece. Its digital data travels halfway around the earth to a web server in a distant country. Even though film-based photo-graphy is perishing and digital cameras are penetrating everyday objects, nothing can substitute for the feeling of anticipation while waiting for a photo to develop. Like bringing film to the photo printing office, taking a card with a printed web address from a stack creates a space in which to reminisce about the good old days. As you stand in front of the piece, the line between the virtual self and the physical self blurs. With photos stacking up on the web server, participants collectively build and share a single memory through the piece. Because of its intense and antique visual imprint, even when our experience with this piece dims, our shared childhood memories of electronic home appliances will remain.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759727</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81421594806]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Yunsil]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Heo]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Seoul National University, Seoul, South Korea]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[yunsil@snu.ac.kr]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759728</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81421599972]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Hyunwoo]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bang]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Seoul National University, Seoul, South Korea]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[savoy@snu.ac.kr]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Yunsil Heo and Hyunwoo Bang Memoirs Memoirs is an interactive installation piece. It is a memoir of 
humanity s struggle to invent home appliances in pursuit of happiness. The piece is composed of a brown 
TV tube panel with a Polaroid camera on top. Its antique look stimulates a sense of nostalgia for old-fashioned 
home appliances. As you come close to the piece, a custom-made Polaroid camera automatically recognizes 
your face and takes a picture of you, and a physically simulated photo paper falls down and hits the 
pile of photos inside the virtual interior of the piece. Its digital data travels halfway around the 
earth to a web server in a distant country. Even though film-based photo-graphy is perishing and digital 
cameras are penetrating everyday objects, nothing can substitute for the feeling of anticipation while 
waiting for a photo to develop. Like bringing film to the photo printing office, taking a card with a 
printed web address from a stack creates a space in which to reminisce about the good old days. As you 
stand in front of the piece, the line between the virtual self and the physical self blurs. With photos 
stacking up on the web server, partici­pants collectively build and share a single memory through the 
piece. Because of its intense and antique visual imprint, even when our experience with this piece dims, 
our shared childhood memories of electronic home appliances will remain. Yunsil Heo and Hyunwoo Bang 
are new media artists exploring intuitive and fun communica­tions between the real and virtual worlds. 
They have exhibited their work at festivals and in galleries, including SIGGRAPH 2008 (Los Angeles), 
Ars Electronica Center (Linz, Austria), the National Art Center Tokyo, Incheon Digital Art Pavilion (Incheon, 
Korea), and the Victoria &#38; Albert Museum (London). Heo earned her MFA at the Department of Design 
| Media Arts at the University of California, Los Angeles, and is currently pursuing her PhD at Seoul 
National University. She operates an interactive media design company, New Media Lab Inc., in South Korea. 
Bang earned his PhD in mechanical engineering from Seoul National University and worked as a post-doctoral 
fellow in the Department of BioEngineering at the University of California, Los Angeles. He is now an 
assistant professor at Seoul National University. Yunsil Heo School of Crafts and Design Seoul National 
University Seoul, South Korea yunsil@snu.ac.kr Hyunwoo Bang School of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering 
Seoul National University Seoul, South Korea savoy@snu.ac.kr www.everyware.kr/portfolio/contents/ 10_memoirs/index.htm 
 Memoirs. &#38;#169; 2010 Yunsil Heo and Hyunwoo Bang. &#38;#169; 2011 Yunsil Heo and Hyunwoo Bang 
 |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 366 367, 2011  Memoirs. &#38;#169; 2010 Yunsil Heo and Hyunwoo 
Bang. Photo &#38;#169; 2010 Jaehong Park, Museum of Art Seoul National University. Memoirs. &#38;#169; 
2010 Yunsil Heo and Hyunwoo Bang. Memoirs  |  Heo and Bang  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019359</article_id>
		<sort_key>170</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>10</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Transplant]]></title>
		<page_from>368</page_from>
		<page_to>369</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019359</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019359</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Emerging from the intersection of sculpture, theater, and engineering, Heidi Kumao's video and machine art generates artistic spectacles in order to visualize the unseen: thought patterns, men-tal states, emotions, compulsions, and dreams. Through the creation of hybrid art forms (kinetic sculptures, animations, and interactive works), she explores the psychological underpinnings of everyday situations and institutional contexts, such as the nuclear family, mainstream media, and traditional gender roles. <i>Transplant</i> explores the lives of Japanese nationals and citizens who were interned in War Relocation Centers in the dusty desert of California during World War II, and how they cultivated gardens as a creative outlet to survive their confinement. Despite the horrendous conditions, residents of these "camps" constructed beautifully landscaped parks, ponds, and rock gardens. <i>Transplant</i> pays homage to their ingenuity and personal drive to transform gravel into gardens, altering their built environment as an act of defiance. This piece is part of the project <i>Timed Release</i>, a continuing series of intimate theater pieces about surviving confinement, supported by a 2009 Guggenheim Fellowship.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759729</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487655192]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Heidi]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Kumao]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Michigan School of Art & Design, Ann Arbor, Michigan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[hkumao@umich.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Heidi Kumao Transplant Emerging from the intersection of sculpture, theater, and engineering, Heidi 
Kumao s video and machine art generates artistic spectacles in order to visualize the unseen: thought 
patterns, men­tal states, emotions, compulsions, and dreams. Through the creation of hybrid art forms 
(kinetic sculptures, animations, and interactive works), she explores the psychological underpinnings 
of everyday situations and institutional contexts, such as the nuclear family, mainstream media, and 
traditional gender roles. Transplant explores the lives of Japanese nationals and citizens who were interned 
in War Relocation Centers in the dusty desert of California during World War II, and how they cultivated 
gardens as a creative outlet to survive their confinement. Despite the horrendous conditions, residents 
of these camps constructed beautifully landscaped parks, ponds, and rock gardens. Transplant pays homage 
to their ingenuity and personal drive to transform gravel into gardens, altering their built environment 
as an act of defiance. This piece is part of the project Timed Release, a continuing series of intimate 
theater pieces about surviving confinement, supported by a 2009 Guggenheim Fellowship. Heidi Kumao received 
her MFA from the School of the Art Institute of Chicago and is an associate professor at the School of 
Art &#38; Design at the University of Michigan. Kumao has exhibited her work nationally and internationally 
in one-person exhibitions at the Museo de Arte Moderno, Buenos Aires; Fundació Joan Miró, Barcelona; 
and Center for the Arts, Yerba Buena Gardens, San Francisco. Group exhibition venues include ZeroOne 
San Jose, Museo Universitario Arte Contemporáneo in Mexico City, Wing Luke Asian Art Museum in Seattle, 
and the National Academy Museum in New York City. Her work has been reviewed in Artforum, ArtPapers, 
and Sculpture Magazine, and is held in a number of private and public collections. She has received fellowships 
from the Guggenheim Foundation, the Creative Capital Foundation, New York Foundation for the Arts, American 
Association of University Women, and the National Endowment for the Arts. Heidi Kumao University of 
Michigan School of Art &#38; Design Ann Arbor, Michigan USA hkumao@umich.edu www.heidikumao.net  Transplant. 
&#38;#169; 2009 Heidi Kumao. &#38;#169; 2011 Heidi Kumao  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 368 369, 
2011  Transplant. &#38;#169; 2009 Heidi Kumao. Transplant  |  Heidi Kumao  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019360</article_id>
		<sort_key>180</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>11</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[The Insatiable]]></title>
		<page_from>370</page_from>
		<page_to>371</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019360</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019360</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p><i>The Insatiable</i> is a video installation composited from a dozen sets of footage filmed at an open night market in Taiwan. It is part of the Things that are edible series, created by artist Jawshing Arthur Liou during an artistic residency in his hometown of Taipei after 16 years of living abroad. Working with both lens-based representation and digital post-production, Liou aims to transform recognizable imagery into realms only the mind can reach. His photographically realistic digital videos are filled with details with which he responds to the experience of illness, spiritual sanctuary, and the spectacles of life. The street scenes here are only half a mile away from his home. The visual strategy is a fusion of macro and micro views. The streetlights and mingling walkers are transformed into bodies of massive creatures, bearing resemblance to snakes, dragons, or even huge intestines. Liou says, "Our intimacy with food and food-related culture makes this my first choice of subject matter. With digital post-production tools, I transformed the night market into massive bodies in the sky, a wedding banquet into jewelry-banded plates, and my mother's rice dish into landscapes." In this way he creates "a rewarding treat in and of itself."</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759730</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487646205]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jawshing]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[Arthur]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Liou]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[liou@indiana.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Jawshing Arthur Liou The Insatiable The Insatiable is a video installation composited from a dozen sets 
of footage filmed at an open night market in Taiwan. It is part of the Things that are edible series, 
created by artist Jawshing Arthur Liou during an artistic residency in his hometown of Taipei after 16 
years of living abroad. Working with both lens-based representation and digital post-production, Liou 
aims to transform recognizable imagery into realms only the mind can reach. His photographically realistic 
digital videos are filled with details with which he responds to the experience of illness, spiritual 
sanctuary, and the spectacles of life. The street scenes here are only half a mile away from his home. 
The visual strategy is a fusion of macro and micro views. The streetlights and mingling walkers are transformed 
into bodies of massive creatures, bearing resemblance to snakes, dragons, or even huge intestines. Liou 
says, Our intimacy with food and food-related culture makes this my first choice of subject matter. With 
digital post-production tools, I transformed the night market into massive bodies in the sky, a wedding 
banquet into jewelry-banded plates, and my mother s rice dish into landscapes. In this way he creates 
a rewarding treat in and of itself. Originally from Taiwan, artist Jawshing Arthur Liou has resided in 
the US since 1994. He received his MFA in electronic intermedia and photography from the University of 
Florida. He is currently an associate professor and area head of digital art at Indiana University Bloomington. 
Liou s videos and prints are held in numerous public and private collections. Recent acquisitions include 
the Museum of Fine Arts Houston and the Indianapolis Museum of Art. Liou s work has traveled internationally, 
including exhibitions in New York, Chicago, London, Montréal, Houston, and Taipei. Liou is the recipient 
of the Garry B. Fritz Award from the Society for Photographic Education, the Rising Star Award at Fotofusion, 
and an Efroymson Contemporary Arts Fellowship. Jawshing Arthur Liou Indiana University Bloomington, 
Indiana USA liou@indiana.edu www.arthurliou.com  The Insatiable. &#38;#169; 2010 Jawshing Arthur Liou. 
 &#38;#169; 2011 Jawshing Arthur Liou  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 370 371, 2011  The Insatiable. 
&#38;#169; 2010 Jawshing Arthur Liou. The Insatiable | Jawshing Arthur Liou  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019361</article_id>
		<sort_key>190</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>12</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Travel Stones]]></title>
		<page_from>372</page_from>
		<page_to>373</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019361</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019361</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>For the last decade, Jacquelyn Martino has focused her artistic practice on the design of a rule-based computational language to generate works in the visual design language of her evolving style. <i>Travel Stones</i> is an installation that applies this computational language to the creation of a collection of cultural artifacts from a fictitious ancient culture. Martino makes use of her rule system to generate a series of realistic cultural artifacts made plausible by the combination of their consistent design language and their grounding in a number of historical references. In the installation, the viewer reads a museum-style exhibition text detailing the origins of the artifacts. The imagined culture derives from an ancient people who carry their travel stones -- much as house keys -- as a way to access their home center, which is ultimately more spiritual than physical. The text leads the viewer to believe that the four accompanying paintings document a first-hand exposure to the stones by someone external to the culture. Passed from generation to generation, the stones further serve as resonant objects in the tracing of the people's history. Prompted by the drawings on the stones, the ancients recount tales of their origins to the next generations as well as to those they meet in travel. Through their stories, they maintain their sense of identity and place while simultaneously transferring fragments of their culture to others. In this piece, the enabling algorithmic production system is integral to Martino's process, but not particularly apparent to the viewer. The visual separation of high-tech process from pseudo-historic product calls into question any easy distinction between technology and culture in our own place and time.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759731</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100508902]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jacquelyn]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Martino]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[IBM T. J. Watson Research Center, Yorktown Heights, New York]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[jacquelyn.martino@gmail.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Jacquelyn Martino Travel Stones For the last decade, Jacquelyn Martino has focused her artistic practice 
on the design of a rule-based computational language to generate works in the visual design language 
of her evolving style. Travel Stones is an installation that applies this computational language to the 
creation of a collection of cultural artifacts from a fictitious ancient culture. Martino makes use of 
her rule system to generate a series of realistic cultural artifacts made plausible by the combi­nation 
of their consistent design language and their grounding in a number of historical references. In the 
installation, the viewer reads a museum-style exhibition text detailing the origins of the artifacts. 
The imagined culture derives from an ancient people who carry their travel stones much as house keys 
 as a way to access their home center, which is ultimately more spiritual than physical. The text leads 
the viewer to believe that the four accompanying paintings document a first-hand exposure to the stones 
by someone external to the culture. Passed from generation to generation, the stones further serve as 
resonant objects in the tracing of the people s history. Prompted by the drawings on the stones, the 
ancients recount tales of their origins to the next generations as well as to those they meet in travel. 
Through their stories, they maintain their sense of identity and place while simultaneously transferring 
fragments of their culture to others. In this piece, the enabling algorithmic production system is integral 
to Martino s process, but not particularly apparent to the viewer. The visual separation of high-tech 
process from pseudo-historic product calls into question any easy distinction between technol­ogy and 
culture in our own place and time. Jacquelyn Martino is an artist-researcher concentrating on emerging 
forms of computational design and interaction technology. She holds a PhD in design computation from 
Massachusetts Institute of Technology, an MFA in computer graphics and interactive techniques from Pratt 
Institute, and a BA in mathematics/computer science from Mount Holyoke College. She is currently a research 
scientist at The IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center. Martino combines art, design, and algorithms in 
a technology-intersected artistic practice. Her current art-research focus is on design computation as 
it relates to computational drawing and human-computer interaction. Concerned with issues of visual language 
development within the contexts of exploration of self and cultural relevance, her artwork has been shown 
in venues such as SIGGRAPH, ISEA, and ArCade. Her written research has been published in peer-reviewed 
forums as diverse as Leonardo, IEEE Visualization (INFOVIS), SIGCHI, and AAAI. Jacquelyn Martino IBM 
T.J. Watson Research Center Yorktown Heights, New York USA jacquelyn.martino@gmail.com www.jacquelynmartino.com 
 Travel Stones. &#38;#169; 2011 Jacquelyn Martino.  &#38;#169; 2011 Jacquelyn Martino |  Leonardo, 
Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 372 373, 2011 372  Travel Stones. &#38;#169; 2011 Jacquelyn Martino.  Travel 
Stones  |  Jacquelyn Martino 373  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019362</article_id>
		<sort_key>200</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>13</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Open House]]></title>
		<page_from>374</page_from>
		<page_to>375</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019362</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019362</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>When the US housing market collapsed in 2008, so did the dreams of many middle- and lower-class Americans. Florida, California, Nevada, and Arizona were hit particularly hard, and not by a force of nature, but by the abstract and invisible hand of the market. Prior to the collapse, the movement of global capital seemed like a distant reality to most homeowners, but in the end it was the imaginary systems of value, and not bricks and mortar, that asserted the ultimate authority over our homes. <i>Open House</i> is an installation by Jack Stenner and Patrick LeMieux that allows visitors to telematically inhabit a "distressed" home in Gainesville, Florida. The house at 1617 NW 12th Road is currently in financial limbo, while undergoing the process of foreclosure due to the housing collapse. Virtual markets have transformed this otherwise livable property into a ghost house. <i>Open House</i> allows individuals to repopulate this disenfranchised space and assume the role of virtual squatters -- opening the door, flicking the lights, rattling the shutters, and remotely occupying the abandoned property. Live video feedback integrates real-time physical effects with one's virtual actions. Through <i>Open House</i>, virtual squatters can temporarily resist eviction by mirroring the market and becoming hybrid subjects occupying both virtual and physical space. Like the foolish man who builds his house on sand, we watch the architecture crumble around us. Download <i>Open House</i> at www.no-place.org/open_house.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759732</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81350567920]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jack]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Stenner]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[stenner@uf.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759733</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487647417]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Patrick]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[LeMieux]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Duke University, Durham, North Carolina]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[patrick.lemieux@duke.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Jack Stenner and Patrick LeMieux Open House When the US housing market collapsed in 2008, so did the 
dreams of many middle- and lower-class Americans. Florida, California, Nevada, and Arizona were hit particularly 
hard, and not by a force of nature, but by the abstract and invisible hand of the market. Prior to the 
collapse, the movement of global capital seemed like a distant reality to most homeowners, but in the 
end it was the imaginary systems of value, and not bricks and mortar, that asserted the ultimate authority 
over our homes. Open House is an installation by Jack Stenner and Patrick LeMieux that allows visitors 
to telematically inhabit a distressed home in Gainesville, Florida. The house at 1617 NW 12th Road is 
currently in financial limbo, while undergoing the process of foreclosure due to the housing collapse. 
Virtual markets have transformed this otherwise livable property into a ghost house. Open House allows 
individuals to repopulate this disenfranchised space and assume the role of virtual squatters opening 
the door, flicking the lights, rattling the shutters, and remotely occupying the abandoned property. 
Live video feedback integrates real-time physical effects with one s virtual actions. Through Open House, 
virtual squatters can temporarily resist eviction by mirroring the market and becoming hybrid subjects 
occupying both virtual and physical space. Like the foolish man who builds his house on sand, we watch 
the architecture crumble around us. Download Open House at www.no-place.org/open_house. Jack Stenner 
is an artist who has worked with technology, video, and installation since the mid-1990s. He is currently 
an assistant professor of art and technology at the University of Florida, School of Art and Art History. 
His work addresses issues related to our socio-culturally constructed reality and the ways we create 
meaning. He is interested in place and how meaning is embedded, manipulated, and transcoded in the environment. 
His work explores the construction of a hybrid subject : a subject that is neither entirely human nor 
machinic. Combining techniques from information retrieval and visualization, content analysis, video 
gaming, computer vision, and experimental video, he seeks to create experiences that encourage us to 
reconsider what we think we know about our world and to imagine an alternative utopia. Patrick LeMieux 
is an artist and PhD student in the Department of Art, Art History, and Visual Studies at Duke University. 
His artwork, scholarship, and teaching focus on the ethics of viewership, alternative histories of art, 
and critical game design. Investigating those puzzles, puns, riddles, and games employed by artists throughout 
the twentieth century, LeMieux builds art games featuring monochromatic mechanics, infinite inactivity, 
and simulated silence. He has exhibited artwork in the Tampa Museum of Art, Tallahassee Museum of Fine 
Arts, and the Samuel P. Harn Museum of Art. His scholarly publications are forthcoming in Digital Humani­ties 
Quarterly, Electronic Book Review, and the Leonardo Electronic Almanac. Jack Stenner University of Florida 
Gainesville, Florida USA stenner@ufl.edu Patrick LeMieux Duke University Durham, North Carolina USA patrick.lemieux@duke.edu 
www.no-place.org/open_house  Open House. &#38;#169; 2010 Jack Stenner and Patrick LeMieux.  &#38;#169; 
2011 Jack Stenner and Patrick LeMieux  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 374 375, 2011 374  Open House. 
&#38;#169; 2010 Jack Stenner and Patrick LeMieux.  Open House. &#38;#169; 2010 Jack Stenner and Patrick 
LeMieux.  Open House  |  Stenner and LeMieux 375  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019363</article_id>
		<sort_key>210</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>14</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[ItSpace]]></title>
		<page_from>376</page_from>
		<page_to>377</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019363</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019363</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>In the first version of <i>ItSpace</i> (2007), artist Peter Traub subverted the convention of the online social network by creating nine profile pages on the web site MySpace that featured everyday objects from his house. Each page had a photo of an object, a description, and, most importantly, a one-minute piece of music composed of recordings of the object being struck and resonated in various ways. The objects were "friends" with each other, and visitors to the site were invited to create new <i>ItSpace</i> pages to friend the existing ones. In the physical version of <i>ItSpace</i>, the original nine objects are brought partly back into the physical world through photographs affixed to backing boards. Each photo board has a push-button embedded in the featured object. When a visitor presses the button, it triggers a one- to two-minute remix of the object's sounds in real time. No two remixes are the same, and visitors may press multiple buttons and combine objects to create a collage. From an interface perspective, the interactive possibilities are limited by the push-button switches -- similar to how interaction and control on a site like Facebook or MySpace is limited within the tightly controlled confines of the commercial social network. In both the online and physical versions of <i>ItSpace</i>, Traub says, "I want visitors to learn something about me that could not fit into the limiting format of a personal profile. Instead, they encounter a collection of objects from where I live and listen to how I treat those objects musically and aesthetically. <i>ItSpace</i> traces connections, imagined and real, between me and these objects in my home, telling the viewer/listener about the space in which I live in a way that language cannot convey."</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759734</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487655469]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Peter]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[Michael]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Traub]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Independent Artist, Charlottesville, Virginia]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[ptraub@virginia.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Peter Michael Traub ItSpace In the first version of ItSpace (2007), artist Peter Traub subverted the 
convention of the online social network by creating nine profile pages on the web site MySpace that featured 
everyday objects from his house. Each page had a photo of an object, a description, and, most importantly, 
a one-minute piece of music composed of recordings of the object being struck and resonated in various 
ways. The objects were friends with each other, and visitors to the site were invited to create new ItSpace 
pages to friend the existing ones. In the physical version of ItSpace, the original nine objects are 
brought partly back into the physical world through photographs affixed to backing boards. Each photo 
board has a push-button embedded in the featured object. When a visitor presses the button, it triggers 
a one- to two-minute remix of the object s sounds in real time. No two remixes are the same, and visitors 
may press multiple buttons and combine objects to create a collage. From an interface perspective, the 
interactive possibilities are limited by the push-button switches similar to how interaction and control 
on a site like Facebook or MySpace is limited within the tightly controlled confines of the commercial 
social network. In both the online and physical versions of ItSpace, Traub says, I want visitors to learn 
something about me that could not fit into the limiting format of a personal profile. Instead, they encounter 
a collection of objects from where I live and listen to how I treat those objects musically and aesthetically. 
ItSpace traces connections, imagined and real, between me and these objects in my home, telling the viewer/listener 
about the space in which I live in a way that language cannot convey. Peter Traub is a composer/installationist/net 
artist currently living in Charlottesville, Virginia. He received his master s in electro-acoustic music 
from Dartmouth College in 1999 and com­pleted his PhD in 2010 in the Composition and Computer Technologies 
program at the University of Virginia. Between Dartmouth and UVA, Peter lived in the San Francisco Bay 
Area for five years and worked as a software developer for various internet start-ups. He has composed 
numerous works of electronic music, net art, and sound installations, and his works have been performed 
and exhibited internationally. ItSpace was featured on National Public Radio s Day to Day in 2008. Peter 
Michael Traub Independent Artist Charlottesville, Virginia USA ptraub@virginia.edu www.petertraub.net 
 ItSpace. &#38;#169; 2008 Peter Traub.  &#38;#169; 2011 Peter Michael Traub  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, 
No. 4, pp. 376 377, 2011 376  ItSpace. &#38;#169; 2008 Peter Traub.  ItSpace  |  Peter Michael Traub 
 377  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019364</article_id>
		<sort_key>220</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>15</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Reveries and Line Drawings]]></title>
		<page_from>378</page_from>
		<page_to>379</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019364</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019364</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>In <i>Reveries and Line Drawings</i>, a projected video piece first shown at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago's New Blood exhibition, artists Georgia Wall and Nick Bastis offer methods in which stored spatial reveries can be recalled and represented using both analog and digital technologies. The piece posits forms in which spaces can be visualized without being physically present through the use of technology and memory. This process was explored with two participants, who visualized places they had never visited: Rebecca Zorach, an art historian at the University of Chicago, visualized Art & Soul, an experimental art center founded by a street gang and the MCA in the Lawndale neighborhood of Chicago that existed from 1968 to 1972; and Andrew Norman Wilson, an MFA candidate at SAIC, visualized the home of his collaborator in Bangalore, India -- he has come to know both the person and the place through the internet.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759735</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487648324]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Georgia]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wall]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[School of the Art Institute of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[georgiarrwall@gmail.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759736</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487653643]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Nick]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bastis]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[nbastis@gmail.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Georgia Wall and Nick Bastis Reveries and Line Drawings In Reveries and Line Drawings, a projected video 
piece first shown at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago s New Blood exhibition, artists Georgia 
Wall and Nick Bastis offer methods in which stored spatial reveries can be recalled and represented using 
both analog and digital technologies. The piece posits forms in which spaces can be visualized without 
being physically present through the use of technology and memory. This process was explored with two 
partici­pants, who visualized places they had never visited: Rebecca Zorach, an art historian at the 
University of Chicago, visualized Art &#38; Soul, an experimental art center founded by a street gang 
and the MCA in the Lawndale neighborhood of Chicago that existed from 1968 to 1972; and Andrew Norman 
Wilson, an MFA candidate at SAIC, visualized the home of his collabora­tor in Bangalore, India he has 
come to know both the person and the place through the internet. Georgia Wall received her BA in 2008 
from Oberlin College in Ohio. She is currently an MFA student at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago. 
With a background in both dance and visual art, Wall s practice is grounded in performance, but her deliverables 
often take form through video and audio pieces. Wall has shown work both nationally in New York, Chicago, 
and San Francisco and abroad, in Italy, Turkey, and Canada. Nick Bastis graduated with a BA in architecture 
and geography from Middlebury College and studied at the master s level at the Royal Institute in Sweden. 
Most recently, Bastis was a visiting artist at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago and a Propeller 
Fund Grant winner through Gallery 400 and the Andy Warhol Foundation. He is currently a researcher for 
the Metropolitan Planning Council, a non-profit urban planning and advocacy group. Georgia Wall School 
of the Art Institute of Chicago Chicago, Illinois USA georgiarrwall@gmail.com Nick Bastis University 
of Chicago Chicago, Illinois USA nbastis@gmail.com www.georgiawall.com www.nickbastis.com  Reveries 
and Line Drawings. &#38;#169; 2010 Georgia Wall and Nick Bastis.  &#38;#169; 2011 Georgia Wall and Nick 
Bastis |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 378 379, 2011 378  Reveries and Line Drawings. &#38;#169; 
2010 Georgia Wall and Nick Bastis.  Reveries and Line Drawings  |  Wall and Bastis 379  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2019365</article_id>
		<sort_key>230</sort_key>
		<display_label>Pages</display_label>
		<pages>2</pages>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>16</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Third Skin]]></title>
		<page_from>380</page_from>
		<page_to>381</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2019342.2019365</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2019365</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>"Analogue becomes the new Digital" in Andrea Zapp's experiments in textile media narratives. Her work explores digital media and the mapping of collective space through fabric print, image patterns, embroidery techniques, and other formats of physical object and embellishment. <i>Third Skin</i> captures imagery of our social, digital, and urban neighborhoods and interiors and transfers them to fabric and dress design. Zapp plays with Marshall McLuhan's idea of "clothing being an extension of skin, the way that media are an extension of the body." In these pieces, photography, surveillance, and online footage become the sources for hand-manufactured dresses as media narratives. They map the collective and shared (images, digital and physical scenarios, and objects) onto the domestic: a one-off garment as individual statement and choice. Skin is explored as a media surface and as a metaphor for mapping and merging physical and digital realities. Zapp's goal here is to establish a stronger emotional link between audience and media artwork. The virtual space is framed as the other place of memory and home by capturing it in analogue paraphernalia, modeled on and manufactured from the digital. Craft and media design objects and artifacts render the digital space domestic and decorative, but with the intention of provoking a surreal and paradoxical sense of longing and belonging to a parallel world. As Zapp suggests, "the idea of a digital habitat, a shared environment, is the main driving narrative in my installations, down to the actual physical architecture in many of my earlier works resembling physical living spaces, hotels, houses, and private webcam scenarios to create related metaphors."</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>A.m</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Fine arts</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010470</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Fine arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469.10010471</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities->Performing arts</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002944</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->General and reference</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2759737</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81319504935]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Andrea]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Zapp]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Manchester Metropolitan University, Manchester, United Kingdom]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[zapp@snafu.de]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Andrea Zapp Third Skin Analogue becomes the new Digital in Andrea Zapp s experiments in textile media 
narratives. Her work explores digital media and the mapping of collective space through fabric print, 
image patterns, embroidery techniques, and other formats of physical object and embellishment. Third 
Skin captures imagery of our social, digital, and urban neighborhoods and interiors and transfers them 
to fabric and dress design. Zapp plays with Marshall McLuhan s idea of clothing being an extension of 
skin, the way that media are an extension of the body. In these pieces, photography, surveillance, and 
online footage become the sources for hand-manufactured dresses as media narratives. They map the collective 
and shared (images, digital and physical scenarios, and objects) onto the domestic: a one-off garment 
as individual statement and choice. Skin is explored as a media surface and as a metaphor for mapping 
and merging physical and digital realities. Zapp s goal here is to establish a stronger emotional link 
between audience and media artwork. The virtual space is framed as the other place of memory and home 
by capturing it in analogue paraphernalia, modeled on and manufactured from the digital. Craft and media 
design objects and artifacts render the digital space domestic and decorative, but with the intention 
of provoking a surreal and paradoxical sense of longing and belonging to a parallel world. As Zapp suggests, 
the idea of a digital habitat, a shared environment, is the main driving narrative in my installations, 
down to the actual physical architecture in many of my earlier works resembling physical living spaces, 
hotels, houses, and private webcam scenarios to create related metaphors. Andrea Zapp is a senior research 
fellow in media arts at Manchester Metropolitan University School of Art and programme leader of the 
Media Lab. She published Networked Narrative Environments as Imaginary Spaces of Being and New Screen 
Media: Cinema/Art/Narrative, with Martin Rieser. She has curated the international exhibitions StoryRooms: 
Interactive Networks, Media Art and Installations, at The Museum of Science and Industry in Manchester; 
The World is My Imagination: Media-Model-Miniature, at CUBE Gallery, Manchester; POI: Moving, Mapping, 
Memory, at Cornerhouse, Manchester; and Analogue is the New Digital, an exhibition across the digital 
networks of Manchester, in collaboration with Simon Blackmore, as part of AND Festival. She currently 
curates an online exhibition and publication on the same topic, in collaboration with the SIGGRAPH Digital 
Arts Community. She has lectured and shown her artwork at numerous international venues, museums, exhibitions, 
and festivals since the mid-1990s, including Tate Modern, BEAP, ISEA, Ars Electronica, and SIGGRAPH. 
Visit www.andreazapp.com for a full list of projects. Andrea Zapp Manchester Metropolitan University 
Manchester, United Kingdom zapp@snafu.de www.andreazapp.com  Third Skin. &#38;#169; 2011 Andrea Zapp. 
 &#38;#169; 2011 Andrea Zapp  |  Leonardo, Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 380 381, 2011 380  Third Skin. &#38;#169; 
2011 Andrea Zapp.  Third Skin  |  Andrea Zapp 381  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
	</article_rec>
	</section>
</content>
</proceeding>
