<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE proceeding SYSTEM "proceeding.dtd">
<proceeding ver="6.0" ts="04/10/2010">
<conference_rec>
	<conference_date>
		<start_date>07/12/1974</start_date>
		<end_date>07/14/1974</end_date>
	</conference_date>
	<conference_loc>
		<city><![CDATA[Boulder]]></city>
		<state>Colorado</state>
		<country></country>
	</conference_loc>
	<conference_url></conference_url>
</conference_rec>
<series_rec>
	<series_name>
		<series_id>SERIES382</series_id>
		<series_title><![CDATA[International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques]]></series_title>
		<series_vol></series_vol>
	</series_name>
</series_rec>
<proceeding_rec>
	<proc_id>563182</proc_id>
	<acronym>SIGGRAPH '74</acronym>
	<proc_desc>Proceedings of the 1st annual conference</proc_desc>
	<conference_number></conference_number>
	<proc_class>conference</proc_class>
	<proc_title>Computer graphics and interactive techniques</proc_title>
	<proc_subtitle></proc_subtitle>
	<proc_volume_no></proc_volume_no>
	<issn></issn>
	<eissn></eissn>
	<copyright_year>1974</copyright_year>
	<publication_date>07-12-1974</publication_date>
	<pages></pages>
	<plus_pages></plus_pages>
	<price><![CDATA[]]></price>
	<other_source></other_source>
	<publisher>
		<publisher_id>PUB27</publisher_id>
		<publisher_code>ACMNY</publisher_code>
		<publisher_name>ACM</publisher_name>
		<publisher_address>2 Penn Plaza, Suite 701</publisher_address>
		<publisher_city>New York</publisher_city>
		<publisher_state>NY</publisher_state>
		<publisher_country>USA</publisher_country>
		<publisher_zip_code>10121-0701</publisher_zip_code>
		<publisher_contact>Bernard Rous</publisher_contact>
		<publisher_phone>212 869-7440</publisher_phone>
		<publisher_isbn_prefix></publisher_isbn_prefix>
		<publisher_url>www.acm.org/publications</publisher_url>
	</publisher>
	<sponsor_rec>
		<sponsor>
			<sponsor_id>SP932</sponsor_id>
			<sponsor_name>ACM Special Interest Group on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques</sponsor_name>
			<sponsor_abbr>SIGGRAPH</sponsor_abbr>
		</sponsor>
	</sponsor_rec>
	<categories>
		<primary_category>
			<cat_node/>
			<descriptor/>
			<type/>
		</primary_category>
	</categories>
	<ccc>
		<copyright_holder>
			<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
			<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
		</copyright_holder>
	</ccc>
</proceeding_rec>
<content>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563183</article_id>
		<sort_key>2</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>1</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[A model for human faces that allows speech synchronized animation]]></title>
		<page_from>2</page_from>
		<page_to>2</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563183</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563183</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A parametric model for human faces is described which is capable of expression and lip animation. With this model speech synchronized animation is reduced to varying parameters in accordance with a timed speech sequence.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14111766</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100304539]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Frederic]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[I.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Parke]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563184</article_id>
		<sort_key>3</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>2</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Measuring three-dimensional surfaces with a two-dimensional data tablet]]></title>
		<page_from>3</page_from>
		<page_to>3</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563184</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563184</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[This paper describes a method for measuring the three-dimensional position of points on a surface using only a two-dimensional tablet or digitizer, standard photographic techniques and some computing power. The tablet is used to extract two-dimensional information from photographs of the surface. Data from multiple views of the surface is processed to give the three-dimensional position of points on the surface. This method has been successfully used to obtain point position data for the polygonal representation of several human faces and a human body.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14111766</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100304539]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Frederic]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[I.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Parke]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 MEASURING THREE-DIMENSIONALSURFACES WITH A TWO-DIMENSIONAL DATA TABLET by  This paper describes a 
method for measuring the three-dimensional position of points on a surface using only a two-dimensional 
tablet or digitizer, standard photographic techniques and some computing power. The tablet is used to 
extract two-dimensional information from photographs of the surface. Data from multiple views of the 
surface is processed to give the three-dimensional position of points on the surface. This method has 
been successfully used to obtain point position data for the polygonal representation of several human 
faces and a human body. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal 
or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or 
commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy 
otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission 
and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -3­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563185</article_id>
		<sort_key>4</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>3</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Computer graphics as a way of life]]></title>
		<page_from>4</page_from>
		<page_to>4</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563185</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563185</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Civilization and its requisite overhead have neatly brought us away from real-time interactions. The high priests of technology use unwieldly systems to perpetuate cybercrud--the art of using computers to put things over on people. This mentality can be countered by bringing to people systems that are easily learned and used--'habitable' systems. 'Habitability', then, is the quality of a system that makes it comfortable to learn and use.Computer graphics, is especially in a media production environment, must be highly people-oriented. This paper attempts to develop the two essential components for a people-oriented computer system--habitability and environment, using the educational media production laboratory known as the Circle Graphics Habitat as the example.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP15032129</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100432746]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Thomas]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[A.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[DeFanti]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago Circle, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P59331</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100455127]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Daniel]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Sandin]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago Circle, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14144137</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[82658669257]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Theodor]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[H.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Nelson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago Circle, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 COMPUTER GRAPHICS AS A WAY OF LIFE by . Thomas A. DeFanti, Daniel J. Sandin, and Theodor H.  Civilization 
and its requisite overhead have neatly brought us away from real-time interactions. The high priests 
of technology use unwieldly systems to perpetuate cybercrud--the art of using computers to put things 
over on people. This mentality can be countered by bringing to people systems that are easily learned 
and used--'habitable'systems. 'Habitability',then, is the quality of a system that makes itcomfortable 
to learn and use. Computer graphics, is especially in a media production environment, must be highly 
people-oriented. This paper attempts to develop the two essential components for a people-orientedcomputer 
system--habitability and environment, using the educational media production laboratory known as the 
Circle Graphics Habitat as the example.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of 
this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed 
for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first 
page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior 
specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -4­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563186</article_id>
		<sort_key>6</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>4</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Computer graphics]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[whence and hence]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>6</page_from>
		<page_to>6</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563186</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563186</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[One of the most important, far-reaching, sophisticated, and glamorous endeavors of the computer field is computer graphics. It reaches into the major computer areas of input, output, programming and debugging. It can be useful to every discipline that employs to advantage the computer. From whence came this powerful tool? What is is? What is its future? Answers to these questions are included in the scope of this article. It divides computer graphics into two main divisions - passive and interactive. The passive division includes microfilm recorders, ink pen recorders, plotters, and printers. Under the interactive division are grouped computer animation and computer-generated movies. This survey article considers the history of all the major groups of computer graphics: a discussion of the typical hardware of each; and a section on computer-aided design as well as one on computer graphics professional groups and societies, In the appendicies are a comprehensive glossary of computer graphics terminology and a bibliography of over 650 items.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP31036436</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100304865]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jackie]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[S.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Potts]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Naval Ship Research and Development Center, Bethesda, Maryland]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 COMPUTER GRAPHICS -WHENCE AND HENCE by Jackie S. Potts' One of the most important, far-reaching, sophisticated,and 
glamorous endeavors of the computer field is computer graphics. It reaches into the major computer areas 
of input, output, programming and debugging. Itcan be useful to every discipline that employs to advantage 
the computer. From whence came this powerful tool? What is is? What is its future? Answers to these questions 
are included in the scope of this article. Itdivides computer graphics into two main divisions -passive 
and interactive. The passive division includes microfilm recorders, ink pen recorders, plotters, and 
printers. Under the interactive division are grouped computer animation and computer­ generated movies. 
This survey article considers the history of all the major groups of computer graphics: a discussion 
of the typical hardware of each; and a section on computer-aideddesign as well as one on computer graphics 
professional groups and societies, In the appendicies are a comprehensive glossary of computer graphics 
terminology and a bibliography of over 650 items.  personal or classroom use is granted without fee 
provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear 
this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado 
-6­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563187</article_id>
		<sort_key>7</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>5</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Practical computer graphics for scientific users]]></title>
		<page_from>7</page_from>
		<page_to>7</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563187</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563187</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The scientific computer user presents a unique challenge to the graphics system designer. If the graphics system is properly designed and implemented, computer graphics becomes a vital research tool for the scientific user. These users' desires and expectations play an important role in every phase of the design process.This paper describes the philosophy of the graphics system at the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) and its implementation. Details of algorithms are not presented; rather the purpose has been to describe a successful computer graphics system which may serve as a guide for other designers who desire to provide practical computer graphics. This graphics system operates under a batch-mode computer system without using interactive terminals.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362677</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81450594467]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Thomas]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wright]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder, Colorado]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 PRACTICAL COMPUTER GRAPHICS FOR SCIENTIFIC USERS by Thomas J.  The scientific computer user presents 
a unique challenge to the graphics system designer. Ifthe graphics system is properly designed and implemented, 
computer graphics becomes a vital research tool for the scientific user. These users' desires and expectations 
play an important role inevery phase of the design process. This paper describes the philosophy of the 
graphics system at the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) and its implementation. Details 
of algorithms are not presented; rather the purpose has been to describe a successful computer graphics 
system which may serve as a guide for other designers who desire to provide practical computer graphics. 
This graphics system operates under a batch-mode computer system without using interactive terminals. 
 Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is 
granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage 
and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, 
to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. -7-SIGGRAPH 
74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563188</article_id>
		<sort_key>8</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>6</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Interactive computer graphics for assisting human programmers]]></title>
		<page_from>8</page_from>
		<page_to>8</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563188</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563188</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A theory exists that a graphic "transfer function" of humans may be characterizable. A computer graphic terminal trained with an understanding of this function may be capable of identifying with a human and appreciably raising the potential quality of human/computer graphic dialog. An Interactive Computer Graphic Assisted Programming (ICGAP) System is described which uses computer graphics to aid in the construction of computer graphic programs, conveniencing interactive computer graphic experiments.The rich, relatively untapped fields of art and psychology deserve computer graphic science's attention. An example of one area is the psychologist's model of the process of representationalism.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362653</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100618298]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Leo]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[T.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Sprecher]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[GTE Laboratories, Inc., Waltham, Massachusetts]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 INTERACTIVE COMPUTER GRAPHICS FOR ASSISTING HUMAN PROGRAMMERS by  A theory exists that a graphic "transfer 
function" of humans may be characterizable. A computer graphic terminal trained with an under­standing 
of this function may be capable of identifying with a human and appreciably raising the potential quality 
of human/computergraphic dialog. An Interactive Computer Graphic Assisted Programming (ICGAP) System 
is described which uses computer graphics to aid inthe construc­tion of computer graphic programs, conveniencing 
interactive computer graphic experiments. The rich, relatively untapped fields of art and psychology 
deserve computer graphic science's attention. An example of one area is the psychologist's model of the 
process of representationalism.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work 
or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed 
for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first 
page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior 
specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -8­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563189</article_id>
		<sort_key>9</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>7</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphics geometric perception and communication]]></title>
		<page_from>9</page_from>
		<page_to>9</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563189</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563189</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The Pennsylvania State University Computation Center is currently performing research and development in the areas of communication and perception to expand a user's ability to function in a dynamic interactive computer graphics environment. One aspect of this research is the development of an on-line approach to graphics comprehension and learning through user-interaction.withgeometric imagery on a cathode-ray-tube. Such geometric imagery allows fundamental concepts of computer graphics to be readily conveyed <b>to</b> the user with or without the guidance of a knowledgeable graphics programmer. This paper, together with a film, describes the nature of such an approach. The film illustrates some of the aspects of system/user interaction embodied in the geometric perception and communication package in development at the Computation Center.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362633</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100460244]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Frederick]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[R.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Stocker]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[The Pennsylvania State University, University Park, Pennsylvania]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362676</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100503333]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Thomas]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Minsker]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[The Pennsylvania State University, University Park, Pennsylvania]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 GRAPHICS GEOMETRIC PERCEPTION AND COMMUNICATION by Frederick R. Stocker and Thomas  The Pennsylvania 
State University Computation Center iscurrently performing research and development in the areas of communication 
and perception to expand a user's ability to function in a dynamic inter­active computer graphics environment. 
One aspect of this research is the development of an on-line approach to graphics comprehension and learning 
through user-interaction.withgeometric imagery on a cathode-. ray-tube. Such geometric imagery allows 
fundamental concepts of computer graphics to be readily conveyed  the user with or without the guidance 
of a knowledgeable graphics programmer. This paper, together with a film, describes the nature of such 
an approach. The film illustrates some of the aspects of system/user interaction embodied in the geometric 
perception and communication package in development at the Computation Center.  Permission to make 
digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee 
provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear 
this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior -9­ specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, 
Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563190</article_id>
		<sort_key>10</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>8</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Solution plans and interactive problem solving]]></title>
		<page_from>10</page_from>
		<page_to>10</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563190</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563190</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The concept of a "solution plan" is used to characterize the structure of interactive systems in which the user guides the solution process. A formalism for describing and analyzing solution plan structures is presented. The formalism can be used to define the role of the user in an interactive system. The solution plan approach to interaction is particularly applicable to problems which have an obvious graphical representation. An interactive graphics system for solving a class of routing problems is described. Suggestions for the application of the approach to other problems are included.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P299244</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100561873]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[William]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[E.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Howden]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California, Irvine, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 SOLUTION PLANS AND INTERACTIVE PROBLEM SOLVING by William E.  The concept of a "solution plan" is 
used to characterize the structure of interactive systems inwhich the user guides the solution process. 
A formalism for describing and analyzing solution plan structures is presented. The formalism can be 
used to define the role of the user in an interactive system. The solution plan approach to interaction 
isparticularly applicable to problems which have an ob­vious graphical representation. An interactive 
graphics system for solving a class of routing problems is described. Suggestions for the application 
of the approach to other problems are included.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or 
all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made 
or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation 
on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, 
requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -10­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563191</article_id>
		<sort_key>12</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>9</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[A graphical display system utilizing plasma panels]]></title>
		<page_from>12</page_from>
		<page_to>12</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563191</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563191</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A graphics display system utilizing recently available 512 line plasma panels interfaced to a DEC PDP-11 computer will be described. As the panel electronics allow one cell to be turned on or off each 20 &#181;s the required display processor functions are implemented in software with no loss of performance. This results in a display system with a rich instruction set as the entire PDP-11 instruction set becomes part of the graphics instruction set. Since the plasma panels combine both memory and selective erase, a unique capability has thus been achieved.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP40028710</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81314489260]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[J.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[F.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Jarvis]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Bell Telephone Laboratories, Holmdel, New Jersey]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 A GRAPHICAL DISPLAY SYSTEM UTILIZING PLASMA PANELS by J. F.  A graphics display system utilizing recently 
available 512 line plasma panels interfaced to a DEC PDP-11 computer will be described. As the panel 
electronics allow one cell to be turned on or off each 20  the required display processor functions 
are implemented in software with no loss of performance. This results in a display system with a rich 
instruction set as the entire PDP-11 instruction set becomes part of the graphics instruction set. Since 
the plasma panels combine both memory and selective erase, a unique capability has thus been achieved. 
 Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use 
is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage 
and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, 
to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 
74 Boulder, Colorado -12­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563192</article_id>
		<sort_key>13</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>10</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Multi-console intelligent satellite graphics]]></title>
		<page_from>13</page_from>
		<page_to>13</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563192</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563192</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A variety of needs, in combination, make existing configurations for interactive computer graphics unsatisfactory for our purposes. Attempts to simultaneously satisfy all of these needs, lead to a graphics system configuration that is under development for potential utilization in a variety of circumstances within the Department of the Army. It is part of an overall project, Multi-discipline Engineering Design, Evaluation and Analysis (MEDEA), to provide an integrated capability to in-house, government scientists and engineers.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362643</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100020176]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[J.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[C.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Jervert]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[US Army Electronics Command, Fort Monmouth. N. J.]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362664</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100095587]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[R.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[M.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Dunn]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[US Army Electronics Command, Fort Monmouth. N. J.]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 MULTI-CONSOLE INTELLIGENT SATELLITE GRAPHICS by J. C. Jervert and R. M.  A variety of needs, in combination, 
make existing configurations for interactive computer graphics unsatisfactory for our purposes. Attempts 
to simultaneously satisfy all of these needs, lead to a graphics system configuration that is under development 
for potential utilization in a variety of circumstances within the Department of the Army. It is part 
of an overall project, Multi-discipline Engineering Design, Eval­uation and Analysis (MEDEA), to provide 
an integrated capability to in­house, government scientists and engineers. Permission to make digital 
or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this 
notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior -13­ specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, 
Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563193</article_id>
		<sort_key>14</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>11</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[An interactive network graphics system]]></title>
		<page_from>14</page_from>
		<page_to>14</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563193</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563193</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[This paper discusses a number of issues relevant to the design of systems for performing interactive graphics over a computer network such as the ARPA Network. We then describe a working implementation of such a system and an example of its use.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP77036288</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81413600319]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Dan]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Cohen]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P340804</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100480307]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Edward]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Taft]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Xerox Palo Alto Research Center, Palo Alto, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563194</article_id>
		<sort_key>15</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>12</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Methodologies for the cost-benefit analysis of computer graphics systems]]></title>
		<page_from>15</page_from>
		<page_to>15</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563194</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563194</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[This paper assesses the state of the art in cost-benefit analyses of computer graphics systems and suggests an approach for developing improved methodology. Cost-benefit analyses are distinguished from analyses of system performance in that the latter is directed at optimizing system performance at a given level of investment, while the former is directed at justifying the investment itself.Computer graphic system design alternatives are first outlined. Then methods of analyzing the performance and costs of computer systems in general and graphic systems in particular are discussed. With this information it is shown how cost-effectiveness analyses may be performed. The next crucial step is to conduct benefit analysis, an ill-defined art. The results of benefit analysis must be combined with cost-effectiveness analysis in order to perform the desired cost-benefit analysis.An experimental methodology is suggested for better performing benefit analyses of computer graphics systems. A more rigorous formulation of the cost-benefit procedure is then outlined. No attempt is made in this report to actually perform such an analysis.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P116723</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100544759]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Ira]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[W.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Cotton]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[National Bureau of Standards, Washington, D.C.]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 METHODOLOGIES FOR THE COST-BENEFIT ANALYSIS OF COMPUTER GRAPHICS SYSTEMS by Ira W. Cotton' This paper 
assesses the state of the art incost-benefit analyses of computer graphics systems and suggests an approach 
for developing improved methodology. Cost-benefit analyses are distinguished from analyses of system 
performance in that the latter is directed at opti­mizing system performance at a given level of investment, 
while the former is directed at justifying the investment itself. Computer graphic system design alternatives 
are first outlined. Then methods of analyzing the performance and costs of computer systems in general 
and graphic systems inparticular are discussed. With this information it isshown how cost-effectivenessanalyses 
may be performed. The next crucial step is to conduct benefit analysis, an ill-defined art. The results 
of benefit analysis must be combined with cost-effectiveness analysis in order to perform the desired 
cost-benefit analysis. An experimental methodology is suggested for better performing benefit analyses 
of computer graphics systems. A more rigorous formu­lation of the cost-benefit procedure is then outlined. 
No attempt is made in this report to actually perform such an analysis. Permission to make digital or 
hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this 
notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior -15­ specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, 
Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563195</article_id>
		<sort_key>17</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>13</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Standards for network graphics communications]]></title>
		<page_from>17</page_from>
		<page_to>17</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563195</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563195</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Common protocols provide a means for the interchange of information between dissimilar systems in a computer network. This paper discusses the background and philosophy of the common graphics protocol currently under development for the ARPANET and outlines the details of its design. Other applications for such a protocol are suggested.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P116723</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100544759]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Ira]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[W.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Cotton]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[National Bureau of Standards, Washington, D.C.]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563196</article_id>
		<sort_key>18</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>14</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[An example of a pragmatic approach to portable interactive graphics]]></title>
		<page_from>18</page_from>
		<page_to>18</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563196</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563196</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Standards for graphics subroutines would encourage the coding of portable programs using graphics. However such standards do not yet exist. In this paper a small set of generally available primitive subroutines, and FORTRAN, are used to pragmatically provide a degree of portability for a second level graphics package. This package consists of only nine subroutines and yet provides considerable power for coding interactive graphical numerically oriented programs.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP42049534</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81332528065]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Lyle]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[B.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Smith]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Stanford University, Stanford, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563197</article_id>
		<sort_key>19</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>15</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Reducing graphics programming effort through structured support]]></title>
		<page_from>19</page_from>
		<page_to>19</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563197</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563197</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[This paper describes a method for structuring graphics support which simplifies the programming of interactive applications, while improving their portability by providing a device-independent interface. The primary objective is to ease the task of the application programmer in developing applications which use interaction and graphics. Common graphics functions which are used by several applications are generalized and defined in terms of transition tables. User actions become inputs, system wait points become states, and system responses are pointed to by table outputs. A suitable modification is applied to each of the generalized graphics functions to tailor it to be used by a particular application.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362666</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100603095]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Richard]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[A.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Lewallen]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Clemson University, Clemson, South Carolina]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 REDUCING GRAPHICS PROGRAMMING EFFORT THROUGH STRUCTURED SUPPORT by Richard A.  This paper describes 
a method for structuring graphics support which simplifies the programming of interactive applications, 
while improving their portability by providing a device-independentinter­face. The primary objective 
is to ease the task of the application programmer in developing applications which use interaction and 
graphics. Common graphics functions which are used by several applications are generalized and defined 
in terms of transition tables. User actions become inputs, system wait points become states, and system 
responses are pointed to by table outputs. A suitable modification isapplied to each of the generalized 
graphics functions to tailor it to be used by a particular application. Permission to make digital or 
hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this 
notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado 
-19­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563198</article_id>
		<sort_key>21</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>16</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[XPLG]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[experiences in implementing an experimental interactive graphics programming system]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>21</page_from>
		<page_to>21</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563198</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563198</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[An experiemtnal interactive graphics programming system has been built for a Xerox Sigma 5 computer based on William M. Newman's display procedures. The XPL compiler generator system was used for extending the syntax and semantics of the XPL language to produce a graphics language called XPLG. The XPLG compiler produces calls to a runtime support load module which handles windowing, viewports, clipping, boxing, 2-dimensional transformations, call naming, hit processing, etc. Independence from the numerous types of display and pointing devices is achieved by isolating all device dependent parts of the system in a separate, simple load module for each device. Several interesting implementation problems were solved.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362619</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100239042]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[C.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[Norman]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Turrill]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Washington, Seattle, Washington]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P299491</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100427828]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[William]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[R.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Mallgren]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Washington, Seattle, Washington]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 XPLG -EXPERIENCES IN IMPLEMENTING AN EXPERIMENTAL INTERACTIVE GRAPHICS PROGRAMMING SYSTEM by C. Norman 
Turrill and William R.  An experiemtnal interactive graphics programming system has been built for a 
Xerox Sigma 5 computer based on William M. Newman's display procedures. The XPL compiler generator system 
was used for extending the syntax and semantics of the XPL language to produce a graphics lan­guage called 
XPLG. The XPLG compiler produces calls to a runtime support load module which handles windowing, viewports, 
clipping, boxing, 2-dimen­sional transformations, call naming, hit processing, etc. Independence from 
the numerous types of display and pointing devices isachieved by isolating all device dependent parts 
of the system ina separate, simple load module for each device. Several interesting implementation problems 
were solved.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom 
use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial 
advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, 
to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or 
a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -21­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563199</article_id>
		<sort_key>22</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>17</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphical language features in ALGOL 68]]></title>
		<page_from>22</page_from>
		<page_to>22</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563199</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563199</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The facilities of ALGOL 68 for defining new data types and operations are used for the description and manipulation of pictures. Starting with points, polygons and strings as primitives more complex pictures may be built up with operations such as uniting of pictures, positioning, scaling, and rotation. The use of the various interactive devices is shortly discussed and a sketch of the procedure, which translates the data structure being created by a GRAPHEX68 program into a graphical assembly language, is given.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362629</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100364998]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[E.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Denert]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Technical University of Berlin, Berlin, Germany]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362634</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100203916]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[G.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Ernst]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Technical University of Berlin, Berlin, Germany]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362637</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100092664]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[H.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wetzel]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Technical University of Berlin, Berlin, Germany]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 GRAPHICAL LANGUAGE FEATURES INALGOL 68 by E. Denert, G. Ernst, H.  The facilities of ALGOL 68 for 
defining new data types and oper­ations are used for the description and manipulation of pictures. Starting 
with points, polygons and strings as primitives more complex pictures may be built up with operations 
such as uniting of pictures, positioning, scaling, and rotation. The use of the various interactive devices 
isshortly discussed and a sketch of the procedure, which translates the data structure being created 
by a GRAPHEX68 program into a graphical assembly language, is given.  Permission to make digital or 
hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this 
notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado 
-22­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563200</article_id>
		<sort_key>23</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>18</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[List processing primitives for basic]]></title>
		<page_from>23</page_from>
		<page_to>23</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563200</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563200</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[This paper describes list-processing primitives which form a component of an interactive graphics system. This system, developed at Bowling Green State University, has a plasma display panel as its central component.This system comprises a BASIC interpreter to which has been added a rich variety of graphic and list-processing primitives. These are implemented as additional BASIC verbs.The list-processing primitives permit creation of arbitrarily comples list structures: trees, multiply linked lists, etc., can all be constructed. It is possible to manipulate list and node names in a natural way. Lists, sublists, and nodes can be added and deleted, lists can be searched, and the list space dynamically reformatted if desired.The system also includes an extremely flexible mechanism for describing and manipulating data contained in a node. Several data types are available ranging from floating point to variable-length integer. It is possible to manipulate data at the bit level.This facility greatly increases the flexibility of the graphic system since it is possible to represent structural relationships between the components of a figure.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P329763</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100044570]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[David]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[L.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Fulton]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Bowling Green State University, Bowling Green, Ohio]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362667</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100635092]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Robert]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[T.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Duquet]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Bowling Green State University, Bowling Green, Ohio]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 LIST PROCESSING PRIMITIVES FOR BASIC by  This paper describes list-processingprimitives which form 
a component of an interactive graphics system. This system, developed at Bowling Green State University, 
has a plasma display panel as its central component. This system comprises a BASIC interpreter to which 
has been added a rich variety of graphic and list-processing primitives. These are implemented as additional 
BASIC verbs. The list-processingprimitives permit creation of arbitrarily comples list structures: trees, 
multiply linked lists, etc., can all be constructed. Itis possible to manipulate list and node names 
in a natural way. Lists, sublists, and nodes can be added and deleted, lists can be searched, and the 
list space dynamically re­formatted ifdesired. The system also includes an extremely flexible mechanism 
for describing and manipulating data contained ina node. Several data types are available ranging from 
floating point to variable-length integer. It is possible to manipulate data at the bit level. This 
facility greatly increases the flexibility of the graphic system since it is possible to represent structural 
relationships between the components of a figure.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part 
or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not 
made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full 
citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to 
lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. -23- SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563201</article_id>
		<sort_key>25</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>19</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[TREE]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[an interactive system for editing tree structures]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>25</page_from>
		<page_to>25</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563201</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563201</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Many existing systems provide extensive facilities for entry and manipulation of text. Typical of these are QED (Bell Telephone), TECO (MIT), TVEDIT (Stanford), and E (Yale). Text entry, insertion, deletion, search, and display are all performed interactively with a small number of key strokes. Unfortunately, similarly powerful and general interactive tools for editing of more general data structures have not been available.The system TREE provides these interactive editing facilities for tree structures. TREE enables insertion, deletion, copying, search, and display of any branch of a given tree structure. Any tree, whether a syntax tree, a decision tree, or a LISP program could be entered rapidly and changed quickly in TREE. The program itself is coded in PDP10 FORTRAN IV and will run with any of a number of inexpensive graphics terminals.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14125544</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100350487]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[J.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[W.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Lewis]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 TREE: AN INTERACTIVE SYSTEM FOR EDITING TREE STRUCTURES by J. W.  Many existing systems provide extensive 
facilities for entry and manipulation of text. Typical of these are QED (Bell Telephone), TECO (MIT), 
TVEDIT (Stanford), and E (Yale). Text entry, insertion, deletion, search, and display are all performed 
interactivelywith a small number of key strokes. Unfortunately,similarly powerful and general inter­ 
active tools for editing of more general data structures have not been available. The system TREE provides 
these interactive editing facilities for tree structures. TREE enables insertion, deletion, copying, 
search, and display of any branch of a given tree structure. Any tree, whether a syntax tree, a decision 
tree, or a LISP program could be entered rapidly and changed quickly inTREE. The program itself iscoded 
in PDP10 FORTRAN IV and will run with any of a number of inexpensive graphics terminals. Permission 
to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without 
fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies 
bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on 
servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, 
Colorado -25­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563202</article_id>
		<sort_key>26</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>20</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Implementation of transform invoking elements]]></title>
		<page_from>26</page_from>
		<page_to>26</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563202</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563202</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[An implementation technique is presented which permits display definitions to be generated by FORTRAN calls. The display definitions generated are used to refresh a non-storage display. The concept of "output processing" of display definitions has been extended to include computation on parameters addressed by the display definitions. This paper will primarily cover the implementation of "sub-picture"-call elements in these display definitions as opposed to line and text elements. These elements of a display definition specify transformed instances of other display definitions as single elements.The invoked definitions may themselves contain such sub-picture-call elements thus permitting a nested structure of display descriptions.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362652</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81541694056]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[L.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Schaefer]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Vector General Incorporated, Canoga Park, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 IMPLEMENTATION OF TRANSFORM INVOKING ELEMENTS by L.J.  An implementation technique is presented which 
permits display definitions to be generated by FORTRAN calls. The display definitions generated are used 
to refresh a non-storage display. The concept of "output processing" of display definitions has been 
extended to include computation on parameters addressed by the display definitions. This paper will primarily 
cover the implementation of "sub-picture"-call elements in these display definitions as opposed to line 
and text elements. These elements of a display definition specify transformed instances of other display 
definitions as single elements. The invoked definitions may themselves contain such sub-picture­call 
elements thus permitting a nested structure of display descriptions. Permission to make digital or hard 
copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that 
copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice 
and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute 
to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -26­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563203</article_id>
		<sort_key>27</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>21</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[An interactive fashion design system "INFADS"]]></title>
		<page_from>27</page_from>
		<page_to>27</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563203</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563203</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[This paper describes an application of a color graphic display system "INFADS" to a fashion design process using man-machine conversation. One of the main characteristics of the system is the interactive design facility created by combining a color picture processing system with a data base system. Another important characteristic is the introduction of a new recursive concept of "picture" and "texture". Some advantages of describing fashion data in a relational data base are discussed in connection with the need for data independence and the need for the semantic retrieval of pictorial data via a data description scheme.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14153096</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100435002]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Tosiyasu]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[L.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Kunii]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Tokyo, Hongo, Tokyo, Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362674</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100586980]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Takako]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Amano]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Fujitsu Ltd., Tokyo, Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14111790</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100304671]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Hiroshi]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Arisawa]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Fujitsu Ltd., Tokyo, Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362672</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100385610]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Sachiko]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Okada]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Tokyo Science University, Tokyo, Japan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 AN INTERACTIVE FASHION DESIGN SYSTEM "INFADS" by Tosiyasu L. Takako Hiroshi Sachiko This paper describes 
an application of a color graphic display system "INFADS" to a fashion design process using man-machine 
conver­sation. One of the main characteristics of the system is the inter­active design facility created 
by combining a color picture processing system with a data base system. Another important characteristic 
is the introduction of a new recursive concept of "picture" and "texture". Some advantages of describing 
fashion data in a relational data base are discussed in connection with the need for data independence 
and the need for the semantic retrieval of pictorial data via a data description scheme.  personal 
or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or 
commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy 
otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission 
and/or a fee. -27- SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563204</article_id>
		<sort_key>29</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>22</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[An image processing approach to computer graphics]]></title>
		<page_from>29</page_from>
		<page_to>29</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563204</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563204</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Computer graphics was conceived as and remains for the most part a line-drawing phenomenon. The cautious management of display lists or of in-line vector generators has captured most of the attention of researchers in computer graphics. Cathode ray tubes with randomly positionable beams have served as the primary medium for this research and development.The underlying position of this paper is that the future of computer graphics does not lie in "vectored" displays but in raster scan television, conceivably as we know it in our homes. This posture is motivated by arguments of cost and compatibility, but the most salient motivation comes in view of the ubiquitous nature of raster scan display technologies.This paper explains a way to implement an image processing approach to computer graphics, one that is conceptually straightforward and, in terms of hardware, fairly easy to design. A device is being built that encompasses as much as is known about raster scan, multi-bit per point displays. Work is described conducted, principally, to produce a multibit per point graphics output device that dynamically shares its image storage with the memory space of an expanded mini-computer.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362649</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100207961]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jeffrey]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Entwisle]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 AN IMAGE PROCESSING APPROACH TO COMPUTER GRAPHICS by Jeffrey  Computer graphics was conceived as and 
remains for the most part a line-drawing phenomenon. The cautious management of display lists or of in-line 
vector generators has captured most of the atten­tion of researchers in computer graphics. Cathode ray 
tubes with randomly positionable beams have served as the primary medium for this research and development. 
 The underlying position of this paper is that the future of computer graphics does not lie in "vectored" 
displays but in raster scan television, conceivably as we know it inour homes. This posture is motivated 
by arguments of cost and compatibility,but the most salient motivation comes in view of the ubiquitous 
nature of raster scan display technologies. This paper explains a way to implement an image processing 
approach to computer graphics, one that isconceptually straightforwardand, in terms of hardware, fairly 
easy to design. A device isbeing built that encompasses as much as is known about raster scan, multi-bit 
per point displays. Work is described conducted, principally, to produce a multi­bit per point graphics 
output device that dynamically shares its image storage with the memory space of an expanded mini-computer. 
 Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use 
is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage 
and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, 
to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. -29-SIGGRAPH 
74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563205</article_id>
		<sort_key>30</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>23</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[A general purpose, expandable processor for real-time computer graphics]]></title>
		<page_from>30</page_from>
		<page_to>30</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563205</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563205</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A class of critical computer requirements for real-time scan T.V. computer graphics is examined in relation to commercially available CPU architectures. Finding general purpose processors not suited, a new processor is proposed which is designed around the concept of "instruction set partitioning." In this design, special hardware-implemented algorithms may be included in the machine instruction set, and these processors allowed to operate asynchronously from each other. The design is projected to generate a complete new frame of a color T.V. picture every 0.1-0.8 seconds depending on image complexity. Due to its inherent generality, the CPU may be similarly expanded to encompass a wide variety of other specialized, or real-time tasks with minimal additional hardware. The 32-bit parallel processor has a design cycle time of 100 ns and is in the price class of a minicomputer.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362648</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100029506]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jeffrey]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[F.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Eastman]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North carolina]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362627</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81544495456]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[David]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[R.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wooten]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North carolina]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 A GENERAL PURPOSE, EXPANDABLE PROCESSOR FOR REAL-TIME COMPUTER GRAPHICS by Jeffrey F. Eastman and 
David R.  A class of critical computer requirements for real-time scan T.V. computer graphics is examined 
in relation to commercially available CPU architectures. Finding general purpose processors not suited, 
a new processor is proposed which is designed around the concept of "instruction set partitioning." Inthis 
design, special hardware­implemented algorithms may be included in the machine instruction set, and these 
processors allowed to operate asynchronouslyfrom each other. The design is projected to generate a complete 
new frame of a color T.V. picture every 0.1-0.8 seconds depending on image complexity. Due to its inherent 
generality, the CPU may be similarly expanded to encompass a wide variety of other specialized, or real-time 
tasks with minimal additional hardware. The 32-bit parallel processor has a design cycle time of 100 
ns and is in the price class of a minicomputer. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or 
all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made 
or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation 
on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, 
requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -30­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563206</article_id>
		<sort_key>36</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>24</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Computer graphics for half-tone three-dimentional object images]]></title>
		<page_from>36</page_from>
		<page_to>36</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563206</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563206</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A system is described for displaying studio-quality television images of objects described by a set of closed polyhedra. The objects are defined by a series of opaque planar surfaces which may obscure and intersect each other. The image description lists are passed through a scan-conversion, hidden surface removal and shading process and are converted to a real-time television signal. Display occurs through a normal T.V.system.Resolution is 512 lines by 512 dots with a color definition of 15 bits (over 32,000 colors). Generation of the display list is through an interactive language based on a tablet input and three-dimensional rotation of the boundary polygon. Color definition is through an electronic "palatte," also interactively. The system incorporates shading of the surfaces based upon the angle of the normal to the surface to the observer.The system is resident on an 8K 16-bit minicomputer which accesses a hybrid rotation array.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP39047909</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100545248]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[John]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Staudhammer]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North Carolina]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362628</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100502127]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Deborah]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Ogden]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North Carolina]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 COMPUTER GRAPHICS FOR HALF-TONE THREE-DIMENSIONAL OBJECT IMAGES by John Staudhammer and Deborah J. 
 A system isdescribed for displaying studio-qualitytelevision images of objects described by a set of 
closed polyhedra. The objects are defined by a series of opaque planar surfaces which may obscure and 
intersect each other. The image description lists are passed through a scan-conversion, hidden surface 
removal and shading process and are converted to a real-time television signal. Display occurs through 
a normal T.V.system. Resolution is512 lines by 512 dots with a color definition of 15 bits (over 32,000 
colors). Generation of the display list is through an inter­active language based on a tablet input and 
three-dimensional rotation of the boundary polygon. Color definition is through an electronic "palatte," 
also interactively. The system incorporates shading of the surfaces based upon the angle of the normal 
to the surface to the observer. The system is resident on an 8K 16-bit minicomputerwhich accesses a hybrid 
rotation array.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or 
classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial 
advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, 
to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or 
a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -36­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563207</article_id>
		<sort_key>39</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>25</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Real time animation of dynamic processes]]></title>
		<page_from>39</page_from>
		<page_to>39</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563207</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563207</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Animation and simulation processes are facilitated by the use of high level graphic languages. The results of these processes are not generally available in real time, developing of microfilm delaying the screening of the process until some time after the computer run.A technique is described which overcomes this problem whilst still allowing the use of a high level graphical language.The addition of a single feature to a "static" graphical language has transformed it into a "dynamic" graphical language allowing real time illustration of time varying processes.The technique is not restricted to the language described but may well be employed by other high level graphical languages.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP31028832</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81332517081]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[G.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[C.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Morris]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Bell-Northern Research, Ottawa, Canada]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 REAL TIME ANIMATION OF DYNAMIC PROCESSES by G. C.  Animation and simulation processes are facilitated 
by the use of high level graphic languages. The results of these processes are not generally available 
in real time, developing of microfilm delaying the screening of the process until some time after the 
computer run. A technique isdescribed which overcomes this problem whilst still allowing the use of 
a high level graphical language. The addition of a single feature to a "static" graphical language has 
transformed it into a "dynamic" graphical language allowing real time illustration of time varying processes. 
 The technique isnot restricted to the language described but may well be employed by other high level 
graphical languages.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal 
or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or 
commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy 
otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission 
and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -39­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563208</article_id>
		<sort_key>40</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>26</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[The REL animated film language]]></title>
		<page_from>40</page_from>
		<page_to>40</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563208</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563208</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Motion picture films generated by computers have now been produced by a number of groups across the country. We wish to report here on the design and implementation of the REL Animated Film Language (AFL), designed primarily for use by artists interested in the aesthetics of abstract motion graphics. The language is simple enough to be used by the artist directly, rather than by a professional programmer acting for the artist. It provides convenient means of expressing spatial and temporal changes in the shape and location of the objects with which the artist constructs his compositions. The artist uses the language to express the inter-object relationships which embody the aesthetic content of the work.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14153585</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100436761]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[F.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Thompson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP39033742</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100230790]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[R.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bigelow]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362658</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100551910]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[N.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Greenfeld]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362644</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100066750]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[J.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Odden]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362625</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100426718]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>5</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[D.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Reece]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14027105</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81413595476]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>6</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[P.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Szolovits]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 THE REL ANIMATED FILM LANGUAGE by  Motion picture films generated by computers have now been pro­duced 
by a number of groups across the country. We wish to report here on the design and implementationof the 
REL Animated Film Language (AFL), designed primarily for use by artists interested in the aesthetics 
of abstract motion graphics. The language is simple enough to be used by the artist directly, rather 
than by a professional programmer acting for the artist. Itprovides convenient means of expressing spatial 
and temporal changes in the shape and location of the objects with which the artist constructs his compositions. 
The artist uses the language to express the inter-object relationships which embody the aesthetic content 
of the work.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom 
use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial 
advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, 
to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or 
a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -40­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563209</article_id>
		<sort_key>41</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>27</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[The system design for GALATEA, an interactive real-time computer graphics system for movie and video analysis]]></title>
		<page_from>41</page_from>
		<page_to>41</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563209</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563209</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The extraction of information from movie film and videotape has always been a very tedious process. Yet the usefulness of these media in biomedical research, behavioral science, industrial testing, etc., is apparent. We are developing a system, GALATEA, for the rapid extraction of data from film or video using interactive graphics. The key aspects of GALATEA are: The user indicates what features are of interest using an x, y digitizing pen. These pen positions are the only data the system sees, so that full digital image encoding is avoided. The user can trace the features while the fim runs (frame-by-frame analysis is not necessary). The user has constant feedback in the form of an animated, computer-generatedmovie (Kinegram), overlaid on the original film image and running synchronously with it. It is this kinetic feedback of the data entered that makes the system efficient. Structured programming, real-time programming techniques, data structures for time-dependent pictures and dynamical graphics "tools" are covered. A detailed discussion is given of Slippage or soft degradation in real-time systems under fluctuating load conditions.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP31023049</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81470651582]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[R.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[P.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Futrelle]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362656</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100352220]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[M.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Potel]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 THE SYSTEM DESIGN FOR GALATEA, AN INTERACTIVE REAL-TIME COMPUTER GRAPHICS SYSTEM FOR MOVIE AND VIDEO 
ANALYSIS by R. P. Futrelle and M. J.  The extraction of information from movie film and videotape has 
always been a very tedious process. Yet the usefulness of these media in biomedical research, behavioral 
science, industrial testing, etc., is apparent. We are developing a system, GALATEA, for the rapid ex­traction 
of data from film or video using interactive graphics. The key aspects of GALATEA are: The user indicates 
what features are of interest using an x, y digitizing pen. These pen positions are the only data the 
system sees, so that full digital image encoding isavoided. The user can trace the features while the 
fim runs (frame-by-frame analysis is not necessary). The user has constant feedback in the form of an 
animated, computer-generatedmovie (Kinegram), overlaid on the original film image and running synchronouslywith 
it. It is this kinetic feedback of the data entered that makes the system efficient. Structured programming, 
real-time programming techniques, data structures for time­ dependent pictures and dynamical graphics 
"tools" are covered. A detailed discussion is given of Slippage or soft degradation in real-time systems 
under fluctuating load conditions.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this 
work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed 
for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first 
page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior 
specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -41­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563210</article_id>
		<sort_key>43</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>28</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[An interactive environment for scientific development]]></title>
		<page_from>43</page_from>
		<page_to>43</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563210</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563210</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[System Development Corporation is developing an interactive graphic scientific development system whose primary objective is ease of direction and use. This system provides an environment within which a scientific researcher--for example, an image processor--can design processes, investigate results, and guide experimental steps.The SDC system is interactive and natural. The user communicates in mathematical or graphic handwritten notation; he can use standard tools or create his own. For example, the user can draw a graph and have it saved as a function, or he can create functions using mathematical notation.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362650</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100285969]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Joan]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bebb]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[System Development Corporation, Santa Monica, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 AN INTERACTIVE ENVIRONMENT FOR SCIENTIFIC DEVELOPMENT by Joan  System Development Corporation isdeveloping 
an interactive graphic scientific development system whose primary objective is ease of direction and 
use. This system provides an environment within which a scientific researcher--forexample, an image processor--candesign 
processes, inves­tigate results, and guide experimental steps. The SDC system is interactive and natural. 
The user communicates in mathematical or graphic handwritten notation; he can use standard tools or create 
his own. For example, the user can draw a graph and have it saved as a function, or he can create functions 
using mathematical notation.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work 
or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed 
for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first 
page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior 
specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -43­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563211</article_id>
		<sort_key>44</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>29</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[A graphical programming system with speech input]]></title>
		<page_from>44</page_from>
		<page_to>44</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563211</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563211</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[An interactive programming system is described where human speech commands and computer graphic input-output facilities are used for the exchange of information between man and machine. The experimental problem solving environment is one of formulating, specifying, debugging and executing (algebraic) procedures interactively on a small processor. The speech recognition system is a real time, syntax directed, limited vocabulary, highly cost effective scheme specifically tailored to this environment. The data transformation operations of the language are verbally specified and the control flow is specified graphically as a two dimensional directed graph. The semantics of the latter structure is independent of the time sequence of its input. An input restricted (conditional input) pseudo-finite state machine model is used for the continuous syntax checking of the input on an atomic token basis and for directing the speech recognizer. The system has been successfully implemented on a small processor at the University of California, Berkeley.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362621</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100327568]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Chacko]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[C.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Neroth]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 A GRAPHICAL PROGRAMMING SYSTEM WITH SPEECH INPUT by Chacko C.  An interactive programming system isdescribed 
where human speech commands and computer graphic input-outputfacilities are used for the exchange of 
information between man and machine. The experimental problem solving environment isone of formulating, 
specifying, de­bugging and executing (algebraic) procedures interactively on a small processor. The speech 
recognition system is a real time, syntax directed, limited vocabulary, highly cost effective scheme 
specifically tailored to this environment. The data transformation operations of the language are verbally 
specified and the control flow is specified graphically as a two dimensional directed graph. The semantics 
of the latter structure is independent of the time sequence of its input. An input restricted (conditional 
input) pseudo-finite state machine model is used for the continuous syntax checking of the input on an 
atomic token basis and for directing the speech recognizer. The system has been successfully implemented 
on a small processor at the University of California, Berkeley.  Permission to make digital or hard 
copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that 
copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice 
and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute 
to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -44­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563212</article_id>
		<sort_key>46</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>30</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Occupant model for human motion]]></title>
		<page_from>46</page_from>
		<page_to>46</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563212</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563212</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A two-dimensional model of a human being has been developed for display on a computer graphic terminal. The model was designed for use with the'SIMULA program which predicts the positions of an occupant within a vehicle cabin during a crash. However, the model can also be used in the simulation of other human motions, such as walking, etc.Also presented is the design of a simple device to automatically generate movies from a terminal screen. Triggered by the bell on the terminal, one frame is taken of each position of any time-varying event, thus creating a movie depicting simulated motion.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P322586</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100242029]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[K.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[D.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Willmert]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Clarkson College of Technology, Postdam, New York]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 OCCUPANT MODEL FOR HUMAN MOTION by K. D.  A two-dimensional model of a human being has been developed 
for display on a computer graphic terminal. The model was designed for use with the'SIMULA program which 
predicts the positions of an occupant within a vehicle cabin during a crash. However, the model can also 
be used in the simulation of other human motions, such as walking, etc. Also presented is the design 
of a simple device to automatically generate movies from a terminal screen. Triggered by the bell on 
the terminal, one frame is taken of each position of any time-varying event, thus creating a movie depicting 
simulated motion. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal 
or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or 
commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy 
otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior -46­specific 
permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563213</article_id>
		<sort_key>47</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>31</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Interacting with discrete simulation using on line graphic animation]]></title>
		<page_from>47</page_from>
		<page_to>47</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563213</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563213</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[An interactive system is described which allows for the graphic construction, simulation, and simultaneous animation of an arbitrary network of guesses. A method is proposed and implemented for representing the events of a discrete simulation by a continuous animation on a graphics terminal. Techniques are presented for the display of parallel animation "sequences", and a non-trivial mapping of simulation time into animation time is described which preserves the relation order and time relationships between events. The program implemented combines this animation facility with other simulation monitoring and control features. An interactive dialogue which makes use of the lightpen and a menu of commands is implemented for the construction and modification of the queuing network. Certain relevent aspects of man-machine interaction are discussed. The usefulness of this type of approach is discussed with respect to computer-aided design applications, educational tools, and research tools.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362654</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100547441]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[M.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Alemparte]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362624</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100620927]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[D.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Chheda]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362626</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100661946]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[D.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Seeley]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14149360</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100423454]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[W.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Walker]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 INTERACTINGWITH DISCRETE SIMULATION USING ON LINE GRAPHIC ANIMATION by  An interactive system is described 
which allows for the graphic construction, simulation, and simultaneous animation of an arbitrary network 
of guesses. A method isproposed and implemented for repre­senting the events of a discrete simulation 
by a continuous animation on a graphics terminal. Techniques are presented for the display of parallel 
animation "sequences", and a non-trivial mapping of simulation time into animation time isdescribed which 
preserves the relation order and time relationships between events. The program implemented combines 
this animation facility with other simulation monitoring and control features. An interactive dialogue 
which makes use of the lightpen and a menu of commands is implemented for the construction and modification 
of the queuing network. Certain relevent aspects of man-machine interaction are discussed. The usefulness 
of this type of approach isdiscussed with respect to computer-aided design applications, educational 
tools, and research tools.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or 
personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for 
profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. 
To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific 
permission and/or a fee. -47- SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563214</article_id>
		<sort_key>48</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>32</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Searching for oil through an interactive graphic terminal]]></title>
		<page_from>48</page_from>
		<page_to>48</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563214</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563214</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[To provide greater speed and flexibility in processing geophysical exploration data, a unique interactive graphic terminal has been developed. Applications include seismic data display with zoom and translation, frequency analysis and filtering, and data correction and modification. Directly interfaced to an IBM 370, model 165 computer, this terminal provides instant access to central computational capabilities, coupled with comprehensive display facilities at the terminal itself. Through the terminal, the user views his results dynamically during processing and iteratively modifies control parameters until those results are optimum.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362617</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81430653263]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[A.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[C.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Reid]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Esso Production Research Company, Houston, Texas]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563215</article_id>
		<sort_key>49</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>33</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphical methods used in the numerical solution of Jeffery-Hamel flow at fixed flow rates]]></title>
		<page_from>49</page_from>
		<page_to>49</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563215</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563215</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A basic problem in the area of Fluid Dynamics is the solution of the Navier-Stokes equations describing the radial flow of viscous incompressible fluid between non-parallel plane walls. Since the known solutions involve transcendental equations containing elliptic functions, there are no explicit equations or methods available for determining the shape of the velocity profile for specified boundary conditions that do not require an iterative or graphical technique. The purpose of this paper is to describe the computer generated graphical solutions which allow for an easy determination of the velocity profile for fixed flow conditions. The paper will describe the step by step process of extending the solution of the problem by working back and forth between the graphical representation of the equations and the numerical solution.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362632</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100575151]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Floyd]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[LeCureux]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362646</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81538556156]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[James]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Burnett]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 GRAPHICAL METHODS USED INTHE NUMERICAL SOLUTION OF JEFFERY-HAMEL FLOW AT FIXED FLOW RATES by Floyd 
LeCureux and James  A basic problem in the area of Fluid Dynamics is the solution of the Navier-Stokes 
equations describing the radial flow of viscous incompressible fluid between non-parallel plane walls. 
 Since the known solutions involve transcendental equations containing elliptic functions, there are 
no explicit equations or methods available for determining the shape of the velocity profile for specified 
boundary conditions that do not require an iterative or graphical technique. The purpose of this paper 
is to describe the computer generated graphical solutions which allow for an easy determination of the 
velocity profile for fixed flow conditions. The paper will describe the step by step process of extending 
the solution of the problem by working back and forth between the graphical representationof the equations 
and the numerical solution. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or 
personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for 
profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. 
To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific 
permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -49­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563216</article_id>
		<sort_key>51</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>34</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphics in business decision making]]></title>
		<page_from>51</page_from>
		<page_to>51</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563216</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563216</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Mountains of data can be converted into easily digestible graphs so that decision makers can grasp the peaks and trends of economic situations and make rapid and confidential decisions.We will study how we can define simple models using a graphic-based Industrial Dynamics system (Forrester of MIT), then interact with them symbionically to obtain graphs of various manufacturing or sales considerations. We will proceed to apply graphic analysis techniques to these graphs in order to produce curves that identify the sensitivities of the analysis, to reinforce confidence in the decision to be made. Finally, we will discuss the progress and the potential of graphics in business decision making.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362641</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100160287]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Irvin]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[M.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Miller]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[IBM Corporation; A74/707, Poughkeepsie, New York]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 GRAPHICS INBUSINESS DECISION MAKING by Irvin M.  Mountains of data can be converted into easily digestible 
graphs so that decision makers can grasp the peaks and trends of economic situations and make rapid and 
confidential decisions. We will study how we can define simple models using a graphic­based Industrial 
Dynamics system (Forrester of MIT), then interact with them symbionically to obtain graphs of various 
manufacturing or sales considerations. We will proceed to apply graphic analysis techniques to these 
graphs inorder to produce curves that identify the sensitivities of the analysis, to reinforce confidence 
in the decision to be made. Finally, we will discuss the progress and the potential of graphics in business 
decision making.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal 
or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or 
commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy 
otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission 
and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado -51­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563217</article_id>
		<sort_key>52</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>35</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphics in finance]]></title>
		<page_from>52</page_from>
		<page_to>53</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563217</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563217</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Since 1969, the Boeing Company has supported the continuous development of a major interactive computing and online data base resource for direct use by its functional personnel. Interactive graphics were added in 1972 when terminal graphic equipment became affordable for widespread use in business application. Today several hundred persons are using this system daily in business, finance and management application including Tektronix 4010/4014 interactive graphic terminals and offline graphics on Stromberg Carlson 4020 hardware.The system known within Boeing as EIS (Estimating Information System) is directed by its users through the EIS command language. The language provides access to broad computational capability through free form algebraic commands, statistical analysis capability, online data input and display, data base input and retrieval in structured and nonstructured files, formal report generating capability, a collection of macro commands tailored to specific user groups and general housekeeping commands.The system accepts any combination of terminal entry and file resident commands with the result that EIS supports a wide range of applications from single use exercises where the sequence of instructions is guided by intermediate results and the availability of data to complex modeling tasks, management support programs and other repetitive processes, all of which are developed and exercised by the end user of the results.The data bases provide users efficient access to historic, current and forecast program information, organizational and economic statistics and a wide range of uniquely structure-defined data bases.The graphics capability like all other system resources is activated by a single graphics command which includes a series of customizing options. The system responds with a display appropriate to the data, the device and options selected. Graphics capability can be further integrated with the resources of the EIS Form Processor to give the user complete control over the output display.In our experience there are three conditions which must be satisfied in order to provide useful graphics service in interactive business support. First, it must be affordable. Secondly, it must be easily controllable by the user. Thirdly, graphics is significant as a support aid in some broader mission, but rarely useful as an end product in its own right.In two years of use graphics has been effective in shortening the discovery process, reducing job cost and improving the communication between business support personnel and company management.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362618</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100242008]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Barry]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Solem]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[The Boeing Company, Seattle, Washington]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 GRAPHICS INFINANCE by Barry J.  Since 1969, the Boeing Company has supported the continuous development 
of a major interactive computing and online data base resource for direct use by its functional personnel. 
Interactive graphics were added in 1972 when terminal graphic equipment became affordable for widespread 
use in business application. Today sev­ eral hundred persons are using this system daily in business, 
finance and management application including Tektronix 4010/4014 interactive graphic terminals and 
offline graphics on Stromberg Carlson 4020 hardware. The system known within Boeing as EIS (EstimatingInformation 
System) is directed by its users through the EIS command language. The language provides access to broad 
computational capability through free form algebraic commands, statistical analysis capa­bility, online 
data input and display, data base input and retrieval in structured and nonstructured files, formal report 
generating capability, a collection of macro commands tailored to specific user groups and general housekeeping 
commands. The system accepts any combination of terminal entry and file resident commands with the 
result that EIS supports a wide range of applications from single use exercises where the sequence of 
instruc­tions is guided by intermediate results and the availability of data  Permission to make digital 
or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies -52­ bear 
this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado 
to complex modeling tasks, management support programs and other re­petitive processes, all of which 
are developed and exercised by the end user of the results. The data bases provide users efficient access 
to historic, current and forecast program information, organizational and economic statistics and a 
wide range of uniquely structure-defined data bases. The graphics capability like all other system resources 
is acti­vated by a single graphics command which includes a series of custom­izing options. The system 
responds with a display appropriate to the data, the device and options selected. Graphics capability 
can be further integrated with the resources of the EIS Form Processor to give the user complete control 
over the output display. Inour experience there are three conditions which must be satis­fied inorder 
to provide useful graphics service in interactive business support. First, itmust be affordable. Secondly, 
it must be easily controllable by the user. Thirdly, graphics issignificant as a support aid insome broader 
mission, but rarely useful as an end product in its own right. Intwo years of use graphics has been effective 
inshortening the discovery process, reducing job cost and improving the communication between business 
support personnel and company management. -53­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563218</article_id>
		<sort_key>54</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>36</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphics in corporate planning]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[a case study]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>54</page_from>
		<page_to>54</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563218</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563218</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[An interactive integrated financial decision aiding system has been in use by all levels of management at IU International Management Corporation for several years. The corporate planning system is a major subsystem utilizing many management science tools. All the decision systems interact directly with corporate officers and staff via computer graphic interfaces. In addition on-line board room graphics, tape recorded graphic presentations and automatically generated manuals are among a few of the other uses made of computer graphics by the corporate planning department. This paper describes the uses of computer graphics in that corporate planning environment proposes a generalized technology to provide the needed systems for business environments.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14157756</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81537783356]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Thomas]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[H.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Johnson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 GRAPHICS IN CORPORATE PLANNING -A CASE STUDY by Thomas H.  An interactive integrated financial decision 
aiding system has been in use by all levels of management at IU International Management Corporation 
for several years. The corporate planning system is a major subsystem utilizing many management science 
tools. All the decision systems interact directly with corporate officers and staff via computer graphic 
interfaces. Inaddition on-line board room graphics, tape recorded graphic presentations and automatically 
generated manuals are among a few of the other uses made of computer graphics by the corporate planning 
department. This paper describes the uses of computer graphics inthat corporate planning environment 
 proposes a generalized technology to provide the needed systems for business environments.  Permission 
to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without 
fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies 
bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to -54­ republish, to post 
on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 
Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563219</article_id>
		<sort_key>55</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>37</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphics in business where we are and where we are going]]></title>
		<page_from>55</page_from>
		<page_to>56</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563219</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563219</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[All of us possess a naturally well-developed faculty for recognizing pattersn. Therefore, the information technology, now furnished with a new dimension in low-cost interactive graphics, is indeed ready to be of meaningful assistance in the process of decision making. How quickly its acceptance will spread among business decision makers will depend primarily upon how swiftly the inertia of habitually dealing with numbers (rather than dealing directly with implicit patterns) can be overcome. Vendors are supplying more of an end-user product today, but the situation is far from ideal; users still have to put several bits and pieces together. It is fair to assume that better quality, more efficient, and more cost-effective graphing, communications, and computational hardware will definitely be forthcoming. Also, users will find gradually more complete systems in the market. While the hardware costs will continue to decline, the software development costs are likely to keep on increasing.Hardware vendors, although in a position to amortize the software development costs over a large number of customers, are expected to keep showing reluctance at providing users with adequate applications software and the post-sales support. If the vendors are to furnish more of the end-user oriented applications software, they must be convinced of its profitability. The users can motivate vendors to concentrate on crystalization of user needs, so that they can respond with more complete products.This paper is intended to stimulate a discussion on the state of interactive graphics art and future trends, in relationship to the (business) user needs and problems. This panel member's bias is reflected above. He believes that right now the first difficult step of "getting started" needs to be taken by most users involved in the business decision-making activity, for which fairly decent products are available. The better decision support systems must be part of an evolutionary process which should be jointly embarked on by users as well as manufacturers. Neither party can do it or will try to do it alone.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362668</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81413600397]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Rohi]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Chauhan]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Tektronix, Inc., Beaverton, Oregon]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563220</article_id>
		<sort_key>58</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>38</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[CARTE]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[a thematic mapping program]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>58</page_from>
		<page_to>58</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563220</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563220</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[CARTE is the graphics display program of the LBL Computer Mapping System, producing thematic maps on microfilm at one hundredth the cost of producing negatives by hand. The program matches a geographical area with statistical data to produce graphic output on 35mm film in the form of cross-hatchedmaps for single-color printing or slides, or color separation frames for multi-color printing (either computer-generateddot screens or total mask frames for photographic screening).A versatile set of directives allows the user to design the map and a corresponding report, and to specify such features as automatic placement of area names, calculation of a smooth distribution for color coding, and boundary clipping to specified limits for sectioning a map.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362662</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100373526]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[P.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[M.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wood]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP31036732</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100312042]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[D.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[M.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Austin]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 CARTE: A THEMATIC MAPPING PROGRAM by P.M. Wood and D.M.  CARTE is the graphics display program of 
the LBL Computer Mapping System, producing thematic maps on microfilm at one hundredth the cost of producing 
negatives by hand. The program matches a geographical area with statistical data to produce graphic output 
on 35mm film in the form of cross-hatchedmaps for single-color printing or slides, or color separation 
frames for multi-color printing (either computer-generateddot screens or total mask frames for photographic 
screening). A versatile set of directives allows the user to design the map and a corresponding report, 
and to specify such features as automatic placement of area names, calculation of a smooth distri­bution 
for color coding, and boundary clipping to specified limits for sectioning a map.  Permission to make 
digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee 
provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear 
this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. -58- SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, 
Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563221</article_id>
		<sort_key>59</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>39</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[The MAPEDIT system for automatic map digitization]]></title>
		<page_from>59</page_from>
		<page_to>59</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563221</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563221</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A system for the automatic digitization of polygon boundaries is described. Digitized map files are created from a driver tape containing identification codes and approximate centroids of polygonal boundaries (e.g., census tracts), and a film image of the map. The digitizer scans on the film plane in an automatic line-following mode, producing the first stage of the map file for the editing system. The MAPEDIT system, which can be used either interactively or in batch mode, reads maps in several standard formats and provides for combining and selecting maps by census (or other) geocodes or by longitude and latitude. This system provides several stages of data compression, analysis, and verification, including algorithms for detecting straight lines, finding corners, fitting insets of maps together and matching boundaries common to a pair of polygons. Auxiliary programs (1) provide a very high resolution (1 part in 25,000) C.R.T. plot of the map, (2) allow a detailed examination and editing of the map and (3) supply missing geocodes using auxiliary tapes such as the Medlist tapes.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP39038672</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81332504714]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[H.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[H.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Holmes]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP31036732</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100312042]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[D.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[M.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Austin]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362678</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81537327656]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[W.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[H.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Benson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 THE MAPEDIT SYSTEM FOR AUTOMATIC MAP DIGITIZATION by H. H. Holmes, D.M. Austin and W. H.  A system 
for the automatic digitization of polygon boundaries is described. Digitized map files are created from 
a driver tape containing identification codes and approximate centroids of polygonal boundaries (e.g., 
census tracts), and a film image of the map. The digitizer scans on the film plane in an automatic line-followingmode, 
producing the first stage of the map file for the editing system. The MAPEDIT system, which can be used 
either interactivelyor inbatch mode, reads maps in several standard formats and provides for combining 
and selecting maps by census (or other) geocodes or by longitude and latitude. This system provides several 
stages of data compression, analysis, and verification, including algorithms for detecting straight lines, 
finding corners, fitting insets of maps together and matching bound­aries common to a pair of polygons. 
Auxiliary programs (1)provide a very high resolution (1part in 25,000) C.R.T. plot of the map, (2)allow 
a detailed examination and editing of the map and (3) supply missing geocodes using auxiliary tapes 
such as the Medlist tapes. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or 
personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for 
profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. 
To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific 
permission and/or a fee. -59- SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563222</article_id>
		<sort_key>61</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>40</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[An interactive computer graphics approach to the design of marching band routines]]></title>
		<page_from>61</page_from>
		<page_to>61</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563222</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563222</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The availability of inexpensive minicomputers and low cost digital/ analog conversion equipment enables one to use interactive graphics in situations where such techniques were previously infeasible. The University of Tulsa is presently developing an interactive graphics package entitled BANDMARCH to assist the choreography of marching band drills. The graphics hardware consist of a 32K Interdata Model 70 minicomputer, a 5MB Diablo Disc system, a Tektronix 603 monitor with 256 x 256 point display provided by a pair of Datel 8 bit D/A converters. The program enables a band director who is most likely not computer oriented to prepare a routine in an existing language (About Face, Left Flank) and view the result of his "design" in realtime. The obvious interactive features of editing, cataloguing and accessing standard functions must be provided in a way that can be easily understood.T. U.'s BANDMARCH (not an acronym) provides such features. Common data structures in a relatively novel environment are a demonstration of the soundness of these techniques to an interactive graphics situation.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362655</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100445245]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[M.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[G.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Collins]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Tulsa, Tulsa, Oklahoma]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP39027167</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100101434]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[G.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[R.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Kane]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Tulsa, Tulsa, Oklahoma]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 AN INTERACTIVE COMPUTER GRAPHICS APPROACH TO THE DESIGN OF MARCHING BAND ROUTINES by M. G. Collins 
and G. R.  The availability of inexpensive minicomputers and low cost digital/ analog conversion equipment 
enables one to use interactive graphics in situations where such techniques were previously infeasible. 
The University of Tulsa is presently developing an interactive graphics package entitled BANDMARCH to 
assist the choreography of marching band drills. The graphics hardware consist of a 32K Interdata Model 
70 minicomputer, a 5MB Diablo Disc system, a Tektronix 603 monitor with 256 x 256 point display provided 
by a pair of Datel 8 bit D/A converters. The program enables a band director who ismost likely not computer 
oriented to prepare a routine inan existing language (About Face, Left Flank) and view the result of 
his "design" in realtime. The obvious interactive features of editing, cataloguing and accessing standard 
functions must be provided ina way that can be easily understood. T. U.'s BANDMARCH (not an acronym) 
provides such features. Common data structures in a relatively novel environment are a demonstration 
of the soundness of these techniques to an interactive graphics situation.  Permission to make digital 
or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this 
notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado 
-61­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563223</article_id>
		<sort_key>62</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>41</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[An interactive design system to be taught 3D graphical-mathematical procedures]]></title>
		<page_from>62</page_from>
		<page_to>62</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563223</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563223</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A designer doing 3D mechanical layouts needs to mix graphical and mathematical operations, as for example: point to a 3D object displayed on the screen and use its location to compute a position to insert another object. It would be desirable to teach complex new procedures to the system by performing the procedure once. This would free the designer to develop procedures tailored to his own needs without relying on programming support. Thus new design applications could be readily generated. We are presently completing such a system.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP309685500</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81540330156]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Donald]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[V.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Steward]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[General Electric Company, San Jose, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362657</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100617512]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Marion]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Stedwell]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[General Electric Company, San Jose, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 AN INTERACTIVE DESIGN SYSTEM TO BE TAUGHT 3D GRAPHICAL-MATHEMATICALPROCEDURES by Donald V. Steward, 
and Marion J.  A designer doing 3D mechanicallayouts needs to mix graphical and mathematical operations, 
as for example: point to a 3D object displayed on the screen and use its location to compute a position 
to insert another object. Itwould be desirable to teach complex new procedures to the system by performing 
the procedure once. This would free the designer to develop procedures tailored to his own needs without 
relying on programming support. Thus new design applications could be readily generated. We are presently 
completing such a system.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or 
personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for 
profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. 
To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific 
permission and/or a fee. -62- SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563224</article_id>
		<sort_key>63</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>42</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Interactive computer graphics applied to the theoretical aircraft/store separation problem]]></title>
		<page_from>63</page_from>
		<page_to>63</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563224</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563224</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Recently, a computer program was developed which computes the theoretical trajectory of a store in the complex flow field after release from an aircraft flying at subsonic speeds. However, the engineer still had the exceptionally difficult problem of preparing the source and sink models which are part of the computer program input.Views of the interactive graphics console illustrate how an interactive graphics computer program (SOURCE) is used to prepare source and sink theoretical aerodynamic models for the aircraft fuselage, nacelles, fuel tanks, and store bodies. Use of this interactive graphics computer program reduces the calendar time required to develop a source and sink model from approximately 2 weeks to one hour. This reduction in required calendar time permits theoretical store separation analyses to be conducted for a store in the early development program when the store shape is frequently being changed.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362638</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100558954]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Harold]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[R.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Spahr]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Sandia Laboratories, Albuquerque, New Mexico]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362640</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100260513]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Hugh]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[A.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Sumlin]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Sandia Laboratories, Albuquerque, New Mexico]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563225</article_id>
		<sort_key>65</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>43</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[A macromodular graphics system for protein structure research]]></title>
		<page_from>65</page_from>
		<page_to>65</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563225</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563225</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A specialized graphics system has been developed for protein research; this system achieves real-time display and manipulation for line-segment models containing up to 4095 end points. The hardware consists of three components: 1) a collection of hardware subroutines assembled from digital computer building blocks called macromodules, 2) vector-matrix transformation and display equipment and 3) a small stored-program computer. This paper provides a general description of the system.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362651</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100392184]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[John]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[M.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Fritsch]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Texas Instruments, Houston, Texas]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP39030521</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100164786]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Robert]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[A.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Ellis]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362675</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100149106]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Thomas]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[H.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Jacobi]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362636</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100280765]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Garland]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[R.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Marshall]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563226</article_id>
		<sort_key>66</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>44</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Application of three-dimensional interactive graphics in x-ray crystallographic analysis]]></title>
		<page_from>66</page_from>
		<page_to>66</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563226</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563226</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[A program called XpY was written for the PDP-10/LDS-1 at the Princeton University Computer Graphics Laboratory, for generating and displaying models of dinucleoside phosphates. The molecule GpC, a member of this class and a fragment of the nucleic acid RNA, was subjected to X-ray diffraction analysis.The paper describes the importance of model building in X-ray analysis, and shows step by step how XpY was used to deduce the atomic coordinates of GpC from the experimental data. The program documentation is also included as an Appendix.A subjective critique of graphics is made in the Conclusions section.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362671</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100326760]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[S.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[D.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Stellman]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Colorado, Denver, Colorado]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 APPLICATION OF THREE-DIMENSIONAL INTERACTIVE GRAPHICS IN X-RAY CRYSTALLOGRAPHICANALYSIS by S. D. 
 A program called XpY was written for the PDP-10/LDS-1 at the Princeton University Computer Graphics 
Laboratory, for generating and displaying models of dinucleoside phosphates. The molecule GpC, a member 
of this class and a fragment of the nucleic acid RNA, was subjected to X-ray diffraction analysis. The 
paper describes the importance of model building inX-ray analysis, and shows step by step how XpY was 
used to deduce the atomic coordinates of GpC from the experimental data. The program documentation is 
also included as an Appendix. A subjective critique of graphics is made in the Conclusions section. 
 Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use 
is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage 
and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, 
to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 
74 Boulder, Colorado -66­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563227</article_id>
		<sort_key>67</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>45</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Computer graphics in simulation of cardiovascular transport phenomena]]></title>
		<page_from>67</page_from>
		<page_to>67</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563227</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563227</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Simulation is a necessary tool if we are to better understand the complexities involved in cardiovascular transport. While some of the phenomena modeled can be described analytically, perusal of the equations alone often doesn't result in full appreciation of the model system. It therefore becomes pertinent to utilize computer graphics in order to enhance simulation of physiologic transport processes. Graphic representation not only facilitates interaction between the investigator and the simulation, it provides a juxtaposition of the model to the real system, as well as a simplification of relationships between various features of the model.Increased mathematical sophistication required in the investigation of cardiovascular transport phenomena often makes traditional graphic representation cumberance. Therefore, several different types of graphics have been utilized, including 2-, 3-, and 4-dimensional displays. The methods and algorithms for these displays have been generalized to make them easy to use over a broad spectrum of applications. In some cases we have generated motion pictures of sequential model solutions which have increased and accelerated model comprehension, as well as been valuable for teaching purposes.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362661</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100316335]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[P.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[M.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Sidell]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362623</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100103048]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[D.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[U.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Anderson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362673</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100392210]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[T.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Knopp]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP309658000</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81540891156]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[J.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[B.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bassingthwaighte]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 COMPUTER GRAPHICS INSIMULATION OF CARDIOVASCULARTRANSPORT PHENOMENA by  Simulation isa necessary tool 
ifwe are to better understand the complexities involved in cardiovasculartransport. While some of the 
phenomena modeled can be described analytically, perusal of the equations alone often doesn't result 
in full appreciation of the model system. It therefore becomes pertinent to utilize computer graphics 
inorder to enhance simulation of physiologic transport processes. Graphic repre­sentation not only facilitates 
interaction between the investigator and the simulation, it provides a juxtaposition of the model to 
the real system, as well as a simplification of relationships between various features of the model. 
 Increased mathematical sophistication required inthe investigation of cardiovasculartransport phenomena 
often makes traditional graphic representation cumberance. Therefore, several different types of graphics 
have been utilized, including 2-, 3-, and 4-dimensional displays. The methods and algorithms for these 
displays have been generalized to make them easy to use over a broad spectrum of applications. In some 
cases we have generated motion pictures of sequential model solutions which have increased and accelerated 
model comprehension,as well as been valuable for teaching purposes.  Permission to make digital or hard 
copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that 
copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice 
and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute 
to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. -67-SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563228</article_id>
		<sort_key>69</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>46</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Data management for an interactive graphics system oriented to planning applications]]></title>
		<page_from>69</page_from>
		<page_to>69</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563228</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563228</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[INTRANS is a man-computer interactive graphics system, intended for analysis of urban and transportation planning problems. It is designed to operate primarily under time sharing on IBM 360-370 computers. The paper describes the functional design and the structure of the data management of INTRANS.The data management is designed to answer the specific needs of planning applications: large data sets, comparative analysis of several alternatives, and interface with batch processing computer programs. At the same time, the system is designed to operate within an environment of extremely limited resources of core and computing time.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362679</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100214355]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Yehuda]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Gur]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Creighton, Hamburg, Inc., Oak Park, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362622</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100134925]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Charles]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Biddle]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Chicago Area Transportation Study, Chicago, Illinois]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 DATA MANAGEMENT FOR AN INTERACTIVE GRAPHICS SYSTEM ORIENTED TO PLANNING APPLICATIONS by  and Charles 
 Yehuda INTRANS is a man-computer interactive graphics system, intended for analysis of urban and transportation 
planning problems. Itis designed to operate primarily under time sharing on IBM 360-370 computers. The 
paper describes the functional design and the struc­ture of the data management of INTRANS. The data 
management is designed to answer the specific needs of planning applications: large data sets, comparative 
analysis of several alternatives, and interface with batch processing computer programs. At the same 
time, the system isdesigned to operate with­inan environment of extremely limited resources of core and 
computing time.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or 
classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial 
advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, 
to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior -69­specific permission 
and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563229</article_id>
		<sort_key>70</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>47</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[The design and evaluation of an interactive geo-data analysis and display system]]></title>
		<page_from>70</page_from>
		<page_to>70</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563229</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563229</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[An interactive geo-data analysis and display system (GADS) has been implemented to support research on man-computer problem-solving. The focus is on problems involving data which can be related to a geographical location. The research goal is to develop systems which non-programmers can use to apply job-specific experience to the definition and solution of instructured problems. The systems must enable users to select, display, manipulate, and interpret data in a sequence which they determine during interaction. To support this requirement GADS provides a data extraction technique for accessing data stored in a variety of files, and a set of data analysis and display functions for conversational problem exploration and solution. In a case-study evaluation, police officers used GADS to solve a manpower allocation problem. The evaluation results identify user characteristics which the system must support and illustrate the value of interactive-problem solving systems.A video tape will show the architecture of the system and will illustrate its use in a manpower allocation problem.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14043398</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100095015]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[P.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[E.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Mantey]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[IBM Research Laboratory, San Jose, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 THE DESIGN AND EVALUATION OF AN INTERACTIVE GEO-DATA ANALYSIS AND DISPLAY SYSTEM P. E.  An interactive 
geo-data analysis and display system (GADS) has been implemented to support research on man-computer 
problem-solving. The focus ison problems involving data which can be related to a geographical location. 
The research goal isto develop systems which non-programmers can use to apply job-specific experience 
to the definition and solution of instructured problems. The systems must enable users to select, display, 
manipulate, and interpret data in a sequence which they determine during interaction. To support this 
requirement GADS provides a data extraction technique for accessing data stored ina variety of files, 
and a set of data analysis and display functions for conversational problem exploration and solution. 
Ina case-study evaluation, police officers used GADS to solve a man­power allocation problem. The evaluation 
results identify user char­acteristics which the system must support and illustrate the value of interactive-problemsolving 
systems. A video tape will show the architecture of the system and will illustrate its use ina manpower 
allocation problem.  personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made 
or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation 
on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, 
requires prior -70­specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563230</article_id>
		<sort_key>71</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>48</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[A man-machine vehicle routing and dispatching system using interactive computer graphics]]></title>
		<page_from>71</page_from>
		<page_to>71</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563230</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563230</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[Vehicle routine and dispatching is normally a dynamic process. The requirements change up to the time the vehicle is to leave on a route and in some cases new requirements occur after the vehicle has begun its trip.Rather than being a replacement for the dispatcher, the system described in this paper is a tool which the dispatcher uses to extend his capability and effectiveness. The dispatcher continues to do what he is best at, decision making in a changing evironnment, while the computer provides the data storage, the data manipulation and the visual assist of a graphics terminal. The interactive mode allows the dispatcher to use this system in a dynamic dispatching environment.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362647</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81410592772]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jdy]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[R.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Hamann]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Colorado, Boulder, Colorado]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 A MAN-MACHINE VEHICLE ROUTING AND DISPATCHING SYSTEM USING INTERACTIVE COMPUTER GRAPHICS by Jdy R. 
 Vehicle routine and dispatching is normally a dynamic pro­cess. The requirements change up to the time 
the vehicle is to leave on a route and in some cases new requirements occur after the vehicle has begun 
its trip. Rather than being a replacement for the dispatcher, the system described inthis paper is a 
tool which the dispatcher uses to extend his capability and effectiveness. The dispatcher continues to 
do what he isbest at, decision making in a changing evironnment,while the computer provides the data 
storage, the data manipulation and the visual assist of a graphics terminal. The interactive mode allows 
the dispatcher to use this system in a dynamic dispatching environment. Permission to make digital or 
hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this 
notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado 
-71­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563231</article_id>
		<sort_key>72</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>49</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Interactive graphics for transportation systems planning and design]]></title>
		<page_from>72</page_from>
		<page_to>72</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563231</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563231</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[This paper summarizes the content and findings of a three-day seminar designed to explore and assess the potential utility of interactive computer graphics for application in the transportation systems planning and design fields. The seminar was structured around the concept of finding good matches between existing technology in the interactive graphics field (capabilities) with high priority and suitable problems in the transportation planning and design fields (needs). The basic objective was to define and specify, as clearly as possible, some guidelines for the U.S. Dept. of Transportation that could assist the formulation of a DOT development and demonstration program strategy for utilizing existing technology in the computer graphics area. The seminar was structured into two parts. The first was tutorial in nature and was designed to provide the participants with an up-to-date description of capabilities and limitations. The second was a review and critique of eight resource papers, prepared especially for and prior to the seminar, which together provided twenty-two recommended development/demonstration projects. Three other recommendations were received from other sources. All twenty-five projects received a priority rating of 1 to 4. Twelve projects were rated as Priority 1 or 2. A wide variety of other recommendations are also included. Fifty persons participated in the seminar, representing a wide variety of activities in both the public and private sectors of the transportation field.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362645</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100155472]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[J.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[B.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Schneider]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Washington, Seattle, Washington]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 INTERACTIVE GRAPHICS FOR TRANSPORTATION SYSTEMS PLANNING AND DESIGN by J. B.  This paper summarizes 
the content and findings of a three-day seminar designed to explore and assess the potential utility 
of inter­active computer graphics for application inthe transportation systems planning and design fields. 
The seminar was structured around the con­cept of finding good matches between existing technology in 
the inter­active graphics field (capabilities)with high priority and suitable problems in the transportation 
planning and design fields (needs). The basic objective was to define and specify, as clearly as possible, 
some guidelines for the U.S. Dept. of Transportationthat could assist the formulation of a DOT development 
and demonstration program strategy for utilizing existing technology in the computer graphics area. The 
seminar was structured into two parts. The first was tutorial in nature and was designed to provide the 
participants with an up-to-date description of capabilities and limitations. The second was a review 
and critique of eight resource papers, prepared especially for and prior to the seminar, which together 
provided twenty-two recommended development/demonstration projects. Three other recommendations were 
received from other sources. All twenty-five projects received a priority rating of  to 4. Twelve projects 
were rated as Priority 1 or 2. A wide variety of other recom­mendations are also included. Fifty persons 
participated in the seminar, representing a wide variety of activities in both the public and private 
 sectors of the transportation field.  Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this 
work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed 
for profit or commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first 
page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior 
-72­ specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563232</article_id>
		<sort_key>74</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>50</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Graphics for data analysis]]></title>
		<page_from>74</page_from>
		<page_to>74</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563232</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563232</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[In recent years, graphics has become an essential part of modern data analysis. It is particularly useful for interactive data analysis. This paper describes a system called CLOUDS which is designed to make available on inexpensive storage tube terminals a wide range of graphic tools related to data analysis, economics, and management science. The system can be accessed nationwide by non profit organizations via the National Bureau of Economic Research computer network.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P249979</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100137119]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Roy]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[E.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Welsch]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[National Bureau of Economic Research, Inc., and Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362639</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100572577]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Helge]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bjaaland]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[National Bureau of Economic Research, Inc., and Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563233</article_id>
		<sort_key>75</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>51</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Interactive analysis and display of the electroencephalogram (EEG) in real time]]></title>
		<page_from>75</page_from>
		<page_to>76</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563233</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563233</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The development of fast, relatively inexpensive graphics terminals permits the integration of interactive display with on-line, real time signal analysis in dedicated minicomputer systems. Interactive display in the context of electroencephalogram (EEG) analysis includes: 1. control over form and parameters of an isometric plot using hidden line suppression and floating level; 2. selection of function and transform to graph; and 3. expansion or contraction of coordinate axes and time scale, from "wide angle" views of the course of several hours of recording of the entire scalp, to "telescopic" blow-ups of the details of two or three seconds of activity in a single channel.The analysis paradigms function on-line and in real time, and incorporate parallel time domain and spectral analysis on data from eight or fewer electrode placements. Spectral estimates of power and simple coherences are typically formed using ensemble averages of non-overlapping one-half to two second periodograms obtained by Fast Fourier Transform. Transient analysis uses heuristic strategies to isolate clinically significant patterns, such as the sharp paroxysmal wave forms associated with the epilepsies. Instrumental and extra-cerebral artifacts are partially eliminated by algorithms based upon heuristic criteria. Parameters of spectral and transient analysis are interactively alterable to facilitate varying experimental paradigms.To implement such systems, which can be both compute and I/0 bound, it is necessary to optimize systems software. A simple and multitasking executive coordinates program task modules. Memory space and computing time are conserved through extensive use of dynamic buffer allocation and double precision integer arithmetic.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362616</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100339995]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[A.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[S.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Gevins]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California Medical Center, San Francisco, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362620</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100252399]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[C.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[L.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Yeager]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California Medical Center, San Francisco, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14153294</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81547086956]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[S.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[L.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Diamond]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of California Medical Center, San Francisco, California]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 INTERACTIVE ANALYSIS AND DISPLAY OF THE ELECTROENCEPHALOGRAM (EEG) INREAL TIME by A. S. Gevins, C. 
L. Yeager, and S. L.  The development of fast, relatively inexpensive graphics terminals permits the 
integration of interactive display with on-line, real time signal analysis in dedicated minicomputer 
systems. Interactive display in the context of electroencephalogram(EEG) analysis includes: 1.control 
over form and parameters of an isometric plot using hidden line suppression and floating level; 2. selection 
of function and transform to graph; and 3. expansion or contraction of coordinate axes and time scale, 
from "wide angle" views of the course of several hours of recording of the entire scalp, to "telescopic" 
blow-ups of the details of two or three seconds of activity in a single channel. The analysis paradigms 
function on-line and in real time, and incor­porate parallel time domain and spectral analysis on data 
from eight or fewer electrode placements. Spectral estimates of power and simple co­herences are typically 
formed using ensemble averages of non-overlapping one-half to two second periodograms obtained by Fast 
Fourier Transform. Transient analysis uses heuristic strategies to isolate clinically signifi­cant patterns, 
such as the sharp paroxysmal wave forms associated with the epilepsies. Instrumental and extra-cerebral 
artifacts are partially elim­ inated by algorithms based upon heuristic criteria. Parameters of spectral 
and transient analysis are interactively alterable to facilitate varying experimental paradigms.  Permission 
to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without 
fee provided that copies are -75­ not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that 
copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to 
post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 
74 Boulder, Colorado To implement such systems, which can be both computeand I/0 bound, it is necessary 
to optimize systems software. A simple and multitasking executive coordinates program task modules. Memory 
space and computing time are conserved through extensive use of dynamic buffer allocation and double 
precision integer arithmetic. -76­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563234</article_id>
		<sort_key>78</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>52</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Interactive modeling system for bridges]]></title>
		<page_from>78</page_from>
		<page_to>79</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563234</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563234</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[The modeling system described in this paper was developed in conjunction with computer program called STACRB that was developed in the CURT research project at the University of Pennsylvania. In essence, the static behavior of horizontally curved and straight aligned bridge structures.The modeling system communicates with the user through a problem oriented language. The commands in this language allow the user to define the parameters that characterize the structure, modify an already completed for a structure. The commands are entered in free format and are executed interpretively, thus allowing the user to communicate with the system in a conversational mode. The user may also enter the command on punched cards and execute the routine as a non-conversational batch job. The modeling system can be used to either control the analysis or operate independently from it. In the former case, the modeling system synthesizes the structure, then calls on the STACRB program to analyze it. When the analysis is completed, the control is returned to the modeling system to interpret the results of the analysis according to the commands supplied by the user. In the latter case, the results from the modeling procedure alone are punched onto cards which may subsequently be inputted to the analysis routine.The modeling system also includes facilities for graphical displays of components of the designed structure such as structure geometry and element discretization or results of analysis such as nodal deflections, reactions and element stresses. The displays may be produced either on the line printer for conversational purposes or on a CALCOMP plotter.The overall increased efficiency introduced by the modeling system in the analysis/design cycle of a bridge structure is quite significant.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362670</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100432548]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[S.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Shore]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>PP14185049</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100533379]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[J.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[L.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wilson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362635</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100374602]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[G.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[A.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Semsarzadeh]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Arya-Mehr University of Technology, Iran]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 INTERACTIVE MODELING SYSTEM FOR BRIDGES by S.  J. L.  and G.A. The modeling system described inthis 
paper was developed in con­junction with computer program called STACRB that was developed inthe CURT 
research project at the University of Pennsylvania. Inessence, the static behavior of horizontally curved 
and straight aligned bridge structures. The modeling system communicates with the user through a problem 
oriented language. The commands inthis language allow the user to define the parameters that characterize 
the structure, modify an al­ready completed for a structure. The commands are entered in free format 
and are executed interpretively,thus allowing the user to communicate with the system in a conversational 
mode. The user may also enter the command on punched cards and execute the routine as a non-conversational 
batch job. The modeling system can be used to either control the analysis or operate independently from 
it. In the former case, the modeling system synthesizes the structure, then calls on the STACRB program 
to analyze it. When the analysis is completed, the control is returned to the modeling system to interpret 
the results of the analysis according to the commands supplied by the user. In the latter case, the results 
from the modeling procedure alone are punched onto cards which may subsequently be inputted to the analysis 
routine. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom 
use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial 
advantage and that copies -78­ bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, 
to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or 
a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado The modeling system also includes facilities for graphical displays 
of components of the designed structure such as structure geometry and element discretizationor results 
of analysis such as nodal deflections, reactions and element stresses. The displays may be produced either 
on the line printer for conversational purposes or on a CALCOMP plotter. The overall increased efficiency 
introduced by the modeling system inthe analysis/design cycle of a bridge structure is quite significant. 
 -79­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>563235</article_id>
		<sort_key>80</sort_key>
		<display_label></display_label>
		<article_publication_date>07-12-1974</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>53</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Traffic analysis and display for the San Francisco vessel traffic system]]></title>
		<page_from>80</page_from>
		<page_to>81</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/563182.563235</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=563235</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[To help improve harbor safety in the face of increasing shipping volume and vessel sites, an experimental Vessel Traffic System has been designed, fabricated, and installed in San Francisco Harbor. The Traffic Analysis and Display portion of the system uses computer generated synthetic map and text displays to provide an interactive system for up to three operators. A series of services has been designed which enable the operators to obtain radar contact information and to enter, modify, and recall text information through a series of simple keyboard actions.In addition to the interactive working displays, 4 supporting displays have been provided for designated map segments of the harbor, along with two alpha numeric displays for summary text information. A set of symbols has been developed to allow quick recognition of the vessel traffic situation by the operators.A control computer connected to three interactive display computers and five passive display units provides complete radar contact processing and display, as well as quick respond to independent operator requests for information or services. The operators can put vessels into any one of three basic categories which allows them to keep the vessels sorted and easily follow the progress of the important ones through the harbor.A background program supplements the operator actions by looking for and reporting specific trouble situations, such as collision warnings, allowing an operator to concentrate on a particular situation without fear of missing a major problem elsewhere in the harbor.]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node/>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362665</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100195078]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[R.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[G.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[King]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[The John Hopkins University, Silver Spring, Maryland]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362630</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100102722]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[F.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[S.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Gregorski]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[The John Hopkins University, Silver Spring, Maryland]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P362660</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100652824]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[P.]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[C.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Marth]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[The John Hopkins University, Silver Spring, Maryland]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 TRAFFIC ANALYSIS AND DISPLAY FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO VESSEL TRAFFIC SYSTEM by R.G. King, F. S. Gregorski, 
and P. C.  To help improve harbor safety in the face of increasing shipping volume and vessel sites, 
an experimental Vessel Traffic System has been designed, fabricated, and installed in San Francisco Harbor. 
The Traffic Analysis and Display portion of the system uses computer generated synthetic map and text 
displays to provide an interactive system for up to three operators. A series of services has been designed 
which enable the operators to obtain radar contact informa­tion and to enter, modify, and recall text 
information through a series of simple keyboard actions. Inaddition to the interactive working displays, 
4 supporting displays have been provided for designated map segments of the harbor, along with two alpha 
numeric displays for summary text information. A set of symbols has been developed to allow quick recognition 
of the vessel traffic situation by the operators. A control computer connected to three interactive 
display computers and five passive display units provides complete radar contact processing and display, 
as well as quick respond to independent operator requests for information or services. The operators 
can put vessels into any one of three basic categories which allows them to keep the vessels sorted and 
easily follow the progress of the important ones through the harbor. Permission to make digital or hard 
copies of part or all of this work or personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that 
copies are not made or distributed for profit or commercial advantage and that copies -80­bear this notice 
and the full citation on the first page. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute 
to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. SIGGRAPH 74 Boulder, Colorado A background 
program supplements the operator actions by looking for and reporting specific trouble situations, such 
as collision warnings, allowing an operator to concentrate on a particular situation without fear of 
missing a major problem elsewhere in the harbor. -81­
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>1974</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
</content>
</proceeding>
