<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE proceeding SYSTEM "proceeding.dtd">
<proceeding ver="6.0" ts="04/10/2010">
<conference_rec>
	<conference_date>
		<start_date>08/07/2011</start_date>
		<end_date>08/11/2011</end_date>
	</conference_date>
	<conference_loc>
		<city><![CDATA[Vancouver]]></city>
		<state>British Columbia</state>
		<country>Canada</country>
	</conference_loc>
	<conference_url></conference_url>
</conference_rec>
<series_rec>
	<series_name>
		<series_id>SERIES382</series_id>
		<series_title><![CDATA[International Conference on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques]]></series_title>
		<series_vol></series_vol>
	</series_name>
</series_rec>
<proceeding_rec>
	<proc_id>2037692</proc_id>
	<acronym>SIGGRAPH '11</acronym>
	<proc_desc>ACM SIGGRAPH 2011 Game Papers</proc_desc>
	<conference_number>2011</conference_number>
	<proc_class>conference</proc_class>
	<proc_title></proc_title>
	<proc_subtitle></proc_subtitle>
	<proc_volume_no></proc_volume_no>
	<isbn13>978-1-4503-0970-7</isbn13>
	<issn></issn>
	<eissn></eissn>
	<copyright_year>2011</copyright_year>
	<publication_date>08-07-2011</publication_date>
	<pages>47</pages>
	<plus_pages></plus_pages>
	<price><![CDATA[]]></price>
	<other_source></other_source>
	<abstract>
		<par><![CDATA[<p>Game Papers explore key issues in video games, inform and substantively advance our current state of knowledge and understanding, and foster new areas for investigation that will drive the next generation of design and player experience.</p>]]></par>
	</abstract>
	<publisher>
		<publisher_id>PUB27</publisher_id>
		<publisher_code>ACMNY</publisher_code>
		<publisher_name>ACM</publisher_name>
		<publisher_address>2 Penn Plaza, Suite 701</publisher_address>
		<publisher_city>New York</publisher_city>
		<publisher_state>NY</publisher_state>
		<publisher_country>USA</publisher_country>
		<publisher_zip_code>10121-0701</publisher_zip_code>
		<publisher_contact>Bernard Rous</publisher_contact>
		<publisher_phone>212 869-7440</publisher_phone>
		<publisher_isbn_prefix></publisher_isbn_prefix>
		<publisher_url>www.acm.org/publications</publisher_url>
	</publisher>
	<sponsor_rec>
		<sponsor>
			<sponsor_id>SP932</sponsor_id>
			<sponsor_name>ACM Special Interest Group on Computer Graphics and Interactive Techniques</sponsor_name>
			<sponsor_abbr>SIGGRAPH</sponsor_abbr>
		</sponsor>
	</sponsor_rec>
	<categories>
		<primary_category>
			<cat_node/>
			<descriptor/>
			<type/>
		</primary_category>
	</categories>
	<chair_editor>
		<ch_ed>
			<person_id>P2809200</person_id>
			<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81350600234]]></author_profile_id>
			<orcid_id></orcid_id>
			<seq_no>1</seq_no>
			<first_name><![CDATA[T.]]></first_name>
			<middle_name><![CDATA[L.]]></middle_name>
			<last_name><![CDATA[Taylor]]></last_name>
			<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
			<affiliation><![CDATA[IT-Universitetet i Kobenhavn]]></affiliation>
			<role><![CDATA[Conference Chair]]></role>
			<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
		</ch_ed>
	</chair_editor>
	<ccc>
		<copyright_holder>
			<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
			<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
		</copyright_holder>
	</ccc>
</proceeding_rec>
<content>
	<section>
		<section_id>2037693</section_id>
		<sort_key>10</sort_key>
		<section_seq_no>1</section_seq_no>
		<section_type>SESSION</section_type>
		<section_title><![CDATA[Analyzing player behavior and experience]]></section_title>
		<section_page_from>1</section_page_from>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037694</article_id>
		<sort_key>20</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>6</pages>
		<display_no>1</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>1</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Evaluating enjoyment within alternate reality games]]></title>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>6</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037694</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037694</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Alternate Reality Games (ARGs) are interactive narrative experiences which use the real world as the platform of the game. By bringing play out into the real world, ARGs provide players with an opportunity to enjoy both the gameplay, and benefit from the rich social experiences and physical activity which come synonymously with the genre. Due to its recent emergence, very little is known on what makes for an enjoyable ARG experience. What can we take from traditional game literature and where does this genre demand changes in our understanding? In this paper we present out work on understanding the player experience within ARGs. We look at the existing literature on enjoyment within video games, and use this to devise a set of new criteria. Through a preliminary validation of our metric, we found that a game which scores well using our analysis is significantly more likely to be enjoyed than a game which scores relatively low. In the process, we found that some of the key components of an enjoyable traditional video game experience are not so essential when considering ARGs.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[alternative reality games]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[enjoyment]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[evaluation]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[flow]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[game play]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[pervasive gaming]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>H.5.1</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Artificial, augmented, and virtual realities</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>H.5.2</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Evaluation/methodology</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>H.5.2</cat_node>
				<descriptor>User-centered design</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10003120.10003123.10010860.10010859</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Human-centered computing->Interaction design->Interaction design process and methods->User centered design</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010147.10010371.10010387.10010866</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Computing methodologies->Computer graphics->Graphics systems and interfaces->Virtual reality</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10003120.10003121.10003124.10010392</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Human-centered computing->Human computer interaction (HCI)->Interaction paradigms->Mixed / augmented reality</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10003120.10003121.10003124.10010866</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Human-centered computing->Human computer interaction (HCI)->Interaction paradigms->Virtual reality</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10003120.10003121.10003122</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Human-centered computing->Human computer interaction (HCI)->HCI design and evaluation methods</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Experimentation</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809201</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487653934]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Andrew]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[P.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Macvean]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Heriot-Watt University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[apm8@hw.ac.uk]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809202</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100096537]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Mark]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[O.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Riedl]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[riedl@cc.gatech.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>2156926</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>2156905</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Barkhuus, L., Chalmers, M., Tennent, P., Hall, M., Bell, M., Sherwood, S., and Brown, B. 2005. Picking pockets on the lawn: The development of tactics and strategies in a mobile game. In <i>Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Ubiquitous Computing</i>, Springer, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 358--374.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Barve, C., Hajarnis, S., Karnik, D., and Riedl, M. O. 2010. Wequest: A mobile alternative reality gaming platform and intelligent end-user authoring tool. In <i>Proceedings of the 6th Conference on Artificial Intelligence for Interactive Digital Entertaiment</i>.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1055072</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1054972</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Benford, S., Rowland, D., Flintham, M., Drozd, A., Hull, R., Reid, J., Morrison, J., and Facer, K. 2005. Life on the edge: Supporting collaboration in location-based experiences. In <i>Proceedings of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems</i>, ACM Press, 721--730.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Csiksentmihalyi, M. 1990. <i>The Psychology of Optimal Experience</i>. Harper Perennial.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Halliwell, S. 1987. <i>The Poetics of Aristotle, translation and Commentary</i>. Duckworth.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Hsu, S. H., Lee, F. L., and Wu, M. C. 2005. Designing action games for appealing to buyers. <i>Cyber Psychology and Behavior. 8</i>, 6 (December), 585--591.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1236238</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1236224</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jegers, K. 2007. Pervasive game flow: understanding player enjoyment in pervasive gaming. <i>ACM Computers in Entertainment 5</i>, 1 (January).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1077257</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1077246</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Magerkurth, C., Cheok, A. D., Mandryk, R. L., and Nilsen, T. 2005. Pervasive games: bringing computer entertainment back to the real world. <i>ACM Computers in Entertainment 3</i>, 3 (July).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Propp, V. 1968. <i>The Morphology of the Folktale</i>. University of Texas Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Rumelhart, D. E. 1977. Understanding and summarizing brief stories. <i>LaBerge, D., and Samuels, S. J. (eds). Basic Processes in Reading: Perception and Understanding</i>, 265--303.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Sotamaa, O. 2002. All the world's a botfighter stage: Notes on location-based multi-user gaming. In <i>Proceedings of Computer Games and Digital Content Conference</i>, Tempere University Press, 35--45.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Stewart, S., 2010. Alternate reality games. http://www.seanstewart.org/interactive/args/.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1077253</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1077246</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Sweetser, P., and Wyeth, P. 2005. Gameflow: a model for evaluating player enjoyment in games. <i>ACM Computers in Entertainment 3</i>, 3 (July).]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Evaluating Enjoyment Within Alternate Reality Games Andrew P. Macvean* Mark O. Riedl School of Mathematical 
and Computer Sciences School of Interactive Computing Heriot-Watt University Georgia Institute of Technology 
 Abstract Alternate Reality Games (ARGs) are interactive narrative experi­ences which use the real world 
as the platform of the game. By bringing play out into the real world, ARGs provide players with an opportunity 
to enjoy both the gameplay, and bene.t from the rich social experiences and physical activity which come 
synonymously with the genre. Due to its recent emergence, very little is known on what makes for an enjoyable 
ARG experience. What can we take from traditional game literature and where does this genre demand changes 
in our understanding? In this paper we present out work on understanding the player experience within 
ARGs. We look at the existing literature on enjoyment within video games, and use this to devise a set 
of new criteria. Through a preliminary validation of our metric, we found that a game which scores well 
using our anal­ysis is signi.cantly more likely to be enjoyed than a game which scores relatively low. 
In the process, we found that some of the key components of an enjoyable traditional video game experience 
are not so essential when considering ARGs. CR Categories: K.8.0 [Computing Milieux]: Personal Computing 
Games; H.5.1 [Information Interfaces and Presen­tation]: Multimedia Information Services Arti.cial, augmented, 
and virtual realities H.5.2 [Information Interfaces and Presenta­tion]: User Interfaces Evaluation / 
Methodology, User-centred design Keywords: Alternative Reality Games, Pervasive Gaming, Enjoy­ment, Flow, 
Evaluation, Game Play Links: DL PDF 1 Introduction Whether developing a video game solely for entertainment, 
or with ulterior motives such as educating or facilitating behavioural change, making for an enjoyable 
experience remains one of the most important aspects for consideration. In the ever evolving area of 
video game development, a relatively new genre known as Per­vasive Gaming has recently emerged. Pervasive 
games aim to blur the lines between the virtual world of the game and the real world of the player in 
order to bring a more immersive and entertaining game experience. One technique regularly used to facilitate 
such game­play is location tracking, using the physical location of the player *e-mail:apm8@hw.ac.uk 
e-mail:riedl@cc.gatech.edu Copyright &#38;#169; 2011 by the Association for Computing Machinery, Inc. 
Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work for personal or classroom use is 
granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for commercial advantage and that 
copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. Copyrights for components of this work 
owned by others than ACM must be honored. Abstracting with credit is permitted. To copy otherwise, to 
republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or 
a fee. Request permissions from Permissions Dept, ACM Inc., fax +1 (212) 869-0481 or e-mail permissions@acm.org. 
Sandbox 2011, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada, August 10, 2011.&#38;#169; 2011 ACM 978-1-4503-0775-8/11/0008 
$10.00 and their subsequent movement as a means of interaction with the game. By bringing the player 
out into the real world, the player can also bene.t from the type of rich social experiences and physical 
activ­ity not possible playing a console game. Magerkurth et al. explain Pervasive games are no longer 
con.ned to the virtual world do­main of the computer but integrate the physical and social aspects of 
the real world [Magerkurth et al. 2005]. Pervasive games have been studied and the Pervasive GameFlow 
Model (PGF) [Jegers 2007] was established to capture the criteria of enjoyment particu­ lar to pervasive 
games. The PGF extends Csikszentmihalyi s notion of optimal experience [Csiksentmihalyi 1990], and its 
application within traditional video gaming, to capture the unique affordances of pervasive gaming. In 
our work, we are interested in one speci.c sub-genre of perva­sive gaming known as Alternate Reality 
Games (ARGs). Layering a .ctional world over the real world, ARGs provide an interactive narrative experience 
played out in the physical world of the player. Although a sub-genre of pervasive games, the emphasis 
on the nar­rative experience brings with it even more unique and novel consid­erations not normally associated 
with game development. Through extra focus on the narrative aspects, and less emphasis on traditional 
pervasive gaming mechanics, including for example skill level and rewards, the question arrises: to what 
extent do the pre­viously devised enjoyment metrics capture the key and in.uential considerations, important 
for this style of gaming? In this paper we discuss the novel demands of ARGs and how preexisting enjoyment 
metrics are not suitable for accurately assessing enjoyment within the genre. We contribute our own metric 
for evaluating enjoyment within ARGs, highlighting where this metric can be linked to PGF and where the 
PGF model cannot capture the novel demands of the genre. Our paper is organized as follows. First, we 
provide greater detail on the sub-genre of Alternate Reality Games and provide a back­ground on evaluating 
enjoyment in games. In Section 4 we present our metric. In Section 5 we describe our preliminary study 
in order to validate the metric. Finally, we draw a set of conclusions on our metric, and how our new 
understanding relates to traditional video game enjoyment.  2 Alternate Reality Games Alternate Reality 
Games are interactive narrative experiences which work by layering a .ctional world over the real world 
of the player. As the player navigates the real world, their movement in.uences the state of the .ctional 
world. A key concept of ARGs is the believable nature of the alternative reality. One technique reg­ularly 
used within the genre is the idea that the player is not in fact playing a game at all [Sotamaa 2002]. 
Rather than simply partic­ ipating in a game, the player is made to feel that game events are actually 
real world events and thus the game should support such a way of thinking. Sean Stewart describes an 
ARG as a story which is broken into pieces which the audience must .nd and assemble [Stewart 2010]. From 
this we can establish two key principles. ARGs by de.nition are predominantly story based games. While 
other pervasive games can rely on more traditional gameplay mechanisms, for example team competition 
/ collaboration [Benford et al. 2005; Barkhuus et al. 2005] as the primary means to facilitate enjoyment, 
within ARGs the primary enjoyment mechanism comes from story based elements. Second of all, an ARG must 
have a modular story struc­ture, with the game split into small independent pieces, and subse­quently 
scattered throughout the real world. The story is then told in small sections as the player travels from 
location to location, each new place bringing a new and connected piece of the narrative. According 
to Stewart [2010], The audience is not only brought into the world because THEY are the ones responsible 
for exploring it, the audience also meaningfully affects how the story progresses. It is built in a way 
that allows players to have a key role in creating the .ction. Therefore, it is the player s responsibility 
to assem­ble the pieces , the game should allow for non linearity in the story structure and contain 
key user-decision points at which the player will make choices that affect their journey through the 
story. Where other games can follow a more linear structure and rely on other el­ements to harbor enjoyment, 
for example character personalisation, this is not the case within ARGs. From these de.nitions of what 
makes an ARG, it is clear that the emphasis is on the narrative of the game, adding unique demands and 
considerations not present within all pervasive games. 3 Game Enjoyment Csikszentmihalyi s work on Flow 
[Csiksentmihalyi 1990] (the the­ ory of an optimal experience) is widely regarded as the foundation of 
understanding enjoyment. Through his work, Csikszentmihalyi constructed a set of eight criteria which, 
if ful.lled during a task, should result in an optimal experience. As well as constructing these eight 
criteria, Csikszentmihalyi made two signi.cant .ndings on enjoyment, namely, optimal experience is the 
same all over the world, and also enjoyment is the same irrespective of social class, age or gender. 
Utilizing Csikszentmihalyi s theory on Flow, Sweetser and Wyeth developed an altered version of the model, 
designed speci.cally to capture the essence of Flow within video games [Sweetser and Wyeth 2005]. While 
this model is widely regarded as an effective evaluator of enjoyment within games, the progression of 
technol­ogy, and the subsequent novel demands brought about by pervasive games, meant that new considerations 
had to be made. An abbre­viated version of the Pervasive GameFlow model [Jegers 2007] is presented in 
Table 3, criteria listed in italics are additions which Jegers made to the existing GameFlow model. 
4 ARG Enjoyment Due to the unique demands of ARGs, an emphasis on the narra­tive aspects rather than 
traditional video game mechanisms, we are forced to question the suitability of the Pervasive GameFlow 
model for accurately capturing the key elements of an enjoyable ARG ex­perience. For example, the PGF 
model states games should in­clude online help so players don t need to exit the game . This hardly seems 
suitable when the aim of the game is to create a con­vincing alternate reality. That being said, many 
of the criteria which make up the eight elements of the PGF model are still highly ap­plicable within 
ARGs. In this section, we outline 5 key principles which we believe to make for an enjoyable ARG experience. 
Each of the criteria is then linked back to the PGF model showing the principles we are basing our work 
on. The PGF model is shown, in abbreviated form, in Table 3 at the end of this paper. Strong Narrative 
Structure -Requirement (I) This principle out­lines the need for a strong basic story, a generalised 
principle based upon traditional narrative research. (a) No dead ends, the .nal outcome should always 
be complete and meaningful. (b) The game should make use of traditional narrative elements, Propp [Propp 
1968] and Aristotel [Halliwell 1987]. (c) The game should contain a number of problems which the player 
is required to solve [Rumelhart 1977]. (d) The narrative should support the creation of both the overall 
goal of the game as well as a number of sub-goals, the resolu­tion of which will lead to the ful.lment 
of the overall goal. (e) The narrative should support the player in their progress to­wards the goal, 
making it clear how they are progressing.  This requirement links back to the following elements in 
the PGF model; Challenge (bullet 4), Control (bullet 3), Clear Goals (bullet 1, 2), Feedback (bullet 
1, 2, 3), Immersion (bullet 1, 2, 3, 4) and Social Interaction (bullet 5). Modular Structure -Requirement 
(II) Working on the basis of a story which is spread throughout the world, all game content should be 
split into small modular pieces. (a) The game should be presented in small modular pieces. (b) It should 
be the players job to assemble these pieces in what­ever manner they wish.  The modular structure requirement 
links back to the PGF notion of Challenge (bullet 3, 4) and Control (bullet 5, 6). Meaningful Story Pieces 
-Requirement (III) It is particularly im­portant in a story based game that all content is meaningful 
and plays a role in the formation of the game. As the overall goal is that a realistic and convincing 
alternate reality is being created, all elements of the game should consistently and convincingly play 
a role in the overall illusion. (a) Each piece should play a role in the overall outcome of the game. 
 (b) The pieces should appear in a logical order. (c) players should feel all elements of the game .t 
within the alter­nate reality created by the game.  The requirement of meaningful story pieces is linked 
to the PGF notion of Concentration (bullet 2, 3) and Immersion (bullet 3, 4). Interactivity -Requirement 
(IV) It is particularly important that the player is afforded the opportunity to interact with the system, 
and that the player feels such interactions were meaningful and in­.uence the direction of the story. 
(a) The decisions and actions of the player should in.uence the overall outcome of the game. (b) The 
player should feel that the decisions had an affect on the game they experience. (c) While the player 
should have control, there should be con­straints such that the player does not stray too greatly or 
feel lost in what they are trying to achieve.  The requirement of interactivity links back to the PGF 
notions of Challenge (bullet 4) and Control (bullet 1, 4, 6). Table 1: ARG Enjoyment Metric. Criteria 
Link The game contained an appropriate intro­duction I (b)(d)(e) The game contained appropriate sub goals 
at each location I (c)(d) II (a)(b) III (b)(c) V (a) The game characters were interesting and relevant 
I (b) III (a)(c) V (a) The game locations were relevant I (a) III (a)(b)(c) The game contained a satisfying 
ending I (a)(b)(d) II (b) III (a) IV (a)(b)(c) V (b) The game contained no dead ends I (a)(b) III (c) 
IV (b) The content at each location was relevant to the overall narrative II (a) III (a)(b)(c) The game 
contained interesting and varied sub-goals I (b)(c) II (b) V (a) The player was afforded control over 
the game I (c) II (b) III (a) IV (a)(b)(c) The story was modular in nature IV (a)(b) V (b) The game was 
of appropriate dif.culty I (c)(e) II (a)(b) III (a) IV (c) V (a)  Skill Level -Requirement (V) In ARGs, 
the skill is set by the content of the game alone. It is particularly important that game content is 
generalizable to a wide audience. (a) The game should be suitable for play by a general audience. Therefore, 
clues should not be personal to the developer or contain references which make no sense to a wider audience. 
 (b) The game should show progression in dif.culty, allowing for a basic introduction and culminating 
in a climatic conclusion.  The requirement of skill level links to the PGF notion of Player Skill (bullet 
1, 2, 4, 5). Based on our key principles we created a metric to assess player enjoyment within an ARG. 
In Table 1 we present the metric as a set of 11 principles along with a link to the requirements which 
were taken into consideration. 5 Validating the Metric We conducted a small scale investigation in order 
to validate our metric. Two games, one designed to score well on the metric, one to score relatively 
poor, were developed using WeQuest, an ARG authoring tool [Barve et al. 2010]. The purpose of the evaluation 
was to ensure that where we felt the game should score high / low, Figure 1: The game play interface 
showing a dialogue between the player and a NPC. so too did members of the game playing community. Further 
to this, we wanted to gather early information on what game made for a more enjoyable experience. In 
order to control external in.uences which could affect enjoyment of a narrative, for example the theme 
of the story, both games were designed with the same overall plot1, but with different narrative structures. 
5.1 Procedure Seven participants were recruited to mark both games for each of the 11 criteria in the 
metric. Each participant played each game twice, in order to explore different paths through the narrative. 
Par­ticipants played the game in a simulated environment, shown in Figure 1. The study was conducted 
in the simulated desktop envi­ronment due to the onerous nature of playing two games in the real world. 
The interface allows participants to move a small character around the map, simulating movement in the 
real world. After play­ing each game, the participants were provided with the 11 criteria, in Table 1, 
with natural language descriptions of what each criteria required. For each of the 11 criteria, participants 
rated each game on a 5-point scale. Additionally each player was asked to comment on which game they 
enjoyed playing more, in order for us to pre­liminarily assess the link between a games score in the 
metric, and how enjoyable it is to play.  5.2 Results Table 2 shows the average score each of the two 
games received for all of the 11 criteria. When referring to the Good game we mean the game designed 
to score well using the metric, while the Bad game was the game intentionally designed to score poorly. 
As one can see from Table 2, in all 11 categories, the Good game scores higher than the Bad game. The 
difference is statistically signi.cant, at most p< 0.05, in 7 of the 11 categories (marked with an *). 
The standard deviation for the Bad Game is also con­sistently higher than that of the Good game, showing 
that Bad Game was more likely to split the opinion of the players, with far more variety present in the 
results obtained. Figure 2 shows the overall average score for each game, calculated using the individ­ual 
scores for each of the 11 criteria. The Good game scored signi.cantly higher, p< 0.01 (t =3.23), than 
the Bad game. In terms of enjoyment, all 7 participants enjoyed the Good game more, conforming our hypothesis 
that a game which scores well 1The plot of a story refers to the high level outline of events. Table 
2: Results. Criteria Good Game Avg Std Dev Bad Game Avg Std Dev Appropriate Introduc­tion* 4.5 0.5 2.5 
0.8 Appropriate Sub-Goals 4.2 0.5 3 0.8 Interesting and Rele­vant Characters* 4 0.6 2.8 1.3 Relevant 
Locations 3.3 0.8 2.8 1.3 Satisfying Ending* 4 0.9 2.2 0.9 No Dead Ends* 4.7 0.8 2.2 1.2 Relevant Location 
Con­tent 4.2 0.8 3.2 1.3 Interesting Sub-Goals* 4 0.9 2.7 1.0 Overall Player Control* 4.3 0.8 2.6 1.2 
Modular 4.2 0.4 3 1.3 Dif.culty* 4.2 0.9 2.7 1.0  using the criteria, is more likely to be enjoyed than 
a game which scores relatively poorer.  6 Discussion From the results, we can see that the two games 
developed are sta­tistically different in 7 of the 11 categories, with the Good game scoring higher in 
all 11 categories. Interestingly, as our games differ signi.cantly in only 7 of the 11 categories, we 
are left to question the importance of each of the 11 categories. We therefore want to investigate the 
role each of the criteria serves in in.uencing the overall enjoyment, and in doing so, establish weightings 
in order to accommodate importance within the model. In our games, where enjoyment was based primarily 
on principles from narrative literature, and the way in which we create enjoyable stories, we can conclude 
that some of the elements from the PGF model are no longer applicable. Where traditional game literature 
examines Player Skills , they are considering the skill set required to play the game. However, in ARGs 
where the goal is to create an alternate reality, in which the player is them self, it is important that 
the skills required for the game are those they already possess. We saw from our results dif.culty does 
still play a role, but not in the same way we generally associate with video gaming. We also consider 
the importance of rewards within traditional video gam­ing. Research has shown game rewards, points, 
items, etc, play an important role within traditional video games [Hsu et al. 2005]. However, in the 
case of an ARG, the reward of the game is the unveiling of the story itself, much like what we see in 
the case of novels and movies. We see this in our results, through the statisti­cally different evaluation 
of key narrative criteria, e.g. appropriate introduction, interesting and relevant characters, no dead 
ends and satisfying ending and the role this plays in the overall enjoyment of the player. We also saw 
from our results four criteria which played no signif­icant role in the overall enjoyment of our players. 
As discussed previously, ARGs are by nature modular games. It was therefore important that both games 
developed for this evaluation were mod­ular and thus it is no surprise our participants identi.ed this. 
In our evaluation we found both games scored similarly for relevance of locations and relevance of location 
content. This is because to ensure playability, location content had to make sense, otherwise players 
would .nd themselves lost and unable to play the game. Although in our example these criteria played 
no role in the overall enjoyment observed, we hypothesise that if we were to isolate one of these criteria, 
and create games signi.cantly different in just that respect, we would see a signi.cant difference in 
the enjoyment of our players. With an insight into the metric, the next stage in the process is to gain 
a better understanding of the role each of the criteria plays on overall enjoyment. We also plan on running 
a large scale evaluation with participants playing the games out in the real world, in order to ensure 
the proposed metric remains valid. The existence of four criteria found to be insigni.cant suggests that 
we must treat ARGs differently from other pervasive games. However, even at this preliminary stage, we 
believe that the seven statistically signi.cant criteria, listed below, can be used to accu­rately evaluate 
enjoyment within an ARG: Appropriate Introduc­tion; Interesting and Relevant Characters; Satisfying Ending; 
No Dead Ends; Interesting Sub Goals; Overall Player Control; Dif.­culty. Therefore, we see this as a 
.rst step towards an understanding of this emergent genre of pervasive video gaming.  Figure 3: Comparison 
of the average individual category scores for both games.  Acknowledgements We would like to thank SICSA 
for their continued funding and sup­port. References BARKHUUS, L., CHALMERS, M., TENNENT, P., HALL, 
M., BELL, M., SHERWOOD, S., AND BROWN, B. 2005. Picking pockets on the lawn: The development of tactics 
and strategies in a mobile game. In Proceedings of the 7th International Con­ference on Ubiquitous Computing, 
Springer, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 358 374. BARVE, C., HAJARNIS, S., KARNIK, D., AND RIEDL, 
M. O. 2010. Wequest: A mobile alternative reality gaming platform and intelligent end-user authoring 
tool. In Proceedings of the 6th Conference on Arti.cial Intelligence for Interactive Digital Entertaiment. 
BENFORD, S., ROWLAND, D., FLINTHAM, M., DROZD, A., HULL, R., REID, J., MORRISON, J., AND FACER, K. 2005. 
Life on the edge: Supporting collaboration in location-based ex­periences. In Proceedings of the SIGCHI 
Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, ACM Press, 721 730. CSIKSENTMIHALYI, M. 1990. The 
Psychology of Optimal Expe­rience. Harper Perennial. HALLIWELL, S. 1987. The Poetics of Aristotle, translation 
and Commentary. Duckworth. HSU, S. H., LEE, F. L., AND WU, M. C. 2005. Designing action games for appealing 
to buyers. Cyber Psychology and Behavior. 8, 6 (December), 585 591. JEGERS, K. 2007. Pervasive game .ow: 
understanding player en­joyment in pervasive gaming. ACM Computers in Entertainment 5, 1 (January). MAGERKURTH, 
C., CHEOK, A. D., MANDRYK, R. L., AND NILSEN, T. 2005. Pervasive games: bringing computer enter­tainment 
back to the real world. ACM Computers in Entertain­ment 3, 3 (July). PROPP, V. 1968. The Morphology of 
the Folktale. University of Texas Press. RUMELHART, D. E. 1977. Understanding and summarizing brief stories. 
LaBerge, D., and Samuels, S. J. (eds). Basic Processes in Reading: Perception and Understanding, 265 
303. SOTAMAA, O. 2002. All the world s a bot.ghter stage: Notes on location-based multi-user gaming. 
In Proceedings of Com­puter Games and Digital Content Conference, Tempere Univer­sity Press, 35 45. STEWART, 
S., 2010. Alternate reality games. http://www.seanstewart.org/interactive/args/. SWEETSER, P., AND WYETH, 
P. 2005. Game.ow: a model for evaluating player enjoyment in games. ACM Computers in En­tertainment 3, 
3 (July). Table 3: Pervasive GameFlow Model. Element Criteria Element Criteria Player Skills Games must 
support player skill devel­opment and mastery 1. players should be able to start playing the game without 
reading the manual 2. learning the game should not be boring, but be part of the fun 3. games should 
include online help so players don t need to exit the game 4. players should be taught to play the game 
through tutorials or initial levels that feel like playing the game 5. players should be rewarded appropriately 
for their effort and skill development 6. game interfaces and mechanics should be easy to learn and use 
7. Pervasive games should be very .exible and enable the players skills to be developed in a pace set 
by the players Control Play­ers should feel a sense of con­trol over their actions in the game 1. players 
should feel a sense of control over their characters or units and their movements and interactions in 
the game world 2. players should feel a sense of control over the game interface and input devices 3. 
players should feel a sense of control over the game shell (starting, stopping, saving, etc.) 4. players 
should not be able to make errors that are detrimental to the game and should be sup­ported in recovering 
from errors 5. players should feel a sense of control and im­pact onto the game world (like their actions 
matter and they are shaping the game world) 6. players should feel a sense of control over the actions 
that they take and the strategies that they use and that they are free to play the game the way that 
they want (not simply discovering actions and strategies planned by the game de­velopers) 7. Pervasive 
games should enable the players to easily pick up game play in a constantly on­going game and quickly 
get a picture of the current status in the game world (in order to assess how the state of the game has 
evolved since the player last visited the game world) Clear Goals 1. overriding goals should be clear 
and presented Feedback 1. players should receive feedback on progress Games should early Players must 
toward their goals provide the 2. Pervasive games should support the players in receive appro­ 2. players 
should receive immediate feedback on player with forming and communicating their own inter­ priate feedback 
their actions clear goals at mediate goals at appropriate 3. players should always know their status 
or appropriate times score times Social Inter­ 1. games should support competition and coop- Immersion 
1. players should become less self-aware and action Games eration between players Players should less 
worried about everyday life or self should support 2. games should support social interaction be­ experience 
2. players should experience an altered sense of and create tween players (chat, etc.) deep but time 
opportunities 3. games should support social communities in­ effortless in­ 3. players should feel emotionally 
involved in for social side and outside the game volvement in the game interaction 4. Pervasive games 
should support and enable possibilities for game oriented, meaningful and purposeful social interaction 
within the gaming system 5. Pervasive games should incorporate triggers and structures (e.g. quests and 
events, fac­tions, guilds or gangs) that motivate the play­ers to communicate and interact socially the 
game 4. players should feel viscerally involved in the game 5. Pervasive games should support a seamless 
transition between different everyday contexts, and not imply or require player actions that might result 
in a violation of social norms in everyday contexts 6. Pervasive games should enable the player to shift 
focus between the virtual and physical parts of the game world without losing too much of the feeling 
of immersion Concentration 1. games should provide a lot of stimuli from dif- Challenge 1. challenges 
in games must match the players Games should ferent sources Games should skill levels require concen­ 
2. games must provide stimuli that are worth at­ be suf.ciently 2. games should provide different levels 
of chal­ tration and the tending to challenging lenge for different players player should 3. players 
shouldn t be burdened with tasks that and match the 3. Pervasive games should stimulate and support be 
able to don t feel important player s skill the players in their own creation of game sce­ concentrate 
on 4. games should have a high workload while still level narios and pacing the game being appropriate 
for the players perceptual, cognitive and memory limits 5. Pervasive games should support the player 
in the process of switching concentration be­tween in-game tasks and surrounding factors of importance 
4. Pervasive games should help the players in keeping a balance in the creation of paths and developments 
in the game world, but not put too much control or constraints on the pacing and challenge evolving 
 
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037695</article_id>
		<sort_key>30</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>5</pages>
		<display_no>2</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>2</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Visualizing and understanding players' behavior in video games]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[discovering patterns and supporting aggregation and comparison]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>6</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037695</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037695</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>As video games become more popular, there is an urge for procedures that can support the analysis and understanding of players' behaviors within game environments. Such data would inform game and level designers of game design issues that should be fixed or improved upon. By logging user-initiated events in video games, analysts have exhaustive information regarding players' actions within games. However, visualizing such data is a challenging task due to the amount of data one has to deal with; the necessity of a deep understanding of the game and players' possible actions within the game plus a deep understanding of questions one wants to answer; the computation that has to be done on the data; and the limitations and/or complexities of current analysis tools. In this paper, we present a new visualization system that allows analysts to build visualization and interact with telemetry data, to identify patterns and identify game design issues efficiently. Besides the system itself, we propose a new approach to visualize players' behavior that has not been explored so far. For example, instead of using heat maps to visualize a single metric (e.g. deaths), our system allows analysts to superimpose and visualize a series of actions players take in the game. This is especially important when one should understand cause and effect within the game. We present examples of the visualizations using an RPG game, Dragon Age Origins (BioWare/EA, 2009). It should be noted that the system is currently under development and testing with analysts working at BioWare.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[players' behavior]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[telemetry data]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[visualization]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[visualization system]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[visualizations]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>I.5.2</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Pattern analysis</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010147.10010257</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Computing methodologies->Machine learning</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Algorithms</gt>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Experimentation</gt>
			<gt>Human Factors</gt>
			<gt>Measurement</gt>
			<gt>Performance</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809203</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81443594456]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Dinara]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Moura]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Simon Fraser University-SIAT, Surrey, BC, Canada]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[dinara@sfu.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809204</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81488653825]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Magy]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[Seif]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[el-Nasr]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Simon Fraser University-SIAT, Surrey, BC, Canada]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[magy@sfu.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809205</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100396860]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Christopher]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[D.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Shaw]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Simon Fraser University-SIAT, Surrey, BC, Canada]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[shaw@sfu.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1176160</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1175891</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Chittaro, L., Ranon, R., & Ieronutti, L. (2006). VU-Flow: A Visualization Tool for Analyzing Navigation in Virtual Environments. <i>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 12</i>(6), 1475--1485.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1463034</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1340738</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Coulton, P., Bamford, W., Cheverst, Pk., & Rashid, O. (2008). 3D Space-Time Visualization of Player Behaviour in Pervasive Location-Based Games. <i>International Journal of Computer Games Technology</i>.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1621875</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1621841</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Drachen, A., & Canossa, A. (2009). Analyzing spatial user behavior in computer games using geographic information systems. <i>Proceedings of the 13th International MindTrek Conference: Everyday Life in the Ubiquitous Era on - MindTrek '09</i> (p. 182). Presented at the the 13th International MindTrek Conference: Everyday Life in the Ubiquitous Era, Tampere, Finland.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1034444</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1032664</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Hoobler, N., Humphreys, G., & Agrawala, M. (2004). Visualizing competitive behaviors in multi-user virtual environments. <i>IEEE Visualization 2004</i> (pp. 163--170). Presented at the IEEE Visualization 2004, Austin, TX, USA.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Hopkins, C. (2010, April 28). Second Life Economy At Record High. <i>Read Write Web</i>. Retrieved from http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/second_life_econom_at_record_high.php]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Isbister, K., & Schaffer, N. (2008). <i>Game Usability: Advancing the Player Experience</i>. Morgan Kaufmann.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jenkins, H. (2006). <i>Convergence Culture: Where Old and New Media Collide</i> (illustrated edition.). NYU Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Kennerly, D. (2003). Better Game Design Through Data Mining. <i>Gamasutra</i>. Retrieved December 14, 2010, from http://www.gamasutra.com/view/feature/2816/better_game_design_through_data_.php]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1357126</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1357054</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Kim, J. H., Gunn, D. V., Schuh, E., Phillips, B., Pagulayan, R. J., & Wixon, D. (2008). Tracking real-time user experience (TRUE): a comprehensive instrumentation solution for complex systems. <i>Proceeding of the twenty-sixth annual CHI conference on Human factors in computing systems - CHI '08</i> (p. 443). Presented at the Proceeding of the twenty-sixth annual CHI conference, Florence, Italy.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Romero, R. (2008). <i>Successful Instrumentation</i>. Presented at the Game Developers Conference.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[The Entertainment Software Association. (2010). The Transformation of the Video Game Industry. Retrieved September 22, 2010, from http://www.theesa.com/gamesindailylife/transformation.asp]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Turkle, S. (2003). Video games and computer holding power. <i>The New Media Reader</i>. The MIT Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1972514</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Witten, I. H., Frank, E., & Hall, M. A. (2011). <i>Data Mining: Practical Machine Learning Tools and Techniques, Third Edition</i> (3rd ed.). Morgan Kaufmann.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Zoeller, G. (2010). <i>Development Telemetry in Video Games Projects</i>. Presented at the Game Developers Conference 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Visualizing and Understanding Players Behavior in Video Games: Discovering Patterns and Supporting Aggregation 
and Comparison Dinara Moura Magy Seif el-Nasr Christopher D. Shaw Simon Fraser University-SIAT Simon 
Fraser University-SIAT Simon Fraser University-SIAT Surrey, BC, Canada V3T 0A3 Surrey, BC, Canada V3T 
0A3 Surrey, BC, Canada V3T 0A3 dinara@sfu.ca magy@sfu.ca shaw@sfu.ca ABSTRACT As video games become 
more popular, there is an urge for procedures that can support the analysis and understanding of players 
behaviors within game environments. Such data would inform game and level designers of game design issues 
that should be fixed or improved upon. By logging user-initiated events in video games, analysts have 
exhaustive information regarding players actions within games. However, visualizing such data is a challenging 
task due to the amount of data one has to deal with; the necessity of a deep understanding of the game 
and players possible actions within the game plus a deep understanding of questions one wants to answer; 
the computation that has to be done on the data; and the limitations and/or complexities of current analysis 
tools. In this paper, we present a new visualization system that allows analysts to build visualization 
and interact with telemetry data, to identify patterns and identify game design issues efficiently. Besides 
the system itself, we propose a new approach to visualize players behavior that has not been explored 
so far. For example, instead of using heat maps to visualize a single metric (e.g. deaths), our system 
allows analysts to superimpose and visualize a series of actions players take in the game. This is especially 
important when one should understand cause and effect within the game. We present examples of the visualizations 
using an RPG game, Dragon Age Origins (BioWare/EA, 2009). It should be noted that the system is currently 
under development and testing with analysts working at BioWare. General Terms Visualization, Telemetry 
Data  Keywords Players behavior, Visualizations, Visualization System 1 INTRODUCTION As games gain more 
popularity (Jenkins, 2006; The Entertainment Software Association, 2010; Turkle, 2003), designers start 
to feel the pressing need to adapt their designs to cater to a wide diverse market. Thus, understanding 
how different players interact and progress within video games is obligatory. For example, for role­playing 
games (RPGs), designers need to verify if design goals are Copyright &#38;#169; 2011 by the Association 
for Computing Machinery, Inc. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work for 
personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for 
commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. Copyrights 
for components of this work owned by others than ACM must be honored. Abstracting with credit is permitted. 
To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific 
permission and/or a fee. Request permissions from Permissions Dept, ACM Inc., fax +1 (212) 869-0481 or 
e-mail permissions@acm.org. Sandbox 2011, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada, August 10, 2011.&#38;#169; 
2011 ACM 978-1-4503-0775-8/11/0008 $10.00 being achieved, including if players appropriately navigate 
through the environment and if they find and collect key items, just to mention a few. As a result, game 
companies have invested time, effort and money to collect such information and test their designs through 
different methods (Isbister and Schaffer, 2008). Recently, there has been a move towards collecting player 
activities through logging user actions. This process is called instrumentation (Kim et al., 2008). Its 
outcome is telemetry data a quantitative record of player-game interactions. Many companies use telemetry 
to uncover system crashes and bugs (Zoeller, 2010). Also, telemetry data allows analysts to assess virtual 
economy (Hopkins, 2010) and catch cheaters (Kennerly, 2003). While those applications are useful, using 
telemetry to analyze player behavior, uncovering design issues, has received little attention. Most current 
work uses visualization methods such as heatmaps and bar charts to represent actions aggregated over 
many players and playthroughs (e.g., Drachen and Canossa (2009). Such methods are limited in analyzing 
temporal progression of players within a game, which is crucial for games like RPGs. Visualizing and 
making sense of telemetry data is challenging due to the large amount of information involved and the 
limitations of current analysis tools. More generic analysis tools may be used but are too complex and 
expensive for design studios. Therefore, more work is needed to develop specialized visualization tools, 
allowing analysts and designers to make sense of telemetry data more efficiently (Romero, 2008). In this 
paper we address this problem by proposing a novel interactive visualization system specialized for video 
games that involve navigation, such as action/adventure games and RPGs. It allows analysts to make sense 
of telemetry data through visualization and comparison between different player types. By interacting 
with our system, analysts are able to visualize player actions by cluster or aggregated over multiple 
clusters. Analysts can also filter the data by specifying time windows. Additionally, our system allows 
analysts to superimpose data categories (which are specific actions taken by the players such as collecting 
items or opening the menu) or filter such data out, which enables them to focus their investigations. 
The result is an intuitive, clean visualization that allow analysts to tell a story based on the data 
and generate new hypotheses to be tested. This paper is organized as follows. First, we discuss related 
research. Second, we explain our interactive visualization system. The last section presents our conclusions 
and future work. 2 PREVIOUS WORK Telemetry provides detailed, quantitative record of thousands of players 
behavioral data. Understanding players behaviors using telemetry is an open problem due to the considerable 
amount of information and data involved (Romero, 2008). To address this problem, several visualization 
and data mining methods can be used. Chittaro et al. (2006) proposed VU-Flow a visualization system 
showing individual or aggregated users paths through lines. Similarly, Coulton et al. (2008) proposed 
a visualization tool to visualize players navigation in Pervasive Location-Based Games, where player 
position is superimposed on a 2D plane with time represented as a 3rd axis. This allows one to understand 
players movement through space. However, it is not scalable. Additionally, Drachen and Canossa (2009) 
proposed the use of heatmaps to represent specific events, such as death and spawn points, in Tomb Raider: 
Underworld. Such variables are aggregated and shown one at a time within a map. This approach was also 
adopted by Romero (2008) and other analysts within the industry. While heatmaps are appropriate to draw 
analysts attention to hot spots within a map, they alone cannot be used to make sense of the context 
behind specific actions or allow exploration of cause and effect. To address these issues, Hoobler et 
al. (2004) developed Lithium a system that enables high-level analysis of competition taking place in 
multi-player games (page, 163). It was developed based on a multiplayer game. Analysts can visualize 
occupancy of the map over time, players orientation, munitions usage, and player classes. Microsoft proposed 
the TRUE system, which supports the triangulation and visualization of telemetry data with other types 
of data (Kim et al., 2008; Romero, 2008). While such triangulation is important for analysts to understand 
the context of action, the visualization system used in TRUE is similar and faces many of the disadvantages 
of heatmaps and simple progression lines discussed above (Romero, 2008). 3 INTERACTIVE VISUALIZATION 
SYSTEM In this section we present the proposed interactive visualization system. This system allows analysts 
to aggregate, filter, visualize, and compare players behavior based on telemetry data. Figure 1 shows 
the basic interface. Analysts can visualize data from all players within different time ranges. They 
can also visualize specific clusters (players with similar play styles), or a single player playthough 
in case of outliers, in a specific time range (top buttons in Figure 1). These clusters are important 
as they provide a level of abstraction over player behavior (typically formed using a clustering algorithm 
(Witten, Frank, &#38; Hall, 2011), and thus provides a scalable solution. Analysts can also specify time 
ranges through the slider (dark gray bar bellow the top buttons in Figure 1). Analysts can pan on that 
time line bar and select a specific map they want to analyze. Player actions are categorized and displayed 
on the left menus (top and bottom). These event categories can be turned on and off. In Figure 1, for 
example, the analyst selected the first hour of gameplay (see top right button). Thus, only the 5 maps 
related to that time range are displayed. Analysts can then evaluate if this information is in tune with 
the designers intentions; e.g., did designers expect players to finish 5 maps in the first hour of gameplay? 
After selecting the map analysts want to work with, they can choose the events they want displayed by 
using the top menu on the left (Figure 1). Event categories are color coded, making it visually easy 
to connect between the event category chosen and its representation in the visualization. More detailed 
information is provided by selecting event categories from the bottom left menu. Figure 1: Interface 
of the proposed visualization system. Analysts have selected the first map from the time line on the 
top. All event categories are selected and visualized. The bottom graph displays Items Collected in the 
first map. Analysts can open new windows with new data (Figure 2); thus they can compare players behaviors 
across different maps. For example, analysts can open different clusters or different maps in new windows. 
In addition, by right clicking on the bottom left menu, analysts can open graphs that present specific 
measures (see new window on the right). Figure 2: Analysts can minimize the bottom part of the interface, 
expanding the map. They can open graphs (or maps) in new windows. 4 VISUALIZING TELEMETRY DATA Video 
games are complex systems that include a large number of actions to be tracked. The system discussed 
above accommodates visualization of several actions at the same time. In this section, due to limitations 
of space, we chose to focus on only 5 event categories; but, the visualization system allows the inclusion 
of other event categories. 4.1 Visualizing time spent in each area Knowing how much time players spent 
playing the game is crucial. In our visualization, we detail how much time players spend in each area 
within a level. We named each room with a different letter. Area A is the starting point. A circle represents 
the total amount of time players spent in one area of the level. The more time players stay in one area, 
the bigger the circle (Figure 3). The size of the circle is calculated by varying the area, not the radius. 
 Figure 3: An example visualization where players spent 11:30 minutes within area A in total. Players 
visited area A 2 times and spent 9:00 minutes and 2:30 minutes in the first and second visits respectively. 
For more precise details about the time players spent in each area, analysts can open up the graph related 
to this event category (Figure 3, bottom). In the graph, each room is represented by a different column. 
The graph shows time spent (Y axis) by location (X axis). Analysts can see how much time players spent 
in a specific room, and how many times they visited a room. Every time players visit a room a new rectangle 
is drawn in the respective column. The gap between the rectangles shows that a new visit occurred. For 
example, in Figure 3, players visited Area E 4 times but spent very little time in the last 3 visits. 
Analysts can mouse over each rectangle to see the exact amount of time spent on average per each visit. 
 4.2 Visualizing interaction with characters Figure 4: Both, time players spent per area and time players 
spent talking to NPCs are visualized. On the bottom, analysts can visualize how many NPCs are within 
each room and how many on average were talked to (blue rectangles). Knowing what players do in each area 
is also important. For example, for an RPG, interacting with non-players characters (NPCs) is important 
because they are a source of information and a key aspect in the narrative. Game designers need to know 
whether players are interacting with NPCs and for how long. Figure 4 shows such relation. The amount 
of time players spent on average talking to NPCs per area is represented by blue circles; again the amount 
of time is represented by the area of the circle. The graph on the bottom (Figure 4) shows the locations 
players visited (X axis) by representations of NPC-player interactions (Y axis). NPCs that players interact 
with are represented by blue rectangles. NPCs that players do not interact with are represented by white 
rectangles. The graph also shows the sequence of areas visited. The player first went from area A to 
B, then C, then B to D, and so on. Thus, analysts can track when players talked with any specific character. 
Gray rectangles represent NPCs that players interacted with in a previous visit to a specific area. The 
size of the rectangle is related to the amount of time players spent talking to an NPC. If analysts mouse 
over a rectangle in the graph, they will see how much time players spent talking to that NPC on average, 
and if that NPC was a key NPC or not. 4.3 Visualizing where maps are activated Figure 5: Analyzing 
when and where players interacted with the map It is important to know where players open the map and 
how much time they spend with the map active. Based on this information designers can hypothesize (and 
then test) if players are getting lost in a specific level or not. The yellow dots on top of the map 
represent locations and relative amount of time players spent checking the map (Figure 5). Based on this 
visualization, analysts can see the most problematic areas in the level. Also, by analyzing the graph 
on the bottom of the screen, analysts can verify when and where players started checking the map and 
for how long. 4.4 Visualizing items collected There are key items in the game that should not be missed 
by players. Figure 6 shows how the system visualizes such data. Each item collected in the game is represented 
by a purple dot on the map. Dots are placed according to the area the items are located in the level. 
Gray dots represent items that were not collected by the player. The graph on the bottom of Figure 6 
works similarly to the graph of Figure 4. Figure 6: Analysis of items collected 4.5 Visualizing players 
paths Figure 7: Analysis of player paths and movement It is important to visualize and understand how 
players navigate through the level. Paths followed by players are represented by green lines on top of 
the map (Figure 7). The more players navigate through an area, the thicker the line representing that 
path will become. The bottom graph shows locations (X axis) and the time spent in each location (Y axis), 
similar to the graph seen in Figure 3. Analysts can see how much time players spent in each area and 
how many times they visited each area. This bottom graph represents players paths in an abstract way. 
Each area is represented by a column. Each visit to an area is represented by a rectangle that varies 
in size based on the amount of time players spent in each visit. Every time a player returns to an area, 
a new rectangle is placed on top of the first one. Finally, arrows connect the rectangles based on the 
sequence of locations the player visited.  5 COMPARING VISUALIZATIONS To exemplify the utility of our 
system, in this section we explain the visualizations generated by 5 different play sessions producing 
3 different clusters where the average times for these clusters were 2:21 (left, n=1), 7:34 (center, 
n=1), and 6:00 (right, n=3) minutes respectively (Figure 8). In this first part of the game, areas C 
and F were locked. There were 11 items to be collected and 17 NPCs in the unlocked areas. Players are 
able to explore the environment, talk to NPCs, open the map, and open the menu/inventory. There was no 
combat. In the first visualization (left), the player navigated fast. He did not collect any item and 
talked to only 2 NPCs. He opened the map every time he entered in a different room until he saw the exit 
in Area G . In the second visualization (center), the player took time exploring the game. He collected 
2 items, visited Area D (missed by the first player), opened the map, and opened the inventory (light 
blue). Finally, in the third visualization (right), players were more interested in talking to NPCs. 
Note that they talked to NPCs in every area they visited. Comparing the first 2 visualizations we notice 
that, as players explore, the visualization becomes busier. The first player left area A as soon as he 
finished the first dialogue. Note that the red circle (total time in the area) and the dark blue circle 
(time spent in dialogues) have almost the same area. In contrast, player 2 spent more time in Area A 
because after finishing the dialogue he opened the inventory and explored the environment collecting 
items. In the third visualization, players also did not leave as soon as the dialogue was over, which 
gave them time to find one item. The data showed here comes from only 5 participants so we cannot draw 
conclusions at this point. However, using visualizations like these, games designers can verify whether 
players are performing as expected and then test and/or improve the game accordingly. For example, if 
players are going from one room to the next too fast, the designer can lock certain areas until specific 
items are collected. If players are taking too long exploring the inventory, designers can investigate 
the user interface of the inventory. That is, based on telemetry data, designers can construct hypotheses, 
test and improve their games. The visualizations presented here show sequences of actions, enabling analysts 
to understand the context in which certain events happened. For example, analysts will be able to verify 
if players got stuck in an area because they missed an NPC and if such event is related to players quitting 
the game. Understanding cause-effect is crucial to improve games.  Figure 8: Comparing actions within 
Dragon Age Origins 6 CONCLUSIONS We have presented an interactive visualization system for visualizing 
players behaviors within RPG and Action/Adventure games where navigation, collection, and talking to 
NPCs are important. Our system has several novel contributions: (a) it allows analysts to interact with 
large data and see temporal progression and cause and effect of player actions, specifically in terms 
of navigation and actions. This is not possible with regular heatmaps or tableau type visualizations. 
(b) It visualizes and enables comparisons of behaviors across different play styles, allowing analysts 
to see how their game fairs to different tastes and styles. (c) We believe that it presents a clean and 
analyst friendly interface to large data, making a daunting task simpler than would have otherwise been 
given the current tools and systems available. This claim needs to be evaluated and tested with designers 
and analysts which is a goal we are currently working towards. Specifically, we are currently collaborating 
with Bioware to evaluate this system with DAO telemetry. Future publications will be concerned with the 
value of the system and its use in a game development pipeline.  ACKNOWLEDGMENT The authors would like 
to extend their sincere thanks to GRAND-NCE for making this work possible. Also, thank you for the reviewers 
for their valuable comments.  REFERENCES Chittaro, L., Ranon, R., &#38; Ieronutti, L. (2006). VU-Flow: 
A Visualization Tool for Analyzing Navigation in Virtual Environments. IEEE Transactions on Visualization 
and Computer Graphics, 12(6), 1475 - 1485. Coulton, P., Bamford, W., Cheverst, Pk., &#38; Rashid, O. 
(2008). 3D Space-Time Visualization of Player Behaviour in Pervasive Location-Based Games. International 
Journal of Computer Games Technology. Drachen, A., &#38; Canossa, A. (2009). Analyzing spatial user behavior 
in computer games using geographic information systems. Proceedings of the 13th International MindTrek 
Conference: Everyday Life in the Ubiquitous Era on -MindTrek 09 (p. 182). Presented at the the 13th International 
MindTrek Conference: Everyday Life in the Ubiquitous Era, Tampere, Finland. Hoobler, N., Humphreys, G., 
&#38; Agrawala, M. (2004). Visualizing competitive behaviors in multi-user virtual environments. IEEE 
Visualization 2004 (pp. 163-170). Presented at the IEEE Visualization 2004, Austin, TX, USA. Hopkins, 
C. (2010, April 28). Second Life Economy At Record High. Read Write Web. Retrieved from http://www.readwrite 
web.com/archives/second_life_econom_at_record_high.php Isbister, K., &#38; Schaffer, N. (2008). Game 
Usability: Advancing the Player Experience. Morgan Kaufmann. Jenkins, H. (2006). Convergence Culture: 
Where Old and New Media Collide (illustrated edition.). NYU Press. Kennerly, D. (2003). Better Game Design 
Through Data Mining. Gamasutra. Retrieved December 14, 2010, from http://www. gamasutra.com/view/feature/2816/better_game_design_throu 
gh_data_.php Kim, J. H., Gunn, D. V., Schuh, E., Phillips, B., Pagulayan, R. J., &#38; Wixon, D. (2008). 
Tracking real-time user experience (TRUE): a comprehensive instrumentation solution for complex systems. 
Proceeding of the twenty-sixth annual CHI conference on Human factors in computing systems - CHI 08 (p. 
443). Presented at the Proceeding of the twenty-sixth annual CHI conference, Florence, Italy. Romero, 
R. (2008). Successful Instrumentation. Presented at the Game Developers Conference. The Entertainment 
Software Association. (2010). The Transformation of the Video Game Industry. Retrieved September 22, 
2010, from http://www.theesa.com/gamesin dailylife/transformation.asp Turkle, S. (2003). Video games 
and computer holding power. The New Media Reader. The MIT Press. Witten, I. H., Frank, E., &#38; Hall, 
M. A. (2011). Data Mining: Practical Machine Learning Tools and Techniques, Third Edition (3rd ed.). 
Morgan Kaufmann. Zoeller, G. (2010). Development Telemetry in Video Games Projects. Presented at the 
Game Developers Conference 2010.  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037696</article_id>
		<sort_key>40</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>8</pages>
		<display_no>3</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>3</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Evaluating gesture-based games with older adults on a large screen display]]></title>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>8</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037696</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037696</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Gesture-based games offer lucrative opportunities to engage users across all segments of the population. However, this requires that associated features go beyond mere expectations to meet the needs and requirements of diverse audience groups. Focusing on designing games for healthy older adults, we present a study exploring the usability and acceptability of a set of three gesture-based games. Designed for a large projection screen display, these games employ vision-based techniques that center on physical embodied interaction using a graphical silhouette. Infrared detection, accompanied by back-projection is used to reduce the effects of occluded body movements. User evaluations with 36 older adults were analyzed using a combination of pre- and post-game questionnaires, direct observations and semi-structured group interviews. The results demonstrate that while all the games were usable, they varied in their physical and social engagement, perceived ease of use and perceived usefulness. In particular, items associated with physical wellbeing were rated highly. During the discussion, we highlight strengths and weaknesses of our findings, including related interaction and application features.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[exergaming]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[gestural interfaces]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[human factors]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[older adults]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[physical exercise]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>H.5.2</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Graphical user interfaces (GUI)</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10003120.10003121.10003124.10010865</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Human-centered computing->Human computer interaction (HCI)->Interaction paradigms->Graphical user interfaces</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809206</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81335496826]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Mark]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Rice]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[mdrice@i2r-a.star.edu.sg]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809207</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487641817]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Marcus]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wan]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[tsmwan@i2r-a.star.edu.sg]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809208</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487644599]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Min-Hui]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Foo]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[mhnfoo@i2r-a.star.edu.sg]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809209</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81452618616]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jamie]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Ng]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[jamie@i2r-a.star.edu.sg]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809210</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487654463]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>5</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Zynie]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Wai]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809211</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487648602]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>6</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Janell]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Kwok]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809212</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487642018]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>7</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Samuel]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Lee]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809213</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487646026]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>8</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Linda]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Teo]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Acsm. 2006. ACSM's guidelines for exercise testing and prescription. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1878842</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1878803</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Alankus, G., Proffitt, R., Kelleher, C., and Engsberg, J. 2010. Stroke therapy through motion-based games: A case study. In <i>Proceedings of the 12th ACM SIGACCESS conference on Computers and Accessibility</i>, 219--226.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Basak C., Boot W. R., Voss M. W., and Kramer A. F. 2008. Can training in a real-time strategy video game attenuate cognitive decline in older adults? <i>J. Psychol Aging 23</i>, 4, 765--777.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Docampo Rama, M. 2001. <i>Technology generations handling complex user interfaces</i>. PhD thesis, Eindhoven University of Technology, Eindhoven, The Netherlands.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Entertainment Software Association. 2008. Sales, demographics and usage data. http://www.theesa.com/facts/pdfs/ESA_EF_2008.pdf]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[European Commission. 2007. &euro;1bn in digital technologies for Europeans to age well. http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/activities/einclusion/policy/ageing/launch/index_en.htm]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Lindeberg, T. 1991. <i>Discrete scale-space theory and the scale-space primal sketch</i>. PhD thesis. Royal Institute of Technology, Sweden.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Macmillian, F., Kirk, A., Peacock, L., Carmichael, A., and Rice, M. 2010. Exer-gaming: Using the Nintendo Wii&#174; as a physical activity tool in adults aged 55 years and above. Poster presentation, <i>3rd International Congress on Physical Activity and Public Health</i>, Toronto.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1358672</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1358628</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Mueller, F., Agamanolis, S., Gibbs, M. R., and Vetere, F. 2008. Remote impact: Shadowboxing over a distance. <i>CHI '08 Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems</i> CHI '08. ACM, New York, 2291--2296.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Nesta. (2009) Preparing for ageing. http://www.nesta.org.uk/library/documents/prepare-for-ageing-v14.pdf]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Owen, A. M., Hampshire, A., Grahn, J. A., Stenton, R., Dajani, S. Burns, A. S., Howard, R. J., and Ballard, C. G 2010. Putting brain training to the test, <i>Nature 465</i>, 7299, 775--778.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Pigford, T., and Williams Andrews, A. 2010. Feasibility and benefit of using the Nintendo Wii Fit for balance rehabilitation in an elderly patient experiencing recurrent falls. <i>Journal of Student Physical Therapy Research 2</i>, 1, 12--20.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Rosenberg, D., Depp, C. A., Vahia, I. V., Reichstadt, J., Palmer, B. W., Kerr, J., Norman, G., Jeste, D. V. and Dilip, V. 2010. Exergames for subsyndromal depression in older adults: A pilot study of a novel intervention. <i>American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry 18</i>, 3, 221--226.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1294221</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1294211</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Shoemaker, G., Tang, A., and Booth, K. S. 2007. Shadow reaching: A new perspective on interaction for large displays. In <i>Proceedings of the 20th Annual ACM Symposium on User interface Software and Technology</i>, 53--56.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Skelton, D. M., and Dinan-Young, S. M. 2008. Ageing and older people. J. P. Buckley, Ed., <i>Exercise physiology in special populations. Advances in Sport and Exercise Science</i>. Elsevier Books, 161--223.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Strauss, A., and Corbin, J. 1998. Basics of qualitative research. Techniques and procedures for developing grounded theory. Sage Publications.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Sugarman, H., Weisel-Eichler, A., Burstin, A., and Brown, R. 2009. Use of the Wii Fit system for the treatment of balance problems in the elderly: A feasibility study. <i>Virtual Rehabilitation International Conference</i>, 111--116.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1592712</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1592700</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Theng, Y. L., Dalan, A. B., Akmal M. L., and Myint, T. Z. 2009. An exploratory study on senior citizens' perceptions of the Nintendo Wii: The case of Singapore. In <i>Proceedings of the 3rd International Convention on Rehabilitation Engineering & Assistive Technology</i>.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Wollersheim, D., Merkes, M., Shields, N., Liamputtong, P., Wallis, L., Reynolds, F., and Koh, L. 2010. Physical and psychosocial effects of Wii video game use among older women. <i>International Journal of Emerging Technologies and Society 8</i>, 2, 85--98.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>20</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Voida, A., and Greenberg, S. 2009. <i>Collocated intergenerational console gaming</i>. Research report 2009-932-11, Department of Computer Science, University of Calgary, Canada.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 (only one person reported using a game console). In most cases they played by themselves, barring three 
exceptions of either playing with friends, children or grandchildren. In terms of physical health, 61.1% 
of participants leisurely walked on a daily basis, with 30.6% jogging, 16.7% cycling and 41.7% doing 
other sport activities (e.g. swimming, golf and dancing) once or more a week. All of the participants 
reported doing some form of regular physical exercise. 5.2 Post-game Score Analysis A repeated measures 
one-way ANOVA was performed to determine if game type had a significant interaction effect on the overall 
mean scores. No significance was found (F(2, 56) = 1.94, p = .16). Additionally, no significant effects 
were found due to age or gender (age: F(2, 56) = 2.05, p = .78; gender: F(2, 56) = .84, p = .43). The 
matrix correlation in Table 3 shows a positive relationship between all constructs across all games, 
with Physical Engagement most correlated to Social Interaction (r = .83, p < .005). Pearson s correlation 
coefficient (two-tailed) was run to determine the significance between the four constructs per game. 
Interestingly, the constructs Physical Engagement and Social Interaction were the only pair that was 
highly significantly correlated across all three games (Virtual Soccer: r = .60, p < .005; Mosquito Invasion: 
r = .87, p < .005; Human Tetris: r = .91, p < .005). Nevertheless, all the constructs were positively 
correlated in all the games, with the exception of Physical Engagement with Perceived Ease of Use in 
Virtual Soccer (r = -.16, p = .35). Constructs PE PEOU SI PU PE 1.00 PEOU .28** 1.00 SI .83** .40** 1.00 
PU .35** .48** .50** 1.00 ** Correlation is significant at .01 level (two-tailed) Table 3: Pearson s 
correlation of constructs across all games. Reviewing the descriptive statistics, a comparison of the 
mean scores per game found Virtual Soccer to be the most physically engaging and socially interactive, 
and Mosquito Invasion the easiest to use and most useful (see Table 4). Mosquito Constructs Human Tetris 
Virtual Soccer Invasion PE 3.97 (.69) 4.46 (.41) 4.26 (.65) PEOU 3.82 (.52) 3.62 (.69) 4.02 (.61) SI 
3.98 (.71) 4.24 (.47) 4.19 (.53) PU 4.23 (.57) 4.07 (.65) 4.42 (.47) Table 4: Mean scores of constructs 
per game. Standard deviations in parentheses. A post-hoc analysis using pairwise comparison of means 
(95% confidence interval) of the constructs for each game was conducted. Participants scored significantly 
higher for both Virtual Soccer (t(35) = 4.51, p < .005) and Mosquito Invasion (t(35) = 2.80, p < .005) 
than Human Tetris in the construct of Physical Engagement. Conversely, no significant differences were 
found in this construct between Virtual Soccer and Mosquito Invasion (t(35) = 2.00, p = .05). No statistical 
significance was also identified in the Perceived Ease of Use of Human Tetris and Mosquito Invasion (t(35) 
= -1.78, p = .08), with the exception of Virtual Soccer, which scored substantially lower than Mosquito 
Invasion (t(35) = -2.96, p < .05). In addition, participants found both Virtual Soccer (t(35) = 2.39, 
p < .05) and Mosquito Invasion (t(35) = 2.71, p < .05) to involve more aspects of social interactivity 
than Human Tetris. Conversely, no significant differences were found in this construct between Virtual 
Soccer and Mosquito Invasion (t(35) = .66, p = .51). Mosquito Invasion was perceived to be the most useful 
game as it was scored significantly higher than both Human Tetris (t(35) = 2.27, p < .05) and Virtual 
Soccer (t(35) = 3.85, p < .005). No significant differences were identified between Human Tetris and 
Virtual Soccer in this construct (t(35) = 1.79, p = .08). In addition, a repeated measures one-way ANOVA 
was conducted to explore the main effects of game type on the scores of the constructs. No significant 
differences were found (Physical Engagement: F(2, 56) = 1.67, p = .20; Perceived Ease of Use: F(2, 56) 
= .81, p = .45; Social Interaction: F(2, 56) = 2.05, p = .15; Perceived Usefulness: F(2, 56) = .83, p 
= .44). A factor analysis was performed using the principal components extraction method with varimax 
rotation. Three factors were extracted based on the mean overall scores across all three games as well 
as for each game. The constructs Physical Engagement and Social Interaction converge to form Factor 1, 
accounting for 32.6% of the total variance, while Factor 2 is related to all attributes listed under 
the construct Perceived Usefulness, accounting for 22.0%. Moreover, all the attributes under the construct 
Perceived Ease of Use are classified under Factor 3, accounting for 12.2% of the total variance. This 
indicates that the participants had perceived a strong inter-relationship between the attributes under 
the constructs of Physical Engagement and Social Interaction -such that the more physically engaging 
they found the game, the more they perceived it to be socially interactive. This is supported by the 
correlation results between the two constructs (see Table 3), found to be of high significance (p < .01). 
 5.3 Pre-interview Questionnaire As can be expected, a comparison of the pre-interview results identified 
varying degrees of variance in the scores. Overall, questions relating to a sense of physical wellbeing: 
being offered different levels of engagement (Q.2), being mentally and physically challenged (Q.8), and 
feeling like I have just exercised (Q.6), scored highest (see Table 5). Rated highly were also wanting 
the game to be useful to my everyday life' (Q.5), wanting the game to reward me (Q.7) and wanting to 
measure my physical performance to prevent injury (Q.1). By contrast, wanting hands free interaction 
(Q.3) and a partner to play along with (Q.4) scored relatively low. Question Mean Std. Deviation Variance 
1 3.69 .88 .79 2 4.03 1.00 .99 3 2.89 1.14 1.30 4 2.92 1.05 1.10 5 3.72 1.16 1.34 6 4.25 .69 .47 
 7 3.69 1.00 1.01 8 4.33 .86 .74  Table 5: Descriptive scores of the pre-interview questionnaire. 
5.3 Video Analysis Reviewing the video data, the main interaction issues are described below. In general, 
the games were very competitive, particularly when paired together. However, it was noticed in Human 
Tetris, even when participants were paired, they accomplished the task individually. With a tendency 
to play for themselves, rather than as part of a team, this may well be a reason why Human Tetris scored 
the lowest amongst the games in the dimension of social interaction. Virtual Soccer: Participants were 
required to exert a range of upper and lower body movements, as they to jump up, tilt, kick, chest and 
head the ball. It was evident that they exerted a lot of coordinated movements, using the full length 
of the screen. Common traits of behavior included bending to scoop the ball from the ground, pushing 
the ball upwards in the air with two hands, or using the sides of the screen as a levy to bounce the 
ball. Given their close proximity, there was a lot of physical touching of the screen to directly engage 
with the ball, whilst we observed that arms extended in front of the body blocked the infrared detection. 
The size of the silhouette could also interfere with the movement of the ball, particularly when it was 
positioned in the corner of the screen. This caused some interaction issues, and more erratic behavior 
by users trying to (at times) frantically move the ball upwards. Anticipating its movement, slower, more 
controlled actions, such as stretching out the arms into a T shape proved an effective gameplay strategy. 
When paired, it was noticed individuals could use this technique to join their silhouettes together, 
acting as a virtual body bridge to bounce the ball (Figure 6). Figure 6: (Top), 3-second video sequence 
of paired interaction; (bottom), coordinated body movements to control the virtual ball. Human Tetris: 
Participants were found to take shortcuts. Rather than make a full body pose, it was common to observe 
them duck or crouch into a ball-like shape to more easily fit within the moving object. While some individuals 
genuinely attempted to make the shape, others avoided taking risks that caused them to lose the game. 
To some degree this was also depended on the complexity of the Tetris shape, as positions that involved 
arching of the back or bending of the arms into two separate positions were particularly difficult to 
accomplish. During the gameplay it was also identified that there was some interference of the head of 
the silhouette hovering over the on-screen start button. This could unintentionally trigger its functionality. 
Similarly some of the cut­out shapes were unproportionate to the size of the body (e.g. too long), indicating 
a need for further refinement in their design. Alternatively, the on-screen arrows used to highlight 
part of the body out of alignment to the moving shape appeared a useful navigational cue for some participants 
(although not in all cases). Mosquito Invasion: Many participants intentionally exerted a lot of physical 
force when swatting the insects. In one case, this heavy impact caused a fly swatter to break, and may 
have caused more damaged to our setup barring the rigidity of the projection screen. Interaction patterns 
varied, but they included multiple tapping and swiping of the screen to eliminate virtual insects, with 
a succession of more rapid actions the nearer the mosquitoes approached the baby. Physical actions included 
a lot of bending and swinging of arms, with some quick reaction times, demonstrating the competitive 
nature of the game. Nevertheless, participants tended to stand in one position, rather than move around 
the display, focusing on a centralized area of the screen. Practical constraints included pressing the 
on/off button on the fly swatter, assuming this was part of the interactive experience. Delaying the 
gameplay, some individuals also tended to tap the swatter over the restart button, rather than intuitively 
hold it in position to activate it. 6 Discussion Overall, the group discussions of the games were positively 
reported as being mentally challenging , exciting , competitive , engaging , and physically beneficial 
. The gestural interfaces were recounted as being easy to understand, while the games themselves were 
described as being intuitive to play. Criticisms were generally low and related to a need for more levels 
(in what was referred to as steps ) to increase the complexity of the gameplay; particularly for the 
Mosquito Invasion and Human Tetris, which some participants thought were too easy. Preferences to the 
games varied, however in general, Virtual Soccer was reported to be good for physical exertion and strategy, 
Human Tetris for hand to eye coordination, while Mosquito Invasion a mixture of these attributes. In 
particular, Mosquito Invasion was favored for combining physical exercise with the very practical objective 
of protecting a vulnerable baby character, as the following comments reiterate: Because you afraid that 
the mosquito will sting the baby, and secondly you want to make sure, you want to kill the mosquitoes 
it makes your mind think very quickly, you have to interact very fast. ...you can see right side of how 
the parents, grandparents concerns of the grandchild, of the baby you see, which is the family value 
. For group versus individual interaction, (given their novelty) there were arguments that the prototype 
games were easier to control when played as a single player. This may also be attributed to a lack of 
time to correctly visualize how to play the games in pairs (despite finding clear examples of participants 
coordinating well together). Alternatively, the competitive nature of the games may have caused some 
negative associations with the questionnaire constructs. In particular, conflicting group involvement 
in Human Tetris constitutes a logical reason why the other games observed significantly higher scores 
in social interaction. Additionally, Mosquito Invasion scored the highest in both ease of use and perceived 
usefulness. Swatting a virtual insect with a physical swatter was observed to be an intuitive action 
that is applicable to everyday life, particularly when compared to the decontextualized task of Human 
Tetris, which inevitably required a higher learning curve. It is also expected that the lower scores 
in the perceived ease of use of Virtual Soccer related to the constraints in controlling the virtual 
ball. However, in this case, the difficulty of the gameplay was thought of as being a positive challenge 
for participants. Physicality of games. Although many of our participants were generally physically active, 
Virtual Soccer was reported as being both strenuous and physically challenging. This corresponds with 
the video analysis, as participants were observed to execute more physical exertion compared to the other 
two games (see Section 5.3). For Virtual Soccer, significantly higher scores were accrued to questions 
related to physical engagement, which interestingly appear highly correlated to social interaction. This 
may be attributed to the perceived increase in their physiological reactions, as users explained heavy 
breathing, with an increase in heart rate during the gameplay (describing how it resembled playing an 
actual football game). Supported by the high scores of question 1 in the pre-interview questionnaire 
(see Table 5) for measuring physical health, such games reconfirm the importance of monitoring exercise 
parameters to determine any difference between perceived and actual heart rate. This brings into question 
the types of built-in feedback required to ensure appropriate levels of safety and motivation -including 
physiological measurements to accurately assess physical vigor. Gesture interaction. Subjectively, some 
participants considered the interaction issues encountered were based on the assumption of not knowing 
the gaming technique, rather than poor usability. Whilst reports of cheating by crouching into a ball-like 
shape rather than stretching into a full body position, related not only to the speed of the moving object, 
but also as previously mentioned, because the application allowed users to make shortcuts. As a result, 
this was reported to defeat the purpose of the game. For the physical embodiment of gestures, like the 
work of Shoemaker et al. [2007], at times we found that users intruded heavily on the other player s 
silhouette, joining arms and hands together to strategically control the directional movement of the 
virtual ball (Figure 6). Dependent on their relative position, the size of the silhouette also changed. 
Those players situated further way from the display, or nearer to the infrared camera, invariably generated 
a larger on-screen presence, dominating more of the screen space. Nevertheless, unlike a solid shadow, 
advantageously the graphical silhouette outline did not impose heavily over the screen background (see 
Figure 1). Noticeable issues were when a user moved away from the sides of the screen, out of the detection 
of the infrared camera. This was evident during Virtual Soccer, where a passive player would back away 
from the display. However, direct visual feedback meant a user could self-correct their position. In 
terms of latency, we found the software responded well in real­time and was robust throughout the user 
evaluations, with a negligible amount of perspective distortion. As previously identified, occluded movements 
hidden by the body could be accommodated by an additional infrared camera. As such, the use of this second 
camera could compensate for the viewpoint limitations of using a single lens. Alternatively, the inference 
of the silhouette to button presses requires better visual feedback, such as the idea of using a motion-based 
charge up until activated metaphor. This is important as many users wrongly perceived an on/off state 
for the on screen button, compared to the actual behavior of waving within its proximity for a set period 
of time. Similarly, the inclusion of a tutorial or demonstration to explain the graphical features and 
gameplay may also be beneficial. However, given our target group, this information is likely to need 
some refinement through further user testing. Input modality. Positively, the hands free interaction 
was considered to draw the user into the screen , complementing the physical exertion in the gameplay 
(described as using all our senses ). Indeed, even those neutral to its effectiveness, recognized the 
physicality created by the games in supporting mental agility. I think it s good from the point that 
it lets your mind and your actions coordinate. That means you have to read what s there and figure it 
[out], so it s a mental connection between physical action and thinking. Comparing the semi-structured 
interviews with the questionnaire data, the hands free interaction was rated lower to other questionnaire 
items. One possibility for this might be the ambiguity of the term hands free , having drawn misunderstanding 
by some participants when completing the post­game questionnaire. By contrast, the immersiveness of the 
display was described as giving a feeling of presence, creating the sense of playing in a football stadium, 
or more generally being part of the animated scene. The tangible aspects of wanting to touch the display 
can be accounted to, not only to the close screen proximity, but the physicality of the games, in what 
was described as getting over excited or lost in the moment . This draws out the idea of employing a 
more tactile, impact-based interface which could accommodate for greater levels of physical exertion 
by using more durable materials, and incorporating stretch sensors, as described by Mueller et al. [2008]. 
Although this increases the risk of sustaining an injury through prolong usage, the gameplay could equally 
be designed for low to moderate forms of exertion. This is an important issue, as the strong impact of 
swatting the virtual mosquitoes (demonstrating the associated affordances of actual insects) caused a 
significant amount of wear and tear to the fly swatters, requiring some maintenance between sessions. 
Design suggestions. In largely female dominated groups it was observed that participants could be quite 
bias towards the perceptions of other older people in their age range. This included reducing the complexity 
of the games by recommending simplified or stationary exercises to accommodate for those in poor health. 
This emphasis on focusing on the safety and mobility limitations of the fragile elderly or disabled was 
somewhat removed to their own interests and personal requirements. Similarly, at times participants became 
more concerned with the commercial costs of purchasing equipment (assuming this was a product ), rather 
than expanding on its design potential. Suggestions by participants to improve the games included a better 
scoring system, such as calculating the number of misses for Mosquito Invasion, incorporating more body 
shapes for Human Tetris, or timing how long the football is kept in the air for Virtual Soccer. Reverting 
back to the work of Voida and Greenberg [2009] in Section 2, individuals also articulated interests for 
intergenerational gameplay within three generations . In particular, young children were thought to warm 
to these styles of games, in helping to build relationships and social bonds between the young and old. 
However, participants were more skeptical of their effectiveness, particularly with adolescents, who 
they thought would get bored by the monotony of the gameplay. For this age group it was argued the games 
needed a more competitive, action-based edge to sustain interest. Likewise, it was felt that the game 
design should build on participants accumulated experience and lifetime of acquired knowledge to accommodate 
for the physical competency of younger players. I know you are physically stronger than me, but I might 
be slightly older, but I know a little bit more from my past experience. You could draw on that element 
that could balance up [the gameplay]. 7 Conclusion Over recent years a significant amount of ageing 
research in game design has centered on evaluating the Nintendo Wii. Focusing on a set of prototypes 
that use a novel form of gesture interaction, we conclude that while they were rated as very usable, 
they are far from complete. Preferences for playing with a partner were mixed, as individuals rated the 
requirements for hands free interaction low in the questionnaire data. This was felt to be noticeably 
different to the feedback received during the group discussions. Unanimous recommendations were made 
to improve the complexity of all games, as individuals highly rated a need for both physical and cognitive 
engagement. Similarly, there appears to be a positive, strong association between physical and social 
interaction, which in this context warrants further understanding. Based on our results, for future work 
there are a number of potential directions to investigate. On the one hand there is the issue of making 
the games more impact-based, whilst providing better sensory feedback and detection of physical movements 
in the gameplay. In particular, we believe the silhouette metaphor warrants a powerful form of personal 
embodiment for this style of interaction. However, beyond technical issues per se, the development of 
such games present a number of user-centered design challenges. For example, to better understand the 
physical requirements of older users, by considering the full range of exercises undertaken. As our participants 
were fairly healthy and techno-savvy there is also the potential to extend the number of older volunteers 
to form a more representative demographic sample. Similarly, there are wider questions in the types of 
rewards and incentives that will motivate different older age groups, including the long-term adherence 
towards a gaming application that ultimately supports better cooperation and social bonding. Acknowledgements 
We would like to thank all the participants for their involvement in this research. We would also like 
to thank the Council for Third Age, WINGS, Fei Yue Community Services, the TSAO Foundation, RSVP and 
the Singapore Action Group of Elders for their organizational support. Finally, we would like to thank 
Yian Ling Cheong for the artwork in this paper. This research was funded by A*STAR SERC Human Factors 
Engineering TSRP Research Grant (No. 092 153 0093). References ACSM. 2006. ACSM's guidelines for exercise 
testing and prescription. Lippincott Williams &#38; Wilkins. ALANKUS, G., PROFFITT, R., KELLEHER, C., 
AND ENGSBERG, J. 2010. Stroke therapy through motion-based games: A case study. In Proceedings of the 
12th ACM SIGACCESS conference on Computers and Accessibility, 219-226. BASAK C., BOOT W. R., VOSS M. 
W., AND KRAMER A. F. 2008. Can training in a real-time strategy video game attenuate cognitive decline 
in older adults? J. Psychol Aging 23, 4, 765-777. DOCAMPO RAMA, M. 2001. Technology generations handling 
complex user interfaces. PhD thesis, Eindhoven University of Technology, Eindhoven, The Netherlands. 
ENTERTAINMENT SOFTWARE ASSOCIATION. 2008. Sales, demographics and usage data. http://www.theesa.com/facts/pdfs/ESA_EF_2008.pdf 
EUROPEAN COMMISSION. 2007. 1bn in digital technologies for Europeans to age well. http://ec.europa.eu/information_society 
/activities/einclusion/policy/ageing/launch/index_en.htm LINDEBERG, T. 1991. Discrete scale-space theory 
and the scale­ space primal sketch. PhD thesis. Royal Institute of Technology, Sweden. MACMILLIAN, F., 
KIRK, A., PEACOCK, L., CARMICHAEL, A., AND RICE, M. 2010. Exer-gaming: Using the Nintendo Wii® as a physical 
activity tool in adults aged 55 years and above. Poster presentation, 3rd International Congress on Physical 
Activity and Public Health, Toronto. MUELLER, F., AGAMANOLIS, S., GIBBS, M. R., AND VETERE, F. 2008. 
Remote impact: Shadowboxing over a distance. CHI '08 Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing 
Systems CHI '08. ACM, New York, 2291-2296. NESTA. (2009) Preparing for ageing. http://www.nesta.org.uk/ 
library/documents/prepare-for-ageing-v14.pdf OWEN, A. M., HAMPSHIRE, A., GRAHN, J. A., STENTON, R., DAJANI, 
S. BURNS, A. S., HOWARD, R. J., AND BALLARD, C. G 2010. Putting brain training to the test, Nature 465, 
7299, 775-778. PIGFORD, T., AND WILLIAMS ANDREWS, A. 2010. Feasibility and benefit of using the Nintendo 
Wii Fit for balance rehabilitation in an elderly patient experiencing recurrent falls. Journal of Student 
Physical Therapy Research 2, 1, 12­ 20. ROSENBERG, D., DEPP, C. A., VAHIA, I. V., REICHSTADT, J., PALMER, 
B. W., KERR, J., NORMAN, G., JESTE, D. V. AND DILIP, V. 2010. Exergames for subsyndromal depression in 
older adults: A pilot study of a novel intervention. American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry 18, 3, 
221-226. SHOEMAKER, G., TANG, A., AND BOOTH, K. S. 2007. Shadow reaching: A new perspective on interaction 
for large displays. In Proceedings of the 20th Annual ACM Symposium on User interface Software and Technology, 
53-56. SKELTON, D. M., AND DINAN-YOUNG, S. M. 2008. Ageing and older people. J. P. Buckley, Ed., Exercise 
physiology in special populations. Advances in Sport and Exercise Science. Elsevier Books, 161-223. STRAUSS, 
A., AND CORBIN, J. 1998. Basics of qualitative research. Techniques and procedures for developing grounded 
theory. Sage Publications. SUGARMAN, H., WEISEL-EICHLER, A., BURSTIN, A., AND BROWN, R. 2009. Use of 
the Wii Fit system for the treatment of balance problems in the elderly: A feasibility study. Virtual 
Rehabilitation International Conference, 111-116. THENG, Y. L., DALAN, A. B., AKMAL M. L., AND MYINT, 
T. Z. 2009. An exploratory study on senior citizens perceptions of the Nintendo Wii: The case of Singapore. 
In Proceedings of the 3rd International Convention on Rehabilitation Engineering &#38; Assistive Technology. 
WOLLERSHEIM, D., MERKES, M., SHIELDS, N., LIAMPUTTONG, P., WALLIS, L., REYNOLDS, F., AND KOH, L. 2010. 
Physical and psychosocial effects of Wii video game use among older women. International Journal of Emerging 
Technologies and Society 8, 2, 85-98. VOIDA, A., AND GREENBERG, S. 2009. Collocated intergenerational 
console gaming. Research report 2009-932­11, Department of Computer Science, University of Calgary, Canada. 
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<article_sponsors>
			<funding_agency>A*STAR SERC Human Factors Engineering TSRP Research</funding_agency>
			<grant_numbers>
				<grant_number>092 153 0093</grant_number>
			</grant_numbers>
		</article_sponsors>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037697</article_id>
		<sort_key>50</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>5</pages>
		<display_no>4</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>4</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[The impact of negative game reviews and user comments on player experience]]></title>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>5</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037697</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037697</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Game reviews and player ratings have an effect on the commercial success of games. They are used extensively by game developers to gauge the success of their titles and by potential buyers to make more informed purchase decisions. However, their potential influence on player experience remains uncertain. We investigated how game reviews and user comments influence players' affective states and experiences during game play. We found that both professional reviews and user comments (especially the negative comments) affected experience measured through game ratings, and that this effect was not mediated by changes in players' moods. Our results are important to the game industry because of the meaningful negative effect that user and critic comments can have on individual player experience and the resulting commercial success of a game.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[biasing effects]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[games]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[negative affect]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[player experience]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[reviews]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.4</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Psychology</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010455.10010459</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Law, social and behavioral sciences->Psychology</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809214</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81477644471]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Ian]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[J.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Livingston]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Saskatchewan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[ian.livingston@usask.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809215</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81392605076]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Lennart]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[E.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Nacke]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Saskatchewan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[lennart.nacke@acm.org]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809216</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100231855]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Regan]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[L.]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Mandryk]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[University of Saskatchewan]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[regan@cs.usask.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Baumeister, R., Bratslavsky, E., Finkenauer, C., and Vohs, K. 2001. Bad is stronger than good. <i>Review of General Psychology 5</i>, 4, 323--370.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Chaiken, S., and Maheswaran, D. 1994. Heuristic processing can bias systematic processing: Effects of source credibility, argument ambiguity, and task importance on attitude judgment. <i>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 66</i>, 3 (mar), 460--473.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Chaiken, S. 2003. Heuristic versus systematic information processing and the use of source versus message cues in persuasion. In <i>Social Psychology: A General Reader</i>. Psychology Press, 461--473.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Fiske, S. 1980. Attention and weight in person perception: The impact of negative and extreme behavior. <i>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 38</i>, 6, 889--906.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Huck, S. W., and Cormier, W. H. 1996. <i>Reading statistics and research</i>. New York: HarperCollins.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ivory, J. D. 2006. Still a man's game: Gender representation in online reviews of video games. <i>Mass Communicationn & Society 9</i>, 1, 103--114.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jenkins, R., Lee, M., Archambault, R., Shane, H., and Greg, S. 2010. The influence of professional critic reviews. EEDAR/SMU behavioral study. Tech. rep., Southern Methodist University, Guildhall. Electronic Entertainment Design and Research, jul.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Lang, P., Sidowski, J., Johnson, J., and Williams, T. 1980. Behavioral treatment and bio-behavioral assessment: Computer applications. In <i>Technology in Mental Health Care Delivery Systems</i>. Ablex Pub. Corp., Norwood, NJ, 119--137.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Larsen, J. M. 2008. Evaluating user experience - how game reviewers do it. In <i>Evaluating User Experiences in Games, Workshop CHI'08</i>.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1920786</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1920778</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Livingston, I. J., Mandryk, R. L., and Stanley, K. G. 2010. Critic-proofing: How using critic reviews and game genres can refine heuristic evaluations. In <i>Proceedings of FuturePlay 2010</i>, ACM, 48--55.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Mandryk, R. L. 2008. Physiological measures for game evaluation. In <i>Game Usability: Advice from the Experts for Advancing the Player Experience</i>. Morgan Kaufmann.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Pennebaker, J. W., Chung, C. K., Ireland, M., Gonzales, A., and Booth, R. J., 2011. LIWC. Retrieved January 2, 2011, from http://www.liwc.net.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Prato, F., and John, O. 1991. Automatic vigilance: The attention-grabbing power of negative social information. <i>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 61</i>, 3, 380--391.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Reinstein, D. A., and Snyder, C. M. 2005. The influence of expert reviews on consumer demand for experience goods: A case study of movie critics. <i>The journal of industrial economics 53</i>, 1, 27--51.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1228994</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1228983</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Sundar, S. S., Knobloch-Westerwick, S., and Hastall, M. R. 2007. News cues: Information scent and cognitive heuristics. <i>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology 58</i>, 3, 366--378.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1520645</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1520340</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Sundar, S. S., Xu, Q., and Oeldorf-Hirsch, A. 2009. Authority vs. peer: how interface cues influence users. In <i>Proceedings of the 27th international conference extended abstracts on Human factors in computing systems</i>, ACM, 4231--4236.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Sundar, S. S. 2007. The MAIN model: A heuristic approach to understanding technology effects on credibility. <i>The John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation Series on Digital Media and Learning</i>, 73--100.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Tversky, A., and Kahneman, D. 1974. Judgment under uncertainty: Heuristics and biases. <i>Science 185</i>, 4754, 1124--1131.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Yi, Y. 1990. Cognitive and affective priming effects of the context for print advertisements. <i>Journal of Advertising 19</i>, 2, 40--48.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1536553</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1536513</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>20</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Zagal, J. P., Ladd, A., and Johnson, T. 2009. Characterizing and understanding game reviews. In <i>Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Foundations of Digital Games</i>, ACM, Orlando, Florida, ACM, 215--222.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 The Impact of Negative Game Reviews and User Comments on Player Experience Ian J. Livingston* Lennart 
E. Nacke Regan L. Mandryk Department of Computer Science Department of Computer Science Department of 
Computer Science University of Saskatchewan University of Saskatchewan University of Saskatchewan Abstract 
Game reviews and player ratings have an effect on the commercial success of games. They are used extensively 
by game developers to gauge the success of their titles and by potential buyers to make more informed 
purchase decisions. However, their potential in.u­ence on player experience remains uncertain. We investigated 
how game reviews and user comments in.uence players affective states and experiences during game play. 
We found that both professional reviews and user comments (especially the negative comments) af­fected 
experience measured through game ratings, and that this ef­fect was not mediated by changes in players 
moods. Our results are important to the game industry because of the meaningful neg­ative effect that 
user and critic comments can have on individual player experience and the resulting commercial success 
of a game. CR Categories: K.8.0 [General]: Games;J.4 [Computer Applica­tions]: Sociology Psychology Keywords: 
biasing effects, games, reviews, player experience, negative affect 1 Introduction In games, experience 
is king. Game reviews can be viewed as ex­pert experience reports giving players an idea of what to expect 
from the game they want to buy [Larsen 2008]. In addition, reviews act as more than just purchase guides, 
they play a role in shaping our understanding of the reviewed games [Zagal et al. 2009] and of ourselves 
as gamers [Ivory 2006]. Game publishers have acknowl­edged the importance of reviews for selling their 
games, and use review aggregation sites to gauge the success of their titles and to determine funding 
for game franchises. For example, the website Metacritic aggregates reviews from both professional game 
critics and game players and is used by players to decide whether or not they will purchase a game. However, 
due to the voice these online review sites provide to game players, the role of professional critics 
has found competition in consumer word-of-mouth and peer com­ments. Thus, it is currently unclear who 
critics or peers has the most persuasive power. Due to the prevalence of game reviews and user comments, 
players form opinions about games before having played them. What re­mains uncertain is how exposure 
to these reviews in.uences player experience, whether the source (e.g., critic or peer) matters, and 
*e-mail: ian.livingston@usask.ca e-mail: lennart.nacke@acm.org e-mail: regan@cs.usask.ca Copyright &#38;#169; 
2011 by the Association for Computing Machinery, Inc. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part 
or all of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not 
made or distributed for commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on 
the first page. Copyrights for components of this work owned by others than ACM must be honored. Abstracting 
with credit is permitted. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to 
lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. Request permissions from Permissions Dept, ACM 
Inc., fax +1 (212) 869-0481 or e-mail permissions@acm.org. Sandbox 2011, Vancouver, British Columbia, 
Canada, August 10, 2011.&#38;#169; 2011 ACM 978-1-4503-0775-8/11/0008 $10.00 whether the player experience 
results from the player s opinion of the game, or is mediated by a change in their mood. The biasing 
of attitudes and opinions is not a new topic in social psychology, economics, or marketing. However, 
biasing caused by textual re­views has received little attention in the .elds of game user research and 
human-computer interaction, especially regarding its effect on player experience. We present a study 
examining the effects of review text on player experience. The review text was manipulated to be either 
positive or negative in tone, either relevant to the subsequent gameplay or not, and derived from either 
an authority (i.e., critic) or peer (i.e., user). Our results show: 1) Players who read the negative 
text rated the game signi.cantly lower than players who read positive text; 2) The text had to relate 
directly to the game to produce biasing effects; 3) The authority of the source (expert or peer) did 
not pro­duce different biasing effects; 4) The effects could not be solely attributed to changes in mood 
as a result of reading the text; and 5) Negative text has a larger biasing effect than positive text. 
Important for our understanding of biasing effects and player expe­rience in general, our results have 
particular relevance to the game industry where it is common practice to release games to critics and 
the media prior to the public release date to get early reviews. 2 Related work Previous work has shown 
that negative stimuli have a signi.cantly greater effect on an individual than positive stimuli. In their 
litera­ture review, Baumeister et al. [2001] concluded that bad is stronger than good in almost every 
area of psychology. For example, it has been shown that negative information is more attention grab­bing 
[Baumeister et al. 2001; Fiske 1980], in.uences impression more, [Fiske 1980], is remembered better [Prato 
and John 1991], and is processed more carefully cognitively than positive informa­tion [Baumeister et 
al. 2001] resulting in a greater biasing effect of negative stimuli. The persuasive biasing power of 
experts and peers has been ex­plored in the domains of movies [Reinstein and Snyder 2005], e-commerce 
[Sundar et al. 2009], advertising [Yi 1990] and news [Sundar et al. 2007]. However, there has only been 
little in­vestigation in the domain of game research. One exception is a recent industrial study investigating 
effects of game ratings on per­ceived game quality and game value [Jenkins et al. 2010]. In this study, 
players were shown a high, low, or no game score and an accompanying comment, such as Game of the year! 
The authors found when players were exposed to a high review score (e.g., 90%) they were more likely 
to rate a game higher than if they were ex­posed to a low review score (e.g., 61%). The authors concluded 
that showing players high game review scores will cause higher player ratings, but attributed their results 
to anchoring [Tversky and Kah­neman 1974]. Anchoring1 is a biasing effect where an individual s ability 
to estimate is biased toward a previously known value. Thus, 1For example, people asked to estimate if 
a price is more or less than 10 dollars are more likely to guess lower values than those who are asked 
if a price is more or less than a 1000 dollars. we cannot know whether the results seen in Jenkins et 
al. [2010] are due only to effects of anchoring, or whether they change the player s perceptions of the 
game. In our experiment, we eliminated all anchoring effects; we did not present review scores, ratings, 
or value to players. Instead players only read an affective text stimu­lus. The use of affective text 
unrelated to a task to bias participants via a change in their mood is known as affective priming [Yi 
1990]. We investigate affective priming through the use of movie reviews. If players reading game reviews 
are invested in evaluating the in­formation in the review, they will expend cognitive effort in the systematic 
processing of that information [Chaiken 2003]. They may also use cues, such as the length of the review 
or the review source, to give weight to the information they have read a me­chanic known as heuristic 
processing [Chaiken 2003; Sundar 2007]. Heuristically-processed cues are based on biases players have; 
for example, that a number of corroborating positive ratings are in­dicative of quality. The latter is 
called the bandwagon heuristic: if others think something is good, then I will think that it is good, 
too [Sundar 2007; Sundar et al. 2007; Sundar et al. 2009]. Another related heuristic cue is the authority 
heuristic: if an expert thinks something is good, I will agree [Sundar et al. 2009]. In the present study, 
we explore the effect of game reviews, user comments, and movie reviews on player experience. 3 Experiment 
Our study asks .ve main research questions: 1. Does the positive or negative tone in review text affect 
player experience? 2. Does the relevance of the review text to the task matter? 3. Does the authority 
(expert or peer) of the authors matter? 4. Can the experience differences be explained by changes in 
mood? 5. How do our results compare to reading no review text?  3.1 Games We used two little-known 
games: Tag: The Power of Paint, a 3D puzzle shooter, and Fancy Pants Adventures (FPA), a 2D platform 
game. The primary factor in choosing games was obscurity the games had to be of professional quality 
but publicly unknown, so that users did not have prior .rst or second hand experience with them. No participant 
expressed prior knowledge of either game when asked after they completed the study. 3.2 Experimental 
Design and Affective Text Stimuli We used a 3 Source (Game Critic, User Comments, Movie Critic) by 2 
Valence (positive, negative) between-subjects design. The sources were either relevant to the task (Game 
Critic and User Com­ments) or not (Movie Critic) and were either authoritative (Game or Movie Critic) 
or peers (User Comments). We also included a control group, who did not read any review text, resulting 
in seven groups. We created the review text by modifying real reviews and user com­ments to ensure that 
the text stimuli were comparable across con­ditions and as authentic as possible. For Movie Critic reviews, 
we modi.ed reviews of obscure .lms to ensure that participants re­sponse to review text was not in.uenced 
by their opinions of the review subject. To create the positive and negative versions, we used affectively-charged 
antonyms. As an example, the statement I love this game in the positive condition would be I hate this 
game in the negative condition. The content and subject matter between conditions was maintained as much 
as possible. For ex­ample, if the positive condition discussed the camera positioning, so did the negative 
condition. Table 1: Valence scores for affective text. Columns show the source and valence condition 
(negative or positive text); rows show the positive and negative LIWC scores for two stimuli. For the 
Game and Movie Critic reviews, we used multiple corrobo­rating reviews to alleviate participant skepticism 
surrounding a sin­gle review. To increase participant buy-in, they were informed that the text had been 
taken from a professional review website. In all cases, the review text was about 1000 words. To ensure 
that the af­fective tone (positive or negative) of our text was comparable across conditions, we used 
the Linguistic Inquiry Word Count (LIWC) text analysis tool [Pennebaker et al. 2011] to measure the valence 
of re­view text for each game (see Table 1). 3.3 Participants and Procedure Seventy participants (29 
female), aged 18 36 (M=24) years began by completing a demographic survey, and then were randomly as­signed 
to a group, balancing for sex. Players then completed the experiment using a custom system to deploy 
the games and gather the survey responses. Players .rst provided their pre-text baseline valence rating 
using the self-assessment manikin (SAM) [Lang et al. 1980], a pictorial 9-point scale commonly used to 
self-report valence. Players then read the text corresponding to their test group (or read nothing in 
the control group). They were required to answer questions related to the text to ensure they systematically 
processed the information, and did not rely solely on heuristic cues [Chaiken 2003]. Players then provided 
their valence rating again, played the game for 15 minutes, and provided a .nal valence rating. Half 
of the partici­pants played Tag .rst, the other half played FPA .rst. To evaluate their experience, players 
wrote a short game review and provided a game rating on a 100-point scale. This procedure was repeated 
for the second game. Before providing their ratings, players were never shown numerical scores to ensure 
that there were no anchoring ef­fects [Tversky and Kahneman 1974] (when exposure to a numeri­cal rating 
would in.uence a player s own numerical rating) as seen in [Jenkins et al. 2010]. To help players choose 
scores, and to aim for consistency across players in their interpretation of the ratings scale, a score 
guideline was provided (0 19: I hated it; 20 49: I didn t like this; 50 74: It was ok, but I m rather 
indifferent; 75 89: It was good, but room for improvement; 90 100: I loved it). 3.4 Data Analyses and 
Dependent Measures Our dependent measures are user ratings on a scale of 1 100 and user valence ratings 
from the SAM. These do not meet the assump­tions of normality and equal variance measured using the Shapiro-Wilk 
test for normality. As such, we used the Mann-Whitney Test for all between-groups tests, and the Wilcoxon 
Signed Ranks Test for within-player comparisons [Huck and Cormier 1996]. Only data from the .rst game 
played are presented, because initial analysis showed that players consistently discovered the experimental 
ma­nipulation after playing the .rst game and answering the surveys, biasing the data from the second 
game. Consistent with previous work [Chaiken 2003; Jenkins et al. 2010; Chaiken and Maheswaran 1994], 
we discarded the data from the biased game trial.  4 Results Does the valence of text affect the experience? 
Players who read positive text rated the game signi.cantly higher than players who read negative text 
(Z =3.6,p .000,M+ = 72.9,SE+ =2.6) (M- = 51.3,SE- =4.4). Figure 1: Means (±SE) for user game rating 
scores by source of affective text and valence of affective text. Does the relevance of the affective 
text to the task matter? Tests for each text source (game critic, user comments, and movie critic) showed 
that reading positive text resulted in higher ratings than reading negative text for the players reading 
game critic reviews (Z =2.8,p = .004) and user comments (Z =2.5,p = .011) for the game that they subsequently 
played, but not for players reading movie critic reviews (Z =1.0,p = .315). See Figure 1. Does the authority 
(expert or peer) of the source matter? The expe­rience ratings for players reading negative game critic 
(expert) and user (peer) text were not signi.cantly different (Z = -1.5,p = .127). Neither were ratings 
for players reading positive game critic and user text (Z = -1.7,p = .081). See Figure 1. Figure 2: 
Means (±SE) of valence ratings (9-point scale, higher is more pleasant) for pre-text, post-text, and 
post-game by source and valence (+, -) of affective text. Can the valence results be explained by a change 
in mood as a re­sult of reading positive or negative text? We were interested in de­termining whether 
reading the affective text had a direct impact on player experience, or whether it caused a change in 
players overall affective state (mood), which then had an impact on player expe­rience. We had asked 
participants to rate their mood both prior to and directly after reading the affective review text. We 
compared these two ratings for each of the six groups (3 Source × 2 Valence) and found that none of the 
differences were signi.cant except for those who read positive movie text (Z =2.1,p = .034). As Figure 
2 shows, reading the positive movie review text improved players self-rated valence. All other differences 
failed to reach signi.cance (pgame- = .666,puser- = .103,pmovie- = .336,pgame+ = .085,p= .230). user+ 
How do our results compare to reading no review text? We included a control group that read no review 
text before playing the game to see whether the positive reviews were improving play experience or the 
negative reviews were worsening play experience. Players reading negative affective text rated the game 
lower than players reading no text at all (Z =3.0,p = .002), but players reading positive affective text 
rated the game no differently than players reading no text at all (Z =1.2,p = .259). See Figure 1. 5 
Discussion There are several results to take away from this study: 1. Reading negative review text negatively 
in.uences player ex­perience. 2. To affect player experience, the text must relate to the game (e.g., 
a review of the game played). 3. The authority of the source does not matter; the peer and ex­pert sources 
did not differ signi.cantly in their in.uence on experience. 4. There was no signi.cant difference in 
mood for players before and after reading game reviews and user comments. 5. The positive review text 
provides no positive bene.t over no review text at all.  We next discuss the meaning of our .ndings 
and how they com­pare to prior work, their industrial relevance, and future research directions. 5.1 
Valence Effects and Review Source In our experiment we showed that the valence of review text signi.­cantly 
affected player experience. We further show that the negative text had a greater effect on player experience, 
and that the authority of the related review source (critic versus peer) does not matter. In­terestingly, 
our results suggest that the observed effect on player ex­perience was not primarily mediated by changes 
in player valence. If this were the case, reading the affective text would produce a change in mood, 
which would then produce a resulting change in player experience. Our results show that although the 
differences in player ratings were signi.cant between the groups who read pos­itive or negative reviews, 
the reviews did not produce a consistent and corresponding affective state change. It could be that the 
SAM ratings data was too noisy to .nd signi.cant differences, but Figure 2 shows no consistent pattern, 
thus we are quite con.dent that the ratings differences cannot be attributed to changes in overall mood. 
Our .ndings also suggest a primary contributing factor is relevance of the text to the game being played. 
The game reviews and user comments about the game produced a consistent and signi.cant dif­ference in 
player game ratings, while the movie reviews did not. 5.2 Explanations of the Observed Effects We believe 
that systematic processing of the review text in.uenced players opinions of and experience with the game; 
however, pre­vious literature has suggested that changes in experience could be explained by heuristic 
cues, anchoring, or affective priming. We address each of these in turn. The bandwagon heuristic suggests 
that if others think that some­thing is good, then I will agree, while the authority heuristic sug­gests 
that if an expert thinks something is good, then I will agree. Previous literature on the effects of 
experts and peers [Sundar 2007; Sundar et al. 2009] has shown the authority heuristic can be super­seded 
by a bandwagon heuristic. Our results showed no differences in player experience after reading expert 
reviews or user comments. It is possible that systematic processing of the negative review text caused 
the prioritization and interpretations of negative content to overshadow any authority or bandwagon heuristic 
effects. In addi­tion, we did not observe a difference between the control condition and any of the positive 
conditions, suggesting that when informa­tion is systematically processed, heuristic cues are less effective. 
Affective priming uses a stimulus, unrelated to the task or object to be viewed, to change a participant 
s affective state or mood [Yi 1990]. In our movie review condition, we did see a positive impact of a 
positive review on players moods, but not a negative impact of a negative review. However, there was 
no effect on player ex­perience, thus our results cannot be explained by affective priming. Because the 
review text had to be related to the game to show ef­fects, we can assume that task-relevance has a much 
stronger effect on player experience than affective priming. Anchoring is a biasing effect where an individual 
s ability to esti­mate is biased toward a previously-known value. In previous work, players exposed to 
a negative rating of a game rated that game lower themselves [Jenkins et al. 2010]. This is clearly an 
effect of anchor­ing, so the previous work does not show that player experience was actually affected. 
In our study, we did not present the players with any numerical ratings, so the content and tone of the 
review text was causing the difference in player experience. Thus, our results cannot be attributed to 
anchoring. We conclude it is cognitive processing and interpretation of nega­tive text that has the greatest 
effect on player experience, not an­choring, affective priming, or heuristic cues. However, additional 
work examining the methods and effects of information processing, is required to con.rm this. 5.3 Effects 
on Player Experience Although we observed changes in game ratings as a result of read­ing affective reviews, 
the question remains whether the ratings dif­ferences were a result of a change in actual player experience 
or a re.ection of the player s cognitive rationalization of their experi­ence with the review text. In 
the former situation, a player who read a negative game review would actually not enjoy the experience 
as much as a player who read a positive review. In the latter, both players would have a similar experience; 
however, the one who read a negative review would interpret their experience as having been more negative. 
To consider this, we can look at how players moods changed over the course of gameplay. A signi.cant 
correlation between review score and post-play SAM ratings (Spearman s . = .442, p .000) show that the 
player s self-rated affective state and their rating of the game correspond. So although reading the 
review text failed to produce an observable change in players affective state, play­ing the game after 
reading the review text did. The more positive that participants were feeling after playing, the higher 
they rated the game. This result leads us to think that actual experience was changed, but to better 
explore this question we must measure player experience during play. We plan to investigate this issue 
by mea­suring player experience at the physiological level [Mandryk 2008], which would tell us if the 
biasing effects from affective reviews are mirrored physiologically during play or if the mind tells 
a different story than the body. 5.4 Practical and Industrial Considerations Compared to no affective 
text, negative reviews and user comments had a detrimental effect on player experience, whereas positive 
re­views produced little to no relative improvement. These results have practical signi.cance for game 
designers, online community managers, and marketers. Unlike other products, games provide entertainment 
experiences that not only require an investment of money but also of personal leisure time, which makes 
an informed purchase decision impor­tant for players. Game reviews facilitate this decision by providing 
player experience reports, giving players an idea of what to expect from the game they want to buy. It 
is standard practice for devel­opers and publishers to show a game to media outlets prior to its release. 
If the game is well received, it can generate hype, which can translate into sales. Our results suggest 
that reading a positive review does not provide bene.t in terms of player experience over reading no 
review, but that a negative review can signi.cantly harm player experience, which would likely generate 
a negative hype ef­fect. Therefore, negative reviews should be avoided, for example through a critic-proo.ng 
approach to playability testing [Livingston et al. 2010]. In an online community this negative effect 
can snowball as play­ers who are in.uenced by critic reviews may in turn post negative comments online, 
in.uencing an even larger player population. As this cycle continues with new players reading and being 
in.uenced by the negative press, the bottom line of a game in terms of sales and future sequels could 
be negatively affected. 5.5 Limitations of the Study We took care in our study design to eliminate in.uencing 
effects (e.g., anchoring), to remove any confounds from the stimuli (e.g., content, length, number of 
authors), and to test all conditions that would explain the nature of the effects (e.g., relevant text, 
authority or peer). Still, there are a few limitations in our work. The SAM results for the control condition 
show that players who read no text were happier than players in any of the other conditions. Read­ing 
and summarizing the text was not as fun as getting straight to the game, which is not surprising, but 
requires that we take care when interpreting differences between the control condition and other forms 
of play. In addition, our play sessions were conducted immediately following the reading of reviews and 
for a single, short duration. More work needs to investigate whether the effects hold for longer or repeated 
play sessions, for play sessions that occur long after reading the reviews, and for games a player is 
anticipat­ing or is previously familiar with.  6 Conclusion Game reviews and player ratings have an 
effect on the commercial success of games, but it has not been clear how game reviews af­fect player 
experience. We investigated how positive and negative text in.uences players affective states and their 
play experiences. Our results show: 1) Players who read the negative text rated the game signi.cantly 
lower than players who read positive text; 2) The text must be relevant and related to the game to produce 
signif­icant player experience effects; 3) The authority of the text (expert or peer) did not in.uence 
the biasing effect; 4) The effects could not be explained by changes in mood as a result of reading affec­tive 
text; and 5) Negative affective text has a larger biasing effect than positive affective text, likely 
due to the more careful process­ing of the negative information. Important for our understanding and 
analysis of player experience, our results have particular rele­vance to the game industry where it is 
common practice to release games to critics and the media prior to the public release date.  Acknowledgements 
This research was funded by NSERC and the GRAND NCE. Thanks to David McDine for literature suggestions 
and our past reviewers who provided helpful comments on previous versions of this document. We are also 
grateful to all participants for taking part in this study. References BAUMEISTER, R., BRATSLAVSKY, 
E., FINKENAUER, C., AND VOHS, K. 2001. Bad is stronger than good. Review of General Psychology 5, 4, 
323 370. CHAIKEN, S., AND MAHESWARAN, D. 1994. Heuristic process­ing can bias systematic processing: 
Effects of source credibility, argument ambiguity, and task importance on attitude judgment. Journal 
of Personality and Social Psychology 66, 3 (mar), 460 473. CHAIKEN, S. 2003. Heuristic versus systematic 
information pro­cessing and the use of source versus message cues in persuasion. In Social Psychology:A 
General Reader. Psychology Press, 461 473. FISKE, S. 1980. Attention and weight in person perception: 
The impact of negative and extreme behavior. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology 38, 6, 889 
906. HUCK, S. W., AND CORMIER, W. H. 1996. Reading statistics and research. New York: HarperCollins. 
IVORY, J. D. 2006. Still a man s game: Gender representation in online reviews of video games. Mass Communicationn 
&#38; Society 9, 1, 103 114. JENKINS, R., LEE, M., ARCHAMBAULT, R., SHANE, H., AND GREG, S. 2010. The 
in.uence of professional critic reviews. EEDAR/SMU behavioral study. Tech. rep., Southern Methodist University, 
Guildhall. Electronic Entertainment Design and Re­search, jul. LANG, P., SIDOWSKI, J., JOHNSON, J., AND 
WILLIAMS, T. 1980. Behavioral treatment and bio-behavioral assessment: Computer applications. In Technology 
in Mental Health Care Delivery Systems. Ablex Pub. Corp., Norwood, NJ, 119 137. LARSEN, J. M. 2008. Evaluating 
user experience -how game re­viewers do it. In Evaluating User Experiences in Games, Work­shop CHI 08. 
LIVINGSTON, I. J., MANDRYK, R. L., AND STANLEY, K. G. 2010. Critic-proo.ng: How using critic reviews 
and game genres can re.ne heuristic evaluations. In Proceedings of FuturePlay 2010, ACM, 48 55. MANDRYK, 
R. L. 2008. Physiological measures for game evalua­tion. In Game Usability: Advice from the Experts for 
Advancing the Player Experience. Morgan Kaufmann. PENNEBAKER, J. W., CHUNG, C. K., IRELAND, M., GONZALES, 
A., AND BOOTH, R. J., 2011. LIWC. Retrieved January 2, 2011, from http://www.liwc.net. PRATO, F., AND 
JOHN, O. 1991. Automatic vigilance: The attention-grabbing power of negative social information. Journal 
of Personality and Social Psychology 61, 3, 380 391. REINSTEIN, D. A., AND SNYDER, C. M. 2005. The in.uence 
of expert reviews on consumer demand for experience goods: A case study of movie critics. The journal 
of industrial economics 53, 1, 27 51. SUNDAR, S. S., KNOBLOCH-WESTERWICK, S., AND HASTALL, M. R. 2007. 
News cues: Information scent and cognitive heuris­tics. Journal of the American Society for Information 
Science and Technology 58, 3, 366 378. SUNDAR, S. S., XU, Q., AND OELDORF-HIRSCH, A. 2009. Au­thority 
vs. peer: how interface cues in.uence users. In Proceed­ings of the 27th international conference extended 
abstracts on Human factors in computing systems, ACM, 4231 4236. SUNDAR, S. S. 2007. The MAIN model: 
A heuristic approach to understanding technology effects on credibility. The John D. and Catherine T. 
MacArthur Foundation Series on Digital Media and Learning, 73 100. TVERSKY, A., AND KAHNEMAN, D. 1974. 
Judgment under un­certainty: Heuristics and biases. Science 185, 4754, 1124 1131. YI, Y. 1990. Cognitive 
and affective priming effects of the context for print advertisements. Journal of Advertising 19, 2, 
40 48. ZAGAL, J. P., LADD, A., AND JOHNSON, T. 2009. Characterizing and understanding game reviews. In 
Proceedings of the 4th In­ternational Conference on Foundations of Digital Games, ACM, Orlando, Florida, 
ACM, 215 222.  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	</section>
	<section>
		<section_id>2037698</section_id>
		<sort_key>60</sort_key>
		<section_seq_no>2</section_seq_no>
		<section_type>SESSION</section_type>
		<section_title><![CDATA[Players and game worlds]]></section_title>
		<section_page_from>2</section_page_from>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037699</article_id>
		<sort_key>70</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>5</pages>
		<display_no>5</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>1</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[All in a day's work]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[a study of World of Warcraft NPCs comparing gender to professions]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>6</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037699</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037699</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Extending Corneliussen's [2008] study of the gender disparity of <i>World of Warcraft</i> Non-Player Characters (NPCs), this paper examines the relationship between sex and profession of NPCs in in the same game. Because NPCs are understudied to date, we attempt to show where and how normative frameworks are, even if unintended, working very much to marginalize women. Our primary focus is to determine if stereotypical associations between types of jobs and the bodies that are depicted performing these jobs are being reinforced.</p> <p>Our findings show that while there are male and female NPCs for all professions, they are not equally represented. There is no statistically significant pattern linking gender and profession, however, males still make up approximately two thirds of the NPCs associated with a 'job' within this particular gameworld. There seems to be subtle hierarchies at work within the distribution of professions within <i>World of Warcraft</i>. For example, ideas of gender in the field of medicine have been transposed into the gameworld through the use of some male first aid NPCs having the title 'Doctor', and yet the title given to a female trainer of the same profession is 'Nurse'. Ultimately, we argue that there are other forces, influences and processes to consider when examining a sociotechnical system like <i>World of Warcraft</i>, including player preferences and conditioning, the fantasy lore upon which the game draws (as well as produces) and the general presentation of gender roles in the larger sociotechnical context.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[MMOGs]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[MMORPGs]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[World of Warcraft]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[game design]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[gender]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[massively multiplayer online role-playing games]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[non-player characters]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[player experience]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[sex]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.4</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Sociology</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010455.10010461</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Law, social and behavioral sciences->Sociology</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809217</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487651000]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Kelly]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Bergstrom]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[York University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[kelly_bergstrom@edu.yorku.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809218</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81350581705]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Victoria]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[McArthur]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[York University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[vickymc@yorku.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809219</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81435596928]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jennifer]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Jenson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[York University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[jjenson@edu.yorku.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809220</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487653438]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Tamara]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Peyton]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[York University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[tpeyton@yorku.ca]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Chen, M. 2009. Communication, coordination, and camaraderie in world of warcraft. <i>Games & Culture 4</i>, 47--73.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Chodorow, N. 1994. <i>Femininities, Masculinities, Sexualities: Freud and Beyond</i>. University Press of Kentucky, Lexington, KY.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Corneliussen, H. G. 2008. World of warcraft as a playground for feminism. In <i>Digital Culture, Play, and Identity: A World of Warcraft Reader</i>, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, H. G. Corneliussen and J. W. Rettberg, Eds., 63--86.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1124834</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1124772</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ducheneaut, N., Yee, N., Nickell, E., and Moore, R. J. 2006. "alone together?": exploring the social dynamics of massively multiplayer online games. In <i>Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on Human Factors in computing systems</i>, ACM, ACM, 407--416.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Higgin, T. 2009. Blackless fantasy: The disappearance of race in massively multiplayer online role-playing games. <i>Games and Culture 4</i>, 1, 3--26.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jenkins, H., and Cassell, J. 2008. From quake girls to desperate housewives: A decade of gender and computer games. In <i>Beyond Barbie and Mortal Kombat: New perspectives on gender and gaming</i>, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, Y. Kafai, C. Heeter, J. Denner, and J. Sun, Eds., 5--20.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1713251</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1713245</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jenson, J., and de Castell, S. 2010. Gender, simulation, and gaming: Research review and redirections. <i>Simulation & Gaming 4</i>, Feb, 51--71.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Johnson, D. G. 2010. Sorting out the question of feminist technology. In <i>Feminist Technology</i>, University of Illinois Press, Chicago, IL, L. L. Layne, S. L. Vostral, and K. Boyer, Eds., 36--54.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Klastrup, L. 2009. The worldness of <i>EverQuest</i>: Exploring a 21st century fiction. <i>Game Studies 9</i>, 1, Accessed March 1, 2011 at http://gamestudies.org/0901/articles/klastrup.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Krzywinska, T. 2008. World creation and lore: <i>World of Warcraft</i> as rich text. In <i>Digital Culture, Play, and Identity: A World of Warcraft Reader</i>, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, H. G. Corneliussen and J. W. Rettberg, Eds., 123--142.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Langer, J. 2008. The familiar and the foreign: Playing (post)colonialism in <i>World of Warcraft</i>. In <i>Digital Culture, Play, and Identity: A World of Warcraft Reader</i>, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, H. G. Corneliussen and J. W. Rettberg, Eds., 87--108.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[McArthur, V., Teather, R. J., and Stuerzlinger, W. 2010. Comparing 3d content creation interfaces in two virtual worlds: World of warcraft and second life. <i>Journal of Virtual Worlds and Gaming 2</i>, 3, 239--258.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1837166</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1837164</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Miller, J. L., and Crowcroft, J. 2009. Avatar movement in world of warcraft battlegrounds. In <i>Proceedings of the 8th Annual Workshop on Network and Systems Support for Games (NetGames '09)</i>, IEEE Press, DiGRA.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Pace, T., Houssian, A., and McArthur, V. 2009. Are socially exclusive values embedded in the avatar creation interfaces of mmorpgs? <i>Journal of Information, Communication and Ethics in Society 7</i>, 2/3, 192--210.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Rubenstein, A. 2007. Idealizing fantasy bodies. Accessed January 16, 2011 at http://www.theirisnetwork.org/archives/12.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Tronstad, R. 2008. Character identification in world of warcraft. the relationship between capacity and appearance. In <i>Digital Culture, Play, and Identity: A World of Warcraft Reader</i>, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, H. G. Corneliussen and J. W. Rettberg, Eds., 249--264.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Walkerdine, V. 2007. <i>Children, Gender, video games: Towards a relational approach to multimedia</i>. Palgrave Macmillan, Basingstroke, UK.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Williams, D., Ducheneaut, N., Xiong, L., Zhang, Y., Yee, N., and Nickell, E. 2006. From tree house to barracks: The social life of guilds in world of warcraft. <i>Games and Culture 1</i>, 4, 338--361.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Williams, D., Consalvo, M., Caplan, S., and Yee, N. 2009. Looking for gender: Gender roles and behaviors among online gamers. <i>Journal of Communication 59</i>, 2009, 700--725.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>20</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Winn, J., and Heeter, C. 2009. Gaming, gender, and time: Who makes time to play? <i>Sex Roles 61</i>, 1--13.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>21</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Woodcock, B. n. d. An analysis of mmog subscription growth. mmogchart.com v23.0. Accessed January 15, 2011 at: http://users.telenet.be/mmodata/Charts/Subs-1.png.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>22</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Woodfield, R. 2008. <i>What women want from work: gender and occupational choice in the 21st century</i>. Palgrave, New York, NY.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>23</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[WoWWiki. 2011. Dwarf. Accessed January 10, 2011 at: http://www.wowwiki.com/Dwarf#Female_dwarves.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>24</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[WoWWiki. 2011. Night elf. Accessed January 10, 2011 at: http://www.wowwiki.com/Night_elves.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 All in a Day s Work: A study of World of Warcraft NPCs Comparing Gender to Professions Kelly Bergstrom* 
Victoria McArthur York University York University Abstract Extending Corneliussen s [2008] study of 
the gender disparity of World of Warcraft Non-Player Characters (NPCs), this paper exam­ines the relationship 
between sex and profession of NPCs in in the same game. Because NPCs are understudied to date, we attempt 
to show where and how normative frameworks are, even if unin­tended, working very much to marginalize 
women. Our primary focus is to determine if stereotypical associations between types of jobs and the 
bodies that are depicted performing these jobs are be­ing reinforced. Our .ndings show that while there 
are male and female NPCs for all professions, they are not equally represented. There is no statis­tically 
signi.cant pattern linking gender and profession, however, males still make up approximately two thirds 
of the NPCs associ­ated with a job within this particular gameworld. There seems to be subtle hierarchies 
at work within the distribution of professions within World of Warcraft. For example, ideas of gender 
in the .eld of medicine have been transposed into the gameworld through the use of some male .rst aid 
NPCs having the title Doctor , and yet the title given to a female trainer of the same profession is 
Nurse . Ultimately, we argue that there are other forces, in.uences and pro­cesses to consider when examining 
a sociotechnical system like World of Warcraft, including player preferences and conditioning, the fantasy 
lore upon which the game draws (as well as produces) and the general presentation of gender roles in 
the larger sociotech­nical context. CR Categories: K.8 [Computing Milieux]: Personal computing Games; 
J.4 [Computer Applications]: Social and behavioral sciences Sociology; Keywords: Game Design, Player 
Experience, World of War­craft, Non-Player Characters, Massively Multiplayer Online Role-Playing Games, 
MMORPGs, MMOGs, Gender, Sex Blizzard Entertainment s World of Warcraft (WoW) is currently the most popular 
game of the Massively Multiplayer Online Role-Playing Game (MMORPG) genre, with more than 12 million 
ac­tive players [Woodcock n. d.]. Because of its overwhelming pop­ ularity, WoW has been the focus of 
a growing body of academic work [Ducheneaut et al. 2006; Miller and Crowcroft 2009]. Re­searchers have 
used WoW to explore a variety of topics including design choices [McArthur et al. 2010; Pace et al. 2009]; 
social play con.gurations [Chen 2009; Williams et al. 2006]; and issues of *kelly bergstrom@edu.yorku.ca 
vickymc@yorku.ca jjenson@edu.yorku.ca §tpeyton@yorku.ca Copyright &#38;#169; 2011 by the Association 
for Computing Machinery, Inc. Permission to make digital or hard copies of part or all of this work for 
personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided that copies are not made or distributed for 
commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and the full citation on the first page. Copyrights 
for components of this work owned by others than ACM must be honored. Abstracting with credit is permitted. 
To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific 
permission and/or a fee. Request permissions from Permissions Dept, ACM Inc., fax +1 (212) 869-0481 or 
e-mail permissions@acm.org. Sandbox 2011, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada, August 10, 2011.&#38;#169; 
2011 ACM 978-1-4503-0775-8/11/0008 $10.00 Jennifer Jenson Tamara Peyton§ York University York University 
race, gender, and economics [Higgin 2009; Tronstad 2008]. In this paper, we work to uncover the imposition 
of frameworks like the sex of NPCs and their profession in the game on players, situating Blizzard s 
design choices within a larger discussion of gendered deptictions of work and labour within WoW. 0.1 
Motivation Our work is an extension of Corneliussen s World of Warcraft as a playground for feminism 
[2008], which looked at the distribu­ tion of male and female NPCs in the starting zones of WoW. We interrogate 
the approach of her study and show the ways in which an understanding of WoW as a sociotechnical system 
both extends her reading and analysis, and arrives at a very different conclusion. In her chapter, Corneliussen 
traces how gender is constructed, and in turn embodied, in WoW. The crux of her argument is that while 
we can look for parity 1 between male and female NPCs visible within the gameworld, the construction 
of WoW s male-female du­alism is clearly wasting the fantasy world s potential for playing with alternative 
gender labels [2008, p. 81]. One of Corneliussen s .ndings is that there are not equal numbers of male 
and female NPCs present within WoW, and indeed, our study shows a similar distribution of NPCs by sex. 
However, we recognize that merely adding more female NPCs to the game will not solve the problems identi.ed 
by Corneliussen. Just because there might be equal numbers of NPCs in game does not mean that they are 
equitably represented. This paper seeks to address the question: how are males and females represented 
by profes­sion, and what might that mean for better understanding the kind of hard wired gender-encoding 
at play in WoW? Our primary focus is to determine if gender is being used to re­inforce stereotypical 
associations between types of jobs and the bodies that are depicted performing those jobs (c.f. Wood.eld 
[2008]). Interrogating and expanding Corneliussen s study, which highlighted the unequal sex ratio of 
NPCs in WoW, we wish to move beyond a simple counting exercise to determine what NPCs can be observed 
doing. Quite simply, we are interested in whether or not patterns of male jobs and female jobs can be 
observed within Azeroth, and argue that the gameworld is not a neutral back­drop or map upon which players 
move about. Decisions about de­sign and construction resonate through the game and shape the ways in 
which interactions, ideas, and identities are formed. Design choices for the gendering of player characters 
and NPCs in WoW are not simply informed by fantasy lore and technical imple­mentation. Visual cues for 
avatar choices and overall content and visual design will always re.ect the larger sociocultural context 
of gamers [Rubenstein 2007], though possibly drawing more heavily on the subset of those who play the 
alpha and beta pre-release ver­sions and who provide their feedback. Claiming that Blizzard is solely 
responsible for the design choices ignores the history and context of both WoW s gameworld and the larger 
canon of fantasy lore (often associated with Tolkien). By putting all the blame on 1Corneliussen s use 
of parity references the recent French Parit´e move­ment seeking equal representation of men and women 
in elected political positions [pg. 63]. to Blizzard, it also avoids discussions of the way that WoW 
is part of a larger sociocultural context, and this context works to shape the expectations and preferences 
voiced by MMORPG players. 0.2 World of Warcraft professions In addition to combat, exploration and (collaborative 
or solo) play, WoW allows for players to choose from a variety of professions. The professions are divided 
between gathering and crafting: the gathering professions involve the acquisition of raw materials and 
crafting professions take these materials and turn them into other items (armor, weapons, potions, etc). 
In addition to being able to choose two professions, players are able to train in four secondary skills 
(cooking, .rst aid, .shing, and archeology2). While not ex­plicitly required for gameplay, professions 
and secondary skills add an extra augmentation to one s play, by providing enhancement, ar­mor, weapons, 
or materials that players can sell for a pro.t to NPCs or other players. Corneliussen touches on professions 
in her chapter. As part of her larger discussion of activities with feminine associations , she brie.y 
examines the signi.cance behind the naming of many pro­fessions. She notes professions that involve picking 
.owers or sewing clothes, activities often associated with femininity, have been given more gender-neutral 
labels like herbalism and tailoring. The use of the term tailoring not only de-feminizes the profession, 
but in fact masculinizes it instead [pg. 79]. Corneliussen is opti­mistic, that while the binary of men 
s work and women s work is still perpetuated in the of.ine world, there is room for play and experimentation 
with gender roles in a gameworld such as WoW. Recognizing that this is an area largely unexplored, this 
study looks at what sorts of relationships (if any) can be observed between the distribution of sex and 
profession among WoW NPCs. 1 Theoretical Framework It would be unfair to characterize WoW as being solely 
constructed by Blizzard and consumed in a non-critical manner by players. In­formed and challenged by 
players themselves, via alpha and beta testing, and later through feedback given in forum posts and else­where, 
the larger sociocultural context in which Blizzard makes its choices cannot be ignored [Rubenstein 2007]. 
However, while players frequently voice their approval or disapproval of changes that might alter what 
they can do (e.g. changes to spells they can cast) and how they can play the game (e.g. changes to PVP 
or dun­geon encounters), it seems that they do not tend to challenge the larger backdrop (e.g. lore) 
of the game. In their 2008 characterization of gender and video games, Henry Jenkins and Justine Cassell 
identi.ed the key gender issues which have largely remained unchanged in the intervening two decades. 
These issues are: (a) the debate about whether girls do and can and should play video games and (b) the 
concern that women are still vastly underrepresented in the .elds that design digital technol­ogy [2008, 
pg. 5]. Jenson and de Castell [2010] note that of the growing body of research that has documented girls/women 
playing and (sometimes) making games, much of it continues to reproduce gender-stereotyped accounts of 
what women/girls want, what they prefer, what they like, how they play and what choices they make when 
they play. In some sense, the work highlighted by Jenson and de Castell [2010] has paralleled the research 
on gender and technology gen­ 2We have chosen to exclude Archeology (and the rest of the Cataclysm expansion 
data about profession trainers) from this study as the expansion was still in the .nal stages of beta 
testing during the writing of this paper. Occupation Males Females P-Value Alchemy 21 12 1.0000 Blacksmithing 
30 9 0.0958 Cooking 24 12 0.7317 Enchanting 15 11 0.6852 Engineering 25 7 0.0982 First Aid 14 18 0.0281 
Fishing 23 8 0.2641 Herbalism 12 21 0.0032 Inscription 10 8 0.6263 Jewelcrafting 9 6 0.7949 Leatherworking 
24 16 0.7440 Mining 24 2 0.0016 Skinning 16 11 0.6937 Tailoring 18 15 0.3677 Table 1: Summary of the 
breakdown of NPC sexes by occupation. The binomial p-values are also included, and the bolded rows indi­cated 
statistical signi.cance on the 5% level. erally, continuing to focus primarily on the documentation of 
choice, lack of interest, and differing ability from their gen­eralized and technologically able male 
counterparts. What remains in most of this work is a predominant, indeed, an almost intuitive re.ex to 
crudely attribute difference as demarcated by male/female sex binaries. This re.ex is present in even 
the most current work on gender and digital game play and presents itself no less persis­tently in research 
that sees itself as assiduously attempting not to re­invoke gender-/sex-based stereotypes [Walkerdine 
2007; Williams et al. 2009; Winn and Heeter 2009]. For researchers whose in­terest is in explaining the 
status quo rather than challenging it, it is easy to .nd theoretical frameworks most notoriously gender 
role theories [Chodorow 1994; Williams et al. 2009] which tell us that people do what they do because 
of gender role expecta­tions . It takes no intellectual effort (or political will) to simply describe 
stereotypical patterns and choices, and then to explain them by reference to stereotypes. Invariably, 
when observations are made about differences in play styles, for instance, or in repre­sentation and 
games, gender-normative reasons for these observed differences are advanced and widely accepted. But 
there is a major .aw in that approach, and it is this: just because girls and women are not represented 
as often in games or in non-stereotypical roles, does not mean that things have to be that way. What 
we are not trying to do here is to reinforce stereotypes. In­stead, we are attempting to show where and 
how there might be something more to it than just the norm. Also, because NPCs are understudied in most 
game studies research to date (for work that has engaged with this subject see for example [Klastrup 
2009; Krzywinska 2008; Langer 2008]), we also want to show where and how those normative frameworks are 
working to marginalize women, even if this is done through unequal and stereotypical rep­resentation. 
 2 Methods &#38; Data Using the World of Warcraft Wiki, a community-generated database for game-related 
knowledge, we compiled a list of NPCs, focusing on sex and occupation. In existence since 2004, the wiki 
contains over 80,000 WoW related articles and is a one of a handful of ma­jor online sources for WoW 
knowledge. Data was collected about all NPCs currently active in the game and listed as being involved 
in training of a profession, including the NPC s name, sex, occu­pation, faction (Horde, Alliance, or 
neutral), their location in the game, and (if relevant) the highest level of training they provide. This 
list was then sorted according to profession and the data set was cleaned by removing invalid and duplicate 
NPCs. This resulted in a database of World of Warcraft NPCs whom players can visit to purchase profession 
training for their character. In total, the dataset contains 421 NPCs, representing 18 races and 14 professions. 
Table 1 gives the breakdown of NPCs with respect to occupation and sex. In our dataset, there are 265 
male and 156 female NPCs for an overall ratio of 63:37. In Figure 1, both sexes are presented as percentages. 
These percentages are broken down by profession, and compared to the overall sex ratio. Finally, a binomial 
test was performed on each occupation, and the resulting p-value is included in Table 1. Here, the p-value 
represents the probability of obtaining the stated number of males and females, or numbers even further 
from the expected 63:37 split, solely due to chance. That is, a small p-value represents a statistically 
signi.cant divergence from the ex­pected ratio.  3 Discussion We found an overall binary sex breakdown 
comparable to that re­ported by Corneliussen. Consistently across all professions (except for .rst aid 
and herbalism) we found more male NPCs than female. Whereas Cornelieussen reported that, on average, 
one third of the NPCs in her sample are female (the total sample size is unstated and only referred to 
in percentages throughout her chapter) [pg. 75], our sample showed that 37% of profession training NPCs 
are female. Assuming a 5% con.dence level, only three professions are statis­tically signi.cant, that 
is, unlikely to be solely the result of chance: mining (reporting more male NPCs than would be expected), 
.rst aid, and herbalism (both reporting more female NPCs than would be expected). While our analysis 
does not seem to indicate a larger trend between professions and sex, it does indicate that two of these 
three outliers3 may possibly be explained by gender patterns set by game lore. When looking at the sex 
ratios of NPCs, mining trainers present considerably more male NPC trainers than would be expected sta­tistically. 
While falling outside the 5% con.dence level, we also noted that blacksmithing had 30 male NPCs and only 
9 females. Dwarves are the majority of WoW NPCs associated with both of these professions. A part of 
gaming lore and fantasy literature long before WoW, Dwarves are commonly associated with the treasure­seeking 
Dwarves found in the writing of J. R. R. Tolkien. While the WoW Dwarves have an origin story that .ts 
with the overarching narratives of the game, the stature, behaviour, and societal structure seem to stay 
fairly consistent with prior fantasy genre conventions that paint Dwarven societies as being primarily, 
if not completely male. When this larger fantasy lore allows for female Dwarves, they are often described 
as being bearded and having very mascu­line features [WoWWiki 2011a]. In WoW, Dwarves have physical attributes 
that differentiate between male and female bodies, but the overall tone of Dwarven fantasy lore remains, 
with males making up a larger portion of city guards and mining trainers. In the case of herbalism trainers, 
we observed a higher number of female NPCs than expected. Over a third of these NPCs were Night Elves. 
Like male Dwarves, larger numbers of female Night Elves can be expected due to the lore of the game. 
The World of Warcraft Wiki entry for Night Elf lore explains: Prior to the conclusion of the Third War, 
Night Elf soci­ ety was sharply divided by gender, with the vast majority 3First aid trainers were split 
mostly between three races: humans, fol­lowed by undead, and then Draenei. This does not seem to have 
a relation­ship to lore, according to our research to date. of men being druids and most women serving 
as war­riors, priestesses, or a combination thereof. These gen­der roles more or less de.ned the culture 
of the Kaldorei for ten thousand years. In the years since the end of the Third War, this gender division 
appears to have eased in favor of more practical concerns, setting aside its histor­ical strictures on 
membership [WoWWiki 2011b]. This seems contrary to Corneliussen s claim that the larger number of male 
Dwarves and female Night Elves appears to be linked to aesthetics. However, using game lore as part of 
our explanation for two out of the three outliers should not be read as an excuse for any and all design 
decisions made by Blizzard. Instead, if this break from the larger distribution of gender amongst professions 
can be accounted for by lore of the Dwarves and the Night Elves, why was a larger lore not constructed 
for all professions? While we have observed that both male and females are represented for all WoW professions 
(albeit, not equally) we would like to sug­gest two examples that further complicate the idea of the 
existence of male and female NPCs being simply enough to represent equal­ity . The .rst involves the 
level of expertise assigned to NPCs within WoW. Just as there are novices and experts among players, 
there are NPC trainers who are labeled as apprentices, and NPCs who are labeled as being highly skilled 
(otherwise known as Grand Masters). For example, while both women and men can teach a player the skill 
of herbalism, 4 out of 5 Grand Master herbalism trainers are women. A similar trend is noted at the Grand 
Master level for mining, where 3 out of 4 trainers at this level are male. This might be viewed as supporting 
a sociocultural norm of ex­pertise surrounding men s work and women s work , represented here by the 
level of Grand Master . Additionally, there are interesting semantic differences in the titles given 
to many of the NPC profession trainers. For example, within the .rst aid profession there are .ve NPCs 
with titles: two males with the title Doctor , one female with the title Nurse , and two others with 
the title Anchorite (one male and one female). Nurse Neela can train a player in the early levels of 
.rst aid, and yet both doctors teach .rst aid at the artisan level, one level above Nurse Neela s instructional 
capabilities. There are several female healers included within this profession, but a distinction between 
women s work and men s work within the .eld of medicine has been tran­scribed to the world of Azeroth 
through the use of the titles of doc­tor and nurse. In some cases, female NPCs received feminized versions 
of a ti­tle, such as a female tailoring trainer labeled as a Sempstress or enchanting trainers as Enchantress 
(female), rather than Enchanter or High Enchanter (male). In the stereotypically feminine pursuit of 
cooking, WoW has more male trainers (24) than female (12). However, male trainers were given titles such 
as Cook or Master Chef, and none of the females are given a special title. The lack of female NPC titles 
also exists among inscription trainers: none of the female trainers have titles, while male NPCs are 
given titles such as Recorder, Scribe, Booker, or Professor. Finally, we wish to draw attention to the 
engineering profession, which is not statisti­cally signi.cant at the 5% level, yet it still has considerably 
more males (25) than females (7). The male engineer trainers have titles such as Arti.cer, Chief Engineer, 
or Tinkmaster, while only one female NPC is given a title (which in fact, reads more like a nick­name). 
Didi the Wrench could be an indicator of Didi s particular adeptness with this tool, or it could be a 
play on the wench . A similar sort of naming convention is used for two male .shing train­ers: Old Man 
Robert and Fishy Ser ji . Much like the multiple ways the Wrench can be interpreted, so too are we left 
to wonder if Fishy is suspicious, or merely adept at his profession.  Figure 1: Fraction of male and 
female NPCs, separated into occupation. The overall sex ratio (63:37) is shown as the grey dashed line. 
The upper error bars indicate the 1 sigma normal approximate error in the fraction of female NPCs, which 
the lower error bars indicate the normal approximate error in the fraction of male NPCs. Corneliussen 
theorizes that the overall ratio of male to female NPCs may have been chosen to re.ect the real world 
demographics of WoW players [pp. 75 76]. While the data we present here cannot support or disprove this 
claim, we note that it does highlight the fact that male and female bodies are not equally represented 
within the world of Azeroth. Despite these divisions of labour seeming to have their roots in the lore 
of the gameworld, it is important to remem­ber that just as the ratio of male to female NPCs was decided 
by the game s developers, so too has the lore been created by Blizzard. These may be tropes that are 
popular amongst other fantasy role­play games, but how have these conventions become so normal­ized? 
WoW is a .ctional fantasy-themed MMORPG, yet it seems unfortunate that the stereotypes surrounding gendered 
labour have been encoded into the game. Rather than challenging gendered as­sumptions that persist in 
the lore from which they draw, perhaps by creating a matriarchal Dwarven society, Blizzard simply maintains 
the status quo.  4 Conclusion &#38; Future Research Corneliussen has laid the groundwork for studies 
like this one to build upon. However, we stress the importance for further research to take into account 
both the ways in which design choices for WoW are in.uenced not only by technological factors such as 
database and software design, but also by the players expectations and feed­back, and by the larger gender 
relations of the world of which WoW is a part. As Johnson [2010] argues, when analyzing the impacts of 
a technology on gender relations, analysts must be conscious of the ways in which technology carries 
pre-existing notions of gender possibilities, presentations and performances. Rather than look­ing for 
equity (or parity ), the focus should be on creating and maintaining technology that favors women [pg. 
42]. Imagining a gameworld that breaks from gendered stereotypes is not some­thing easy to quantify, 
though Corneliussen does try to do so. This is not something that can be done merely by changing the 
sexes of NPCs to represent a more equal ratio between males and fe­males. MMORPGs like WoW are sociotechnical 
systems that will be continually in.uenced both by their developers and their play­ers, which are in 
turn in.uenced by the larger world in which both of these actors exist. And yet, at the most basic level, 
is it really too much to expect at the very least, equal numbers, equal expertise, and equal titling? 
In documenting (largely) qualitative research projects that involve both boys/girls and/or men/women, 
research accounts continue to compress gender based differences into sex-based difference nec­essarily 
coded as male or female. As Jenson and de Castell [2010] point out, this re.ex is present in even the 
most current work on gender and digital game play and presents itself no less persistently in research 
that sees itself as assiduously attempting not to rein­voke gender-/sex-based stereotypes [pg. 63]. While 
our study did not uncover a systematic bias or overt gender stereotyping, neither equality, nor equity 
exist within the WoW gameworld. We hope that this paper has drawn attention to conscious design de­cisions 
made by a developer. Speci.cally, we have argued against the ways in which it is troubling for academics 
and scienti.c lit­erature to attempt to identify the gender relations of a gameworld by boiling them 
down to a strict numbering exercise of head counts of NPCs and ascribing a direct and linear binary relation 
between the gender distributions in the gameworld and an arbitrary designer choice. This latter sort 
of approach reinforces a tendency in aca­demic research to crudely attribute difference as demarcated 
by male/female sex binaries [Jenson and de Castell 2010, pg. 63]. We argue that there are a complex array 
of other forces, in.uences and processes to consider when examining a sociotechnical system like WoW, 
including player preferences and conditioning, the fantasy lore upon which the game draws (as well as 
produces), and how gender is depicted and enacted through professional roles, naming conventions, and 
the larger sociotechnical culture of the game.  References CHEN, M. 2009. Communication, coordination, 
and camaraderie in world of warcraft. Games &#38; Culture 4, 47 73. CHODOROW, N. 1994. Femininities, 
Masculinities, Sexualities: Freud and Beyond. University Press of Kentucky, Lexington, KY. CORNELIUSSEN, 
H. G. 2008. World of warcraft as a playground for feminism. In Digital Culture, Play, and Identity: A 
World of Warcraft Reader, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, H. G. Cor­neliussen and J. W. Rettberg, Eds., 63 
86. DUCHENEAUT, N., YEE, N., NICKELL, E., AND MOORE, R. J. 2006. alone together? : exploring the social 
dynamics of mas­sively multiplayer online games. In Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on Human Factors 
in computing systems, ACM, ACM, 407 416. HIGGIN, T. 2009. Blackless fantasy: The disappearance of race 
in massively multiplayer online role-playing games. Games and Culture 4, 1, 3 26. JENKINS, H., AND CASSELL, 
J. 2008. From quake girls to des­perate housewives: A decade of gender and computer games. In Beyond 
Barbie and Mortal Kombat: New perspectives on gender and gaming, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, Y. Kafai, 
C. Heeter, J. Denner, and J. Sun, Eds., 5 20. JENSON, J., AND DE CASTELL, S. 2010. Gender, simulation, 
and gaming: Research review and redirections. Simulation &#38; Gaming 4, Feb, 51 71. JOHNSON, D. G. 2010. 
Sorting out the question of feminist tech­nology. In Feminist Technology, University of Illinois Press, 
Chicago, IL, L. L. Layne, S. L. Vostral, and K. Boyer, Eds., 36 54. KLASTRUP, L. 2009. The worldness 
of EverQuest: Exploring a 21st century .ction. Game Studies 9, 1, Accessed March 1, 2011 at http://gamestudies.org/0901/articles/klastrup. 
KRZYWINSKA, T. 2008. World creation and lore: World of War­craft as rich text. In Digital Culture, Play, 
and Identity: A World of Warcraft Reader, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, H. G. Cor­neliussen and J. W. Rettberg, 
Eds., 123 142. LANGER, J. 2008. The familiar and the foreign: Playing (post)colonialism in World of Warcraft. 
In Digital Culture, Play, and Identity: A World of Warcraft Reader, MIT Press, Cam­bridge, MA, H. G. 
Corneliussen and J. W. Rettberg, Eds., 87 108. MCARTHUR, V., TEATHER, R. J., AND STUERZLINGER, W. 2010. 
Comparing 3d content creation interfaces in two virtual worlds: World of warcraft and second life. Journal 
of Virtual Worlds and Gaming 2, 3, 239 258. MILLER, J. L., AND CROWCROFT, J. 2009. Avatar movement in 
world of warcraft battlegrounds. In Proceedings of the 8th Annual Workshop on Network and Systems Support 
for Games (NetGames 09), IEEE Press, DiGRA. PACE, T., HOUSSIAN, A., AND MCARTHUR, V. 2009. Are so­cially 
exclusive values embedded in the avatar creation inter­faces of mmorpgs? Journal of Information, Communication 
and Ethics in Society 7, 2/3, 192 210. RUBENSTEIN, A. 2007. Idealizing fantasy bodies. Accessed Jan­uary 
16, 2011 at http://www.theirisnetwork.org/archives/12. TRONSTAD, R. 2008. Character identi.cation in 
world of warcraft. the relationship between capacity and appearance. In Digital Culture, Play, and Identity: 
A World of Warcraft Reader, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, H. G. Corneliussen and J. W. Rettberg, Eds., 249 
264. WALKERDINE, V. 2007. Children, Gender, video games: Towards a relational approach to multimedia. 
Palgrave Macmillan, Bas­ingstroke, UK. WILLIAMS, D., DUCHENEAUT, N., XIONG, L., ZHANG, Y., YEE, N., AND 
NICKELL, E. 2006. From tree house to bar­racks: The social life of guilds in world of warcraft. Games 
and Culture 1, 4, 338 361. WILLIAMS, D., CONSALVO, M., CAPLAN, S., AND YEE, N. 2009. Looking for gender: 
Gender roles and behaviors among online gamers. Journal of Communication 59, 2009, 700 725. WINN, J., 
AND HEETER, C. 2009. Gaming, gender, and time: Who makes time to play? Sex Roles 61, 1 13. WOODCOCK, 
B. n. d. An analysis of mmog subscription growth. mmogchart.com v23.0. Accessed January 15, 2011 at: 
http://users.telenet.be/mmodata/Charts/Subs 1.png. WOODFIELD, R. 2008. What women want from work: gender 
and occupational choice in the 21st century. Palgrave, New York, NY. WOWWIKI. 2011. Dwarf. Accessed January 
10, 2011 at: http://www.wowwiki.com/Dwarf#Female dwarves. WOWWIKI. 2011. Night elf. Accessed January 
10, 2011 at: http://www.wowwiki.com/Night elves.  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037700</article_id>
		<sort_key>80</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>5</pages>
		<display_no>6</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>2</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Designing stories]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[practices of narrative in 3D computer games]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>5</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037700</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037700</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Drawing on theories from game-, film-, and theatre studies, this paper explores two primary ways in which 3D computer games deal with stories. As evident in how these games are creatively designed and publically discussed, one of these approaches focuses on players as implied authors who guide heroes through challenging trials and tribulations. The other approach focuses on players as embodied participants in the story world; players become the hero and experience adventures of their own. This paper argues that in order to understand the differences between these two distinctive design practices it is necessary to critically review the representational logic of narrative as developed once in structuralist narratology and to develop an additional presentational logic, applicable to both marginal narrative practices of the past as well as mainstream practices of the present.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[film]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[game design]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[immersion]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[media comparison]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[narratology]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[presentation]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[representation]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[storytelling]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[theatre]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>J.5</cat_node>
				<descriptor/>
				<type/>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010469</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Arts and humanities</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809221</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487653676]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Teun]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Dubbelman]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Utrecht University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[t.dubbelman@uu.nl]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>265941</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Aarseth, E. 1997. <i>Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</i>. Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Abbott, H. P. 2008. <i>The Cambridge Introduction to Narrative</i>. 2nd edition, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Bordwell, D. 1985. <i>Narration in the Fiction Film</i>. London and New York: Routledge.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Branigan, E. 1992. <i>Narrative Comprehension and Film</i>. London and New York: Routledge.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Calleja, G. 2007. <i>Digital Games as Designed Experience: Reframing the Concept of Immersion</i>. Ph.D. thesis, Victoria University of Wellington.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Card, O. S. 1988. <i>Characters and Viewpoint</i>. Cincinnati: Writers Digest Books.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Chatman, S. 1978. <i>Story and Discourse. Narrative Structure in Fiction and Film</i>. New York: Cornell University Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Cremona, V. A. et al. 2004. <i>Theatrical Events: Borders -- Dynamics -- Frames</i>. New York and Amsterdam: Rodopi.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Elam, K. 2005. <i>The Semiotics of Theatre and Drama</i>. Taylor & Francis e-Library: Routledge. Accessed 21 October 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Gerrig, R. J. 1998. <i>Experiencing Narrative Worlds: On the Psychological Activities of Reading</i>. Colorado: Westview Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jahn, M. 2005. <i>Narratology: A Guide to the Theory of Narrative</i>. English Department: University of Cologne, http://www.uni-koeln.de/~ame02/pppn.htm. Accessed 8 March 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jenkins, H. 2004. Game Design as Narrative Architecture. In N. Wardrip-Fruin and P. Harrigan (eds), <i>First Person: New Media as Story, Performance, and Game</i>. Cambridge: MIT Press, 118--130.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Jenkins, H. 2007. Narrative Spaces. In F. Von Borries, S. P. Walz and M. B&#246;ttger (eds), <i>Space Time Play: Computer Games, Architecture and Urbanism: The Next Level</i>. Basel, Boston and Berlin: Birkh&#228;user, 56--60.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Juul, J. 2005. Games Telling Stories? In J. Raessens and J. Goldstein (eds), <i>Handbook of Computer Game Studies</i>. Cambridge: MIT Press, 219--226.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Kostelanetz, R. 1981. <i>Theatre of Mixed-Means</i>. Ridgewood: Archae Editions.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Lehmann, H.-T.. 2006. <i>Postdramatic Theatre</i>. London and New York: Routledge.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Metz, C. 1974. <i>Film Language: A Semiotics of the Cinema</i>. (trans. M. Taylor), New York: Oxford University Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>551862</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_seq_no>18</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Murray, J. 1998. <i>Hamlet on the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in Cyberspace</i>. Cambridge: MIT Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1462133</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_seq_no>19</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Nitsche, M. 2009. <i>Video Game Spaces: Image, Play, and Structure in 3D Worlds</i>. Cambridge: MIT Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>20</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Prince, G. 1987. <i>A Dictionary of Narratology</i>. Lincoln and London: University of Nebraska Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>21</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Rimmon-Kenan, S. 2005. <i>Narrative Fiction: Contemporary Poetics</i>. 2&#60;sup&#62;nd&#60;/sup&#62; edition, Taylor & Francis e-Library: Routledge. Accessed 21 October 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1209229</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_seq_no>22</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Rollings, A. and Morris, D. 2004. <i>Game Architecture and Design. A New Edition</i>. Berkeley: New Riders Publishing.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>23</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ryan, M.-L. (ed.) 2004. <i>Narrative across Media: The Languages of Storytelling</i>. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>24</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Ryan, M.-L. 2001. Beyond Myth and Metaphor: The Case of Narrative in Digital Media. <i>Game Studies. The International Journal of Computer Game Research 1</i>, 1 (July), http://gamestudies.org/0101/ryan/. Accessed 8 March 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>25</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Schubert, T. and Crusius, J. 2002. Five Theses on the Book Problem: Presence in Books, Film and VR, http://www.igroup.org/projects/porto2002/SchubertCrusiusPorto2002.pdf. Accessed 21 October 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>26</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Stam, R. 2005. <i>New Vocabularies in Film Semiotics: Structuralism, Post-structuralism and Beyond</i>. Taylor & Francis e-Library: Routledge. Accessed 21 October 2010.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>27</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Todorov, T. 1969. <i>Grammaire du D&#233;cam&#233;ron</i>. The Hague: Mouton.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Designing Stories. Practices of Narrative in 3D Computer Games Teun Dubbelman Utrecht University t.dubbelman@uu.nl 
 Abstract Drawing on theories from game-, film-, and theatre studies, this paper explores two primary 
ways in which 3D computer games deal with stories. As evident in how these games are creatively designed 
and publically discussed, one of these approaches focuses on players as implied authors who guide heroes 
through challenging trials and tribulations. The other approach focuses on players as embodied participants 
in the story world; players become the hero and experience adventures of their own. This paper argues 
that in order to understand the differences between these two distinctive design practices it is necessary 
to critically review the representational logic of narrative as developed once in structuralist narratology 
and to develop an additional presentational logic, applicable to both marginal narrative practices of 
the past as well as mainstream practices of the present. CR Categories: J.5 [Computer Applications]: 
Arts and Humanities Arts, fine and performing; K.8.0 [Personal Computing]: General Games Keywords: Game 
Design, Narratology, Storytelling, Immersion, Representation, Presentation, Film, Theatre, Media comparison 
 1 Introduction The worst kinds of game are those (usually adventure games) in which it s obvious that 
the designer thought he was writing a film or a novel. It s the frustrated-author syndrome, and you know 
you re bearing the brunt of it when your choices in the game have shrunk to one linear path, or when 
you find yourself scrolling though neverending cutscene dialogues waiting to get to the action. - Rollings 
and Morris (2004: 13) Game designers who desire to tell a story, better write a film or a novel. One 
often encounters this statement on games and storytelling, both in popular as well as academic debates. 
This paper explores to what extent the practice of storytelling in games indeed deviates from narrative 
practices found in films or novels.    In what way is designing stories for this medium any different? 
First, this paper tries to explicate the narrative logics behind formats such as books and movies; second, 
it will investigate to what extent these logics also apply to 3D computer games; and third, it will distill 
from these inquiries two distinctive approaches to the design of game stories, one closely akin to conventional 
storytelling, the other more related to alternative narrative practices found in experience theatre and 
experimental movies. 2 Narrative as representation Although the scholarly interest in storytelling 
has a long history and can be traced all the way back to Plato s Republic and Aristotle s Poetics, the 
study of narratives as an autonomous academic discipline only came into existence in the 1960s. Termed 
'narratology' by Tzvetan Todorov in his work Grammaire du Décaméron (1969: 10), the theory of the narratological 
aims to present a logical and structural description of the way in which stories are told (Jahn 2005). 
Though scholars in what often is referred to as structuralist narratology disagree about the exact definition 
of narrative, their work unanimously conceives narrative as representational in nature. As explained 
by Marie-Laure Ryan in Narrative Across Media (2004), these narratologists believe the standard conception 
of narrativity to be manifested in the act of =telling somebody else that something happened, with the 
assumption that the addressee is not already aware of the events (13). Also, the etymological root of 
the word narrative defines it as a form of recounting, as it derives in part from the Latin verb narrare, 
which means .to recount.. A feasible definition of the structuralist concept of narrative, then, is given 
by Gerald Prince in his Dictionary of Narratology (1987). According to Prince, narrative should be thought 
of as =the recounting [ ] of one or more real or fictitious events communicated by one, two, or several 
(more or less overt) narrators to one, two, or several (more or less overt) narratees (58). What is 
distinctive about this particular conceptualization of narrative is that it understands narrative as 
something that communicates real or fictitious events from the past. The concept of recounting implies 
that the events expressed (the story) already happened and find themselves re-presented in the present 
by some discourse, whether verbal, written, pantomimic, or any other form of narrative transmission (Chatman 
1978). For structuralist narratologists, then, a narrative retrieves the there-and-then in the here-and-now, 
thereby suppressing (but not replacing) our direct experience of the here-and-now. Its modus operandi 
is concerned with communicating or re-presenting events, not with staging new events. Stories concern 
the there-and-then, and are solely expressed in the here-and-now (Metz 1974: 22). 3 Representation or 
presentation Although structuralist narratologists study various forms of narrative transmission, their 
concept of narrative has arisen mainly out of stories that are either told or written. Not surprisingly, 
it is in these narrative formats where one finds a strong representational logic (Elam 2005: 98). The 
19th century novel is exemplary here. Books of authors such as Charles Dickens or Jane Austen portray 
without exception the story as a thing recounted. This can be contributed largely to the presence of 
a narrator who, in telling the story to the reader, explicitly emphasis its .pastness.. Narrators establish 
the story as something that happened in the past by using the past tense when discussing, summing up, 
and commenting on the events pertinent to it and by employing specific temporal tropes (Rimmon-Kenan 
2005: 110; see also Stam 2005: 90). The representational approach to narrative becomes problematic however 
when applied to narrative formats without an explicit narrator. In cinema or theatre for example the 
discourse does not always clearly acknowledge the .pastness. of the story it expresses. We are presented 
with a sequence of images or gestures, and have the feeling as if the events projected or performed are 
happening right in front of us, in the here-and-now rather than the there-and-then. So to what extent 
are these events still representational in nature as the audience witnesses the events unfolding directly 
in front of them? Is this representational logic still valid? In the second edition of The Cambridge 
Introduction to Narrative (2008), Abbott addresses this specific problem, he writes: Those who favor 
Aristotelian distinctions sometimes use the word presentation for stories that are acted and representation 
(re-presentation) for stories that are told or written. The difference highlights the idea that in theater 
we experience the story as immediately present while we do not when it is conveyed through a narrator. 
My own view is that both forms of narrative are mediated stories and therefore involved in re-presentation, 
conveying a story that at least seems to pre-exist the vehicle of conveyance. (15) Like Abbott, I do 
not prefer to use the Aristotelian distinction between telling (diegesis) and showing (mimeses) to designate 
the difference between representation and presentation. I do prefer however, unlike Abbott, to keep the 
distinction in practice. To me, the logics of representation and presentation provide valuable insights, 
not when used to differentiate between vehicles of narrative conveyance, but when used to address different 
ways in which every single one of these vehicles in principle can deal with stories. Even a story that 
is told can have a presentational logic, and a story that is shown a representational. Admittedly, the 
representational logic governs many popular books and movies, but this logic seems confidently at home 
in not essential to the medium-specific form of these particular media. In terms of story, a Choose-Your-Own 
Adventure book operates differently than a 19th century novel, just as cinematic experiments as Lady 
in the Lake (Montgomery, 1947) or Enter the Void (Noé, 2009) work differently than most classical Hollywood 
blockbusters. 4 The logics of representation and presentation So, what is exactly the difference between 
a representational and a presentational approach to narrative? To get a clearer idea of how the two logics 
differ from each other, this article borrows from performance theory. In theatre studies, a clear distinction 
is made between representation and presentation, not to describe different ways of narrative transmission, 
but to describe different ways in which the performance of a story addresses the audience: There are 
two ways of relating to the audience during the performance of a story. The difference is clearest in 
theater. In a representational play, the actors all act as if there were a fourth wall between them and 
the audience. [ ] Presentational theater, on the other hand, tears down that imaginary fourth wall. The 
actors don t just admit the audience is there, they make constant contact with the audience. (Card 1988: 
134-135) Following Card, I believe the essential difference between representation and presentation to 
lie in the way the audience is addressed in the performance of a story, and consequently the kind of 
spatiotemporal consciousness that arises from this difference. The audience is either addressed as physically 
present or physically absent in the world of the story. In a representational story performance we often 
feel as if we are looking at events that belong to some other time and place, even though the performance 
happens in the here-and-now. The actions on stage .stand for. or .re-present. actions that unfold in 
another spatial and temporal moment. Sceneries, actors, and props all portray places, people and objects 
belonging to this dimension of the there-and-then (Elam 2005: 61). We as the audience, consequently, 
have a strong feeling we do not belong to this other construct of space and time; we observe it hidden 
behind the fourth wall, but do not have our place within it. Even though we experience the story in the 
here-and-now, we still feel as if it happens somewhere else than the here-and-now of our own physical, 
lived existence. Much like the representational story performances in theatre, most movies do not address 
the spectator as physically present within the world of the story (Schubert and Crusius 2002). The audience 
is positioned, in a sense, as a ghostly presence: consciously present, but physically absent, able to 
travel through temporal and spatial barriers (Bordwell 1985: 10). In their goal to show the events that 
are relevant to the story, movies often propel us forwards or backwards in space and time. In only a 
couple of hours we are mentally transported through many different moments in time while visiting many 
different places. Distinctive of narrative discourse when steered by a representational logic, is the 
feeling it creates in the audience as if they move away from the here-and-now of their physical existence 
towards the there-and-then of the story told. This feeling is commonly associated with the idea of narrative 
immersion, as Richard J. Gerrig describes in Experiencing Narrative Worlds. On the Psychological Activities 
of Reading (1999): Readers become "Lost in a book" (see Nell, 1988); moviegoers are surprised when the 
lights come back up; television viewers care desperately about the fates of soap opera characters; museum 
visitors are captivated by the stories encoded in daubs of paint. In each case, a narrative serves to 
transport an experiencer away from the here and now. (3) As will be explained later, the exact opposite 
seems to happen when the discourse is steered by a presentational logic. While we move away from the 
here-and-now towards the there-and-then of the story in what I refer to as the representological mode, 
we seem to stay in the here-and-now and the there-and-then of the story moves towards us in the presentological 
mode (think of reenactments, augmented reality or LARP). The narrative addresses the audience as physically 
present within the story expressed, thereby positioning them as embodied participants. Notably, both 
narrative modes alter our perception of the world around us. When following Janet Murray s exemplary 
definition of immersion as =the sensation of being surrounded by a completely other reality, as different 
as water is from air, that takes over all of our attention, our whole perceptual apparatus (1998: 98), 
the feelings evoked in presentation and representation both fall within the definition of immersion, 
even though the former operates distinctively different from the latter. In his thesis Digital Games 
as Designed Experience: Reframing the Concept of Immersion (2007), Gordon Calleja gives an insightful 
account of two forms of immersion in computer games that seems to align with my own distinction between 
representation and presentation. There is a distinction that needs to be made between holding mental 
images of a scene in mind while imagining being present within that scene, and occupying a location within 
a computer generated environment that anchors users with regards to other agents and enables them to 
interact with the environment from that specific location. [ ] When we identify with a character in a 
movie or a book, or imagine we are in the same room as the protagonist, we have no way of altering the 
course of events; no way of exerting agency. Likewise, the environments and characters represented in 
these media have no way of reacting to our presence, no matter how strongly we identify with them. (88) 
I follow Calleja in the distinction he makes between a form of immersion in which one has the feeling 
of being in the presence of characters without them noticing your presence (representological mode), 
and a form of immersion in which one has the illusion of being physically grounded to one specific location 
in space and time, perceivable for those who share this spatial and temporal moment (presentological 
mode). I prefer however not to incorporate the idea of interaction in this distinction. The distinction 
between narrative presentation and representation is not in essence a distinction between interactive 
and non-interactive. Both forms can be either interactive or non-interactive. Interactivity, or .ergodicity. 
in the context of storytelling, describes the condition of media objects where =nontrivial effort is 
required to allow the reader to traverse the text (Aarseth 1997: 1-2). Admittedly, many presentational 
narratives possess this ergodic quality, but there are many examples of representational narratives which 
also need nontrivial effort to make the story unfold, think of interactive DVD s, games such as Heavy 
Rain (2010) or particular experiential forms of theatre. All these examples hand the audience some form 
of control over the story s direction, thereby giving them the power to (co-)decide the faith of the 
story s characters. In her exploratory article =Beyond Myth and Metaphor - The Case of Narrative in Digital 
Media , Marie-Laure Ryan labels this form of narrative discourse .External-ontological interactivity., 
describing it as follows: Here the user is like the omnipotent god of the system. Holding the strings 
of the characters, from a position external to both the time and space of the fictional world, he specifies 
their properties, makes decisions for them, throws obstacles in their way, and sends them toward different 
destinies lines by altering their environment. (2001; my emphasis) Different from this form of interactivity, 
Ryan also proposes the categories of .Internal-ontological interactivity. and .Internal-exploratory interactivity., 
respectively referring to narrative discourse where =the user is cast as a character who determines his 
own fate by acting within the time and space of a fictional world and narrative discourse where =the 
user takes a virtual body with her into the fictional world, but her role in this world is limited to 
actions that have no bearing on the narrative events (my emphasis). Although these two categories differ 
from each other in the way the player influences the unfolding story, they both belong to the presentational 
logic as both categories give players the feeling as if things are happening in the here-and-now of their 
physical existence. In a presentational story performance events seem to happen in the perceptual field 
of our direct, firsthand or lived experience, even when mediated through a screen or some other means 
of transmission. The moment the performers acknowledge our presence, make eye contact, and start interacting 
with us, we change from being an invisible observer to an active participant. We are made aware of our 
physical presence and through this contact are drawn back to the here-and-now of our own bodily existence: 
physically anchored to one location in space and time and in principle able to act. Contrary to the representational 
logic, we do not move away from the here-and-now towards the there-and-then of the story, but as already 
stated, seem to stay in the here-and-now while the there-and-then of the story moves towards us. In effect, 
we still feel as if existing in some other spatial-temporal moment, but one that aligns with our experience 
of being physically in the here-and-now. In theatre studies, many scholars have tried to explain how 
this presentational mode differs from the representational one. Most importantly, performers make the 
audience aware of their own presence by inviting them into some form of interaction, thereby undoing 
the audience s spectatorial and voyeuristic position. This is often accompanied by a focus on the execution 
of acts that are real in the here-and-now and find their fulfillment in the very moment they happen. 
What occurs in the interaction between audience and spectator could be, but is not necessarily, meaningful 
in comparison with what has happened in the past and is about to happen in the future (Lehmann 2006: 
104-105). Also, the performers usually do not enact prescribed roles but carry out prescribed tasks. 
They can still assume fictional personalities, but not in the representational sense; their actions do 
not signify the actions of protagonists. Rather than representing others personas, performers try to 
alter their own self, typically by changing their appearance and behavior (Kostelanetz 1981: 8). As a 
result, the audience recognizes the performer through the fictional disguise. Performers lose their conventional 
function as an actor portraying a role, and make their performativity an integral part of the theatrical 
experience, often introducing a strong element of role-playing and playfulness in general (Cremona et 
al. 2004: 4-5). These characteristics also apply to the design of many story-driven games. In games such 
as Half-life (1998), BioShock (2007) or Fallout 3 (2008), the game characters, similar to the performers 
in the prior examples, make direct contact with players. They acknowledge our physical presence by looking 
into our eyes, and direct their speech towards us. The opening scene of Half-life 2 (2004) is particularly 
strong in making the player feel as if they are physically anchored in the story world. When the player 
steps of a train riding into a station, a flying robot moves in front of the player and takes a picture 
of him. In this very moment, the game explicitly addresses us as present and perceivable within the story 
world that unfolds around us. Not surprisingly, this does not happen in a representological game like 
Heavy Rain. Characters do not look into the camera directly. Their eyes focus on the avatar who the player 
is controlling, even in the case of a POV shot. As in conventional cinematography, the camera in these 
POV shots positions itself near, but not along, the avatar s line of sight. Rather than looking straight 
into our eyes, characters look slightly past us, thereby enhancing the sensation that these characters 
do not perceive us as being present. Also, in games like Half-life 2 we hardly find as many temporal 
devices (ellipses, flashbacks and flash forwards) as in games like Heavy Rain. The extensive use of these 
editing techniques makes the existence of a narrator recounting a story apparent behind the seemingly 
.presentness. of visual presentation (Branigan 1992: 146-147). Thus, Half-life 2 avoids these techniques 
as they would disrupt our feeling of being not only mentally, but also physically grounded in the story 
world. Like the theatrical performances discussed, the focus is on the execution of acts in the here-and-now, 
as Jesper Juul also emphasizes in one of his articles on game stories: =Now, not just in the sense that 
the viewer witnesses events now, but in the sense that the events are happening now, and that what comes 
next is not yet determined (2005: 223). Game characters play an important role in creating this focus. 
Like performers, they come equipped with a set of prescripted tasks. Their aim is not so much to represent 
certain events from a real or fictitious past, but rather to create new events through interaction within 
the confines of the narrative context. The freedom fighters the player encounters in Half-life 2 for 
example assist the player in various ways, based upon the situation at hand and the decisions the player 
makes. Every encounter results in a different outcome, but stays meaningful within the story world. As 
explained by Michael Nitsche in his book Video Game Spaces. Image, Play, and Structure in 3D Worlds (2008), 
story events like these do not seem to pre-exist the discourse they do not evoke the sensation of .pastness. 
 but seems to come into existence the very moment they happen: Narrating in video game spaces differs 
from that of fixed literary or cinematic pieces. It occurs at the same time as the generation of the 
interactive event and is influenced by it. While literary, cinematic, and many oral forms of narrating 
build on events past and retold, real-time virtual worlds like live television or radio broadcasts narrate 
the events at the moment of their manifestation. (55) A similar observation has been made by Henry Jenkins 
in his exploratory work on storytelling in computer games. In his often-cited article =Game Design as 
Narrative Architecture (2004; see also 2007), Jenkins discusses game stories as being essentially spatial. 
Although he does not really conceptually define the phenomenon of spatial stories or environmental storytelling, 
it seems that Jenkins understands them as being presentological in nature. He characterizes spatial stories 
as follows: =In many cases, the characters - our guides through these richly-developed worlds - are stripped 
down to the bare bones, description displaces exposition, and plots fragment into a series of episodes 
and encounters (2004: 122). Again, the same presentological characteristics I have discussed earlier 
seem to be foregrounded here. Events feel as if coming into existence in the very moment they are expressed 
as the discourse focuses on describing what happens in the here-and-now (description) rather than providing 
a lot of background information on the plot (exposition). Plots fragment into episodes and encounters. 
Unlike the representological mode, where the discourse structures events in tight strings of cause-and-effect, 
the discourse of presentation places events meaningfully besides each other rather than after each other. 
Spatial stories also portray the protagonist less as a distinctive other and more as an empty vessel 
for somebody to project one s own identity on. Because of this, they succeed in extending our physical 
presence and thus function effectively as guides through .richly-developed worlds., to repeat the words 
of Jenkins. All these presentological characteristics are apparent in many, if not most, of the popular 
story-driven games sold today. 5 Conclusion In this paper, I have explored the logics behind two distinctive 
ways in which avatar-based 3D games deal with stories. I have argued that a basic distinction can be 
made between games in which players steer a hero through challenging trials and tribulations (e.g. Heavy 
Rain) and games in which players become the hero and have adventures of their own (e.g. Half-life 2). 
After critically reconceptualizing the understanding of narrative as once developed in structuralist 
narratology, this paper has proposed the terms presentological and representological to describe the 
different workings of these two logics. Presentological games create a form of immersion in which things 
seem to happen in a time and place aligned with the here-and-now of our own physically anchored existence, 
even though we are not literally present. Representological games on the other hand create a form of 
immersion in which one feels consciously present but physically absent when things happen to others in 
a there-and-then; a spatiotemporal elsewhere removed from the here-and-now. References AARSETH, E. 
1997. Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature. Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press. 
ABBOTT, H.P. 2008. The Cambridge Introduction to Narrative. 2nd edition, Cambridge: Cambridge University 
Press. BORDWELL, D. 1985. Narration in the Fiction Film. London and New York: Routledge. BRANIGAN, 
E. 1992. Narrative Comprehension and Film. London and New York: Routledge. CALLEJA, G. 2007. Digital 
Games as Designed Experience: Reframing the Concept of Immersion. Ph.D. thesis, Victoria University of 
Wellington. CARD, O.S. 1988. Characters and Viewpoint. Cincinnati: Writers Digest Books. CHATMAN, S. 
1978. Story and Discourse. Narrative Structure in Fiction and Film. New York: Cornell University Press. 
 CREMONA, V.A. ET AL. 2004. Theatrical Events: Borders Dynamics Frames. New York and Amsterdam: Rodopi. 
 ELAM, K. 2005. The Semiotics of Theatre and Drama. Taylor &#38; Francis e-Library: Routledge. Accessed 
21 October 2010. GERRIG, R. J. 1998. Experiencing Narrative Worlds: On the Psychological Activities 
of Reading. Colorado: Westview Press. JAHN, M. 2005. Narratology: A Guide to the Theory of Narrative. 
English Department: University of Cologne, http://www.uni- koeln.de/~ame02/pppn.htm. Accessed 8 March 
2010. JENKINS, H. 2004. Game Design as Narrative Architecture. In N. Wardrip-Fruin and P. Harrigan (eds), 
First Person: New Media as Story, Performance, and Game. Cambridge: MIT Press, 118-130. JENKINS, H. 
2007. Narrative Spaces. In F. Von Borries, S.P. Walz and M. Böttger (eds), Space Time Play: Computer 
Games, Architecture and Urbanism: The Next Level. Basel, Boston and Berlin: Birkhäuser, 56-60. JUUL, 
J. 2005. Games Telling Stories? In J. Raessens and J. Goldstein (eds), Handbook of Computer Game Studies. 
Cambridge: MIT Press, 219-226. KOSTELANETZ, R. 1981. Theatre of Mixed-Means. Ridgewood: Archae Editions. 
 LEHMANN, H.-T. .2006. Postdramatic Theatre. London and New York: Routledge. METZ, C. 1974. Film Language: 
A Semiotics of the Cinema. (trans. M. Taylor), New York: Oxford University Press. MURRAY, J. 1998. Hamlet 
on the Holodeck: The Future of Narrative in Cyberspace. Cambridge: MIT Press. NITSCHE, M. 2009. Video 
Game Spaces: Image, Play, and Structure in 3D Worlds. Cambridge: MIT Press. PRINCE, G. 1987. A Dictionary 
of Narratology. Lincoln and London: University of Nebraska Press. RIMMON-KENAN, S. 2005. Narrative Fiction: 
Contemporary Poetics. 2nd edition, Taylor &#38; Francis e-Library: Routledge. Accessed 21 October 2010. 
 ROLLINGS, A. AND MORRIS, D. 2004. Game Architecture and Design. A New Edition. Berkeley: New Riders 
Publishing. RYAN, M.-L. (ed.) 2004. Narrative across Media: The Languages of Storytelling. Lincoln: 
University of Nebraska Press. RYAN, M.-L. 2001. Beyond Myth and Metaphor: The Case of Narrative in Digital 
Media. Game Studies. The International Journal of Computer Game Research 1, 1 (July), http://gamestudies.org/0101/ryan/. 
Accessed 8 March 2010. SCHUBERT, T. AND CRUSIUS, J. 2002. Five Theses on the Book Problem: Presence 
in Books, Film and VR, http://www.igroup.org/projects/porto2002/Schubert CrusiusPorto2002.pdf. Accessed 
21 October 2010. STAM, R. 2005. New Vocabularies in Film Semiotics: Structuralism, Post-structuralism 
and Beyond. Taylor &#38; Francis e-Library: Routledge. Accessed 21 October 2010. TODOROV, T. 1969. Grammaire 
du Décaméron. The Hague: Mouton.  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037701</article_id>
		<sort_key>90</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>5</pages>
		<display_no>7</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>3</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Beyond player types]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[gaming achievement goal]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>5</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037701</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037701</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>Education and psychology studies have used motivational constructs called achievement goals to predict learning success and response to failure. In this article we adapted classroom achievement goal scales to instead measure gaming achievement goals. We collected survey data from 432 university students to empirically examine the applicability and utility of achievement goal constructs from education research to gaming. We introduced a new approach to player types based on mastery and performance gaming achievement goals. Four types are studied: super-achievers, mastery-only, performance-only, and non-achievers. We also examined the relationship between our four achievement goal player types to the traditional achiever, explorer player types. We found that Interest in exploration in games can exist in any of the four types, but those with strong mastery goals have the lowest interest in exploration. Gender and gaming frequency were significantly related to gaming achievement goals. The implications and suggestions for designing games for learning and entertainment are discussed.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[achievement goal]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[exploration]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[game design]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[motivation]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[player experience]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[player type]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[serious game]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<general_terms>
			<gt>Design</gt>
			<gt>Experimentation</gt>
			<gt>Human Factors</gt>
			<gt>Measurement</gt>
			<gt>Performance</gt>
		</general_terms>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809222</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100547957]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Carrie]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Heeter]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Michigan State University, San Francisco, CA]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[heeter@msu.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809223</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81460651302]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Yu-Hao]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Lee]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[leeyuhao@msu.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809224</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81365598309]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Ben]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Medler]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[benmedler@gatech.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809225</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81327490117]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Brian]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Magerko]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[magerko@gatech.edu]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Bartle, R. A. 1996. Hearts, clubs, diamonds, spades: Players who suit MUDs. <i>Journal of MUD Research</i>, 1, 1.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Butler, R., and Neuman, O. 1995. Effects of task and ego achievement goals on help-seeking behaviors and attitudes. <i>Journal of Educational Psychology</i>, 87, 261--271.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Dweck, C. S., and Elliott, E. S. 1983. Achievement motivation. In <i>Handbook of child psychology</i>, P. Mussen and E. M. Hetherington, Ed. Wiley, New York, 643--691]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Dweck, C. S., and Leggett, E. L. 1988. A social-cognitive approach to motivation and personality. <i>Psychological Review</i>, 95, 256--273.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Elliot, A. J. 2005. A conceptual history of the achievement goal construct. In, <i>Handbook of competence and motivation</i>, A. Elliot and C. Dweck, Ed. Guilford Press, New York, 52--72.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Elliott, E. S., and Dweck, C. S. 1988. Goals: An approach to motivation and achievement. <i>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</i>, 54, 5--12.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Elliot, A., and McGregor, H. 2001. A 2 X 2 Achievement Goal Framework. <i>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</i>, 80, 3, 501--519.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Elliot, A. J., and Thrash, T. M. 2001. Achievement goals and the hierarchical model of achievement motivation. <i>Educational Psychology Review</i>, 13, 139--156.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Erdley, C., Cain, K., Loomis, C., Dumas-Hines, F., and Dweck, C. S. 1997. The relations among children's social goals, implicit personality theories and response to social failure. <i>Developmental Psychology</i>, 33, 263--272.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Grant. H. and Dweck, C. 2003. Clarifying achievement goals and their impact. <i>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</i>, 85, 3, 541--553.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Heeter, C., Lee, Y. H, Medler, B., and Magerko. B. in press. Impacts of forced serious game play on vulnerable subgroups. <i>International Journal of Games and Computer-Mediated Simulations</i>.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Henderlong, J., and Lepper, M. 2002. The effects of praise on children's intrinsic motivation: A review and synthesis. <i>Psychological Bulletin</i>, 128, 774--795.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Lepper, M. R., and Henderlong, J. 2000. Turning "play" into "work" and "work" into "play": 25 years of research on intrinsic versus extrinsic motivation. In <i>Intrinsic and extrinsic motivation: the search for optimal motivation and performance</i>. C. Sansone and J. M. Harackiewicz Eds. Academic Press: San Diego. 257--307]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>14</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Magerko, B., Heeter, C., and Medler, B. 2010. Tapping into the hidden potential of serious games: Accommodating individual differences. In <i>Interdisciplinary models and tools for serious games: Emerging concepts and future directions</i>. R. Van Eck Ed., IGI Global.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>15</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Mahncke H. W., Bronstone, A., and Merzenich, M. M. 2006. Brain plasticity and functional losses in the aged: Scientific bases for a novel intervention. <i>Program Brain Research</i>, 157, 81--109.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>16</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Yee, N. 2006. Motivations of Play in Online Games. <i>CyberPsychology and Behavior</i>, 9, 6, 772--775.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>17</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Yee, N. 2008. Maps of digital desires: Exploring the topography of gender and play in online games. In <i>Beyond barbie and mortal kombat: New perspectives in gender and gaming</i>. Kafai, Y., Heeter, C., Denner, J. and Sun, J. Eds., MIT Press: Boston, MA.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
 Beyond Player Types: Gaming Achievement Goal Carrie Heeter Yu-Hao Lee Ben Medler Brian Magerko Michigan 
State University Michigan State University 2467 Funston Avenue 409 CAS, MSU San Francisco, CA 94116 415-681-6473 
East Lansing, MI 48824­1212 heeter@msu.edu leeyuhao@msu.edu ABSTRACT Education and psychology studies 
have used motivational constructs called achievement goals to predict learning success and response 
to failure. In this article we adapted classroomachievement goal scales to instead measure gaming achievementgoals. 
We collected survey data from 432 university students to empirically examine the applicability and utility 
of achievementgoal constructs from education research to gaming. We introduced a new approach to player 
types based on mastery and performance gaming achievement goals. Four types are studied: super­achievers, 
mastery-only, performance-only, and non-achievers. We also examined the relationship between our four 
achievement goal player types to the traditional achiever, explorer player types.We found that Interest 
in exploration in games can exist in any ofthe four types, but those with strong mastery goals have the 
lowestinterest in exploration. Gender and gaming frequency were significantly related to gaming achievement 
goals. The implications and suggestions for designing games for learning andentertainment are discussed. 
Categories and Subject Descriptors Player experience, Game design,  Keywords achievement goal, exploration, 
motivation, player type, serious game, 1. INTRODUCTION Digital games are increasingly used in school 
curriculums, corporations or military training, and some games are even prescribed by health professionals 
as treatments. Unlike entertainment games that are played voluntarily, these serious games are often 
assigned to users. Most previous research on digital game motivations has focused on voluntary play, 
little isknown about how people are motivated in assigned gamingsituations, which could affect how well 
these games achieve theirintended outcomes. Our recent research [11] found importantdifferences in forced 
play behaviors and gaming predilections ofthree potentially vulnerable subgroups reluctant gamers, non- 
Copyright &#38;#169; 2011 by the Association for Computing Machinery, Inc. Permission to make digital 
or hard copies of part or all of this work for personal or classroom use is granted without fee provided 
that copies are not made or distributed for commercial advantage and that copies bear this notice and 
the full citation on the first page. Copyrights for components of this work owned by others than ACM 
must be honored. Abstracting with credit is permitted. To copy otherwise, to republish, to post on servers, 
or to redistribute to lists, requires prior specific permission and/or a fee. Request permissions from 
Permissions Dept, ACM Inc., fax +1 (212) 869-0481 or e-mail permissions@acm.org. Sandbox 2011, Vancouver, 
British Columbia, Canada, August 10, 2011.&#38;#169; 2011 ACM 978-1-4503-0775-8/11/0008 $10.00 Georgia 
Institute ofGeorgia Institute of Technology Technology 686 Cherry St. 686 Cherry St. Atlanta, GA 30332-0165 
Atlanta, GA 30332-0165 benmedler@gatech.edu 404-894-2739 magerko@gatech.edu gamers, and female gamers 
identified in the author s previouswork [14]. The current research explores theoretical underpinnings 
to predict different impacts. Education and psychology studies have used motivational constructs called 
achievement goals to predict learning successand response to failure. One kind of achievement goals calledmastery 
goals (e.g. striving to do well) have been linked to more learning. Another achievement goal called performance 
goals(i.e., striving to do better than others) can sometimes lead to morelearning, but sometimes interfere 
with learning. Education achievement goal constructs seem to have strong parallels todigital gaming achievement 
goals because achievement goals and reward systems are integral to game design. Achievements in school 
are rewarded by sense of mastery of subject matter,progression through grade levels, honor roll lists, 
and praise fromteachers and peers. Achievements in games are rewarded by asense of mastery of the game, 
progression through levels, by points, prizes, inclusion on leader boards, and admiration by otherplayers. 
Within a game, a player may opt to pursue mastery goals(try to do well at the game) or performance goals 
(try tooutperform other players). A player may also be unmotivated byeither form of achievement goal, 
particularly if play is assignedrather than voluntary. We used survey questions to explore whether gamingachievement 
goals influence game play in similar ways to howeducational achievement goals influence learning. Gamingachievement 
goals could help to determine whether and howpeople play games and, in the case of games for learning, 
which players are more likely to learn from those games.  2. ACHIEVEMENT GOALS Achievement goals can 
be defined as motivation for taking onchallenging behaviors or how individuals perceive and respond toachievement 
situations [4, 5]. Achievement goals focus on motivation to behave competently or the desire to do well 
(or toavoid doing poorly) on a task or activity (Elliot, 2005). Achievement goals relate to the extrinsic 
reward of being competent, not to the intrinsic rewards of doing somethingcompetently. Two achievement 
goal constructs were identified as key predictors of behavior: performance goals and mastery goals[3, 
10]. A person with performance goals seeks to demonstratetheir ability and avoid demonstrating inability 
in comparison to others. But a person with mastery goals is motivated by developing competence and task 
mastery regardless of others. Performance goals is predicted to lead to debilitating response tofailure, 
while mastery goals were expected to be more likely tocontribute to successful learning from failure 
[6]. Elliot and McGregor [7] later introduced a 2x2 achievement goalframework, in which definition (absolute 
versus normative) andvalence (approach versus avoidance) are the two dimensions ofcompetence. This framework 
yields four achievement goal constructs that our study adopts (see Figure 1). The mastery­approach goal 
focuses on attaining absolute competence or mastering a task. The performance-approach goal focuses on 
attaining normative competence (e.g. outperforming others). Onthe avoidance side, mastery-avoidance goal 
focuses on avoidingabsolute self-referential or task referential incompetence, and performance-avoidance 
goal focuses on avoiding normative incompetence (not performing worse than others) [7]. Figure 1. McGregor 
and Elliot s 2x2 Achievement Goal Framework The mastery-approach goal is the most preferred achievement 
goal in a learning context, followed by performance-approachgoals. Third most preferable is the mastery-avoidance 
goals,which may lead to less optimal consequences, but are still lessharmful to learning than performance-avoidance 
goals [7, 8]. In the context of games for learning, players who are motivated byavoidance goals want 
to avoid failing, and for that reason probably will avoid difficult or complex games where the risk offailure 
is high. There is nothing inherently wrong with enjoying easy success and avoiding challenges in games 
for entertainment.However, when it comes to games for classroom learning orcorporate training, players 
whose play is driven by avoidance goals would be dysfunctional learners because their attention would 
focus on avoiding failure instead of on learning. They arealso less likely to learn from mistakes. Avoidance 
goals are also a dysfunctional for physical and cognitive exercise games becausein order to receive cognitive 
benefits, players need to stretch a little beyond what is comfortable and easy, taking on challenges 
at the edge of their ability [15]. Limiting play to easy brain gamechallenges minimizes the cognitive 
exercise benefits from the games. Performance goals may also be dysfunctional for learning games,because 
they focus attention on extrinsic rewards rather than intrinsic goals such as mastery (of the game or 
subject matter). Research showed that performance-avoidance goals particularlyinterfere with classroom 
learning [12, 13]. 3. RESEARCH QUESTIONS In order to investigate the empirical utility of gaming achievementgoal 
constructs, our first research question validates the gaming achievement goal constructs and compares 
those constructs toclassroom achievement goals: RQ1: What is the distribution of players with mastery-approach,mastery-avoidance, 
performance-approach, and performance­avoidance gaming achievement goals? How do gamingachievement goals 
compare to classroom achievement goals? Can gaming achievement goal constructs be used to construct a 
singleplayer type variable? How does gaming achievement player typerelate to gender and gaming frequency? 
Next, we examine the relationships between gaming achievementmotivations and player characteristics. 
RQ2: How do gaming achievement motivations relate to enjoying accomplishment in games? How does enjoyment 
of accomplishment relate to gaming achievement goals, gender andgaming frequency? Prior research on player 
motivation in online games has identifiedexploration and achievement as important motivations [1, 16, 
17]. However, exploration and achievement have been presented asmutually exclusive player motivations. 
Anecdotal evidence and pretests of our survey instruments suggest this is probably not the case. RQ3: 
How do gaming achievement goals relate to enjoyingexploration in games? How does enjoyment of exploration 
relate to gaming achievement goals, gender and gaming frequency? 4. RESEARCH METHOD An online survey 
was administered to 432 undergraduatesinterested in obtaining extra credit in six large telecommunication,communication, 
history, and culture classes at two large universities. Since a main goal of this study was to explore 
theidea of gaming achievement goals and to examine the relation ofgaming achievement goals to gaming 
preference and enjoyment,for the achievement measures we used Elliot and McGregor s [7]scale and also 
asked those same questions adapted to gamingrather than classroom achievement. Both scales consisted 
of 12 item seven-point Likert-type questions (1 = not at all true of me to7 = very true of me) such as 
My goal is to ...do better in my classes than other students, and My goal is to ...avoid doing worse 
in my classes than other students. The originalachievement scale has been used in many previous studies 
tomeasure classroom achievement goals [2, 9]. We created parallel questions to measure gaming achievement 
goals such as My goalis to ... play better than other players, and My goal is to ...avoidplaying worse 
than other players. Our gaming achievement measures showed high reliability. Cronbach s alpha for mastery­approach 
gaming achievement goals (.90), mastery-avoidance (.84), performance-approach (.82), and performance-avoidance 
(.85). Enjoyment of accomplishment (related to Bartle and Yee s achiever player motivation from prior 
research) and exploration(related to Bartle and Yee s explorer player motivation) weremeasured by a series 
of gaming predilection questions tapping common gaming experiences. We also asked participants demographic 
questions such as gender, age, GPA and how recently they had played a digital game. Of the participants 
in thestudy: 26.2 percent were classified as Non-Gamers who playedgames for two hour or less per week, 
58.4 percent were ModerateGamers who played more than two hours but less than five hoursper week, and 
15.4 percent were Avid Gamers who played forfive or more hours per week. One third of the study participants 
were female.  5. DISCUSSIONS 5.1 Distribution and Relation of Gaming and Classroom Achievement Goals 
In order to investigate gaming achievement goals, we begin byexamining the relation between gaming achievement 
goals and classroom achievement goals. All four measures of gaming achievement goals were significantly 
correlated with their classroom counterpart (Mastery approach r=.93, p<.001; Mastery avoidance r=.20, 
p<.001; Performance approach r=.32, p<.001; Performance avoidance r=.41, p<.001). A student s tendency 
to bemotivated to earn good grades in the classroom was significantly correlated with their desire to 
earn high scores and to avoid failure in games. Despite the correlation between classroom and gamingachievement 
goals, paired t-tests showed significant differences inthe respondents degree of gaming achievements 
goals comparedto classroom achievement goals for all four indices. Gaming mastery approach (t[431]=8.35, 
p<.001) and mastery avoidance (t[426]=5.70, p<.001) goals were both significantly lower than for classroom 
achievement. But gaming performance approach (t[427]=5.53, p<.001) and performance avoidance (t[426]=2.38, 
p<.05) goals were both significantly higher than classroom achievement. In other words, performance is 
a more importantachievement goal for gaming, while mastery is a more importantachievement goal for school. 
Even so, those who had strong achievement goals for school also tended to have strongachievement goals 
for gaming, and this trend was strongest inregard to performance goals. Gamers who were motivated to 
playbetter than others also tend to be motivated to do better than others in school.  Table 1. Gaming 
and Classroom Achievement Goal Comparisonand Correlations In order to better understand the gaming achievement 
constructs, we conducted a factor analysis using principal componentsextraction and Varimax rotation 
on the 12 items representing the four achievement goals. The result yielded a two-factor resultinstead 
of the expected four-factor result. Based on the two factorsolution, we created a single performance 
goals measure and asingle mastery goals measure. The approach-avoidance distinctionwas important in context 
of classroom achievement motivation,but they were too highly correlated for gaming achievement motivations. 
The factor analysis yielded a performance scale which combines approach and avoidance and a mastery scalebased 
only on mastery-approach. These were used to classifyrespondents into four gaming achievement goal player 
types (seeFigure 2). Non-achievers (29% of study participants) were belowmedian motivation on both mastery 
and performance; mastery­only achievers (16%) were above median on mastery and belowthe median on performance; 
performance-only achievers (17%)were above median on performance and below median on mastery;and super-achievers 
(38%) were above median on both masteryand performance gaming achievement motivations. Figure 2. Distribution 
of Achievement Goal Player Types Gender and gaming frequency were significantly related to gaming achievement 
goal player types. Males were much moremotivated to outdo other players than were females. Males weresignificantly 
more likely than females to be super-achievers (40%of male, 34% of female) and males were more likely 
to beperformance-only players (21% of male, 7% of female). A plurality of females (40.9%) was non-achievers. 
Similarly, almosthalf (48.5 percent) of avid gamers were super-achievers, while only 29.5 percent of 
non-gamers were super-achievers. In contrast,only 15.2 of avid gamers were non-achievers, while 38.4 
percentof non-gamers were non-achievers. Gender is deeply conflatedwith gaming frequency. Very few females 
were avid gamers(1.5%). Few males were non-gamers (15.9%), but nearly half offemales were non-gamers 
(48.2%). Thus, gender and gaming frequency were strongly related to gaming achievement goals.  5.2 Gaming 
Achievement Goals and Accomplishment Achievement and exploration are well known player motivations[1, 
16, 17]. Players who were motivated by achievement includedthe motivations for advancement (progress, 
power accumulation,and status), mechanics (numbers optimization, modding, and analysis), and competition 
(challenging others, provocation, anddomination). Players motivated by exploration included motivations 
for discovery (exploration, lore, finding hiddenthings), role-playing (story line, character history, 
roles, fantasy),customization (appearances, accessories, style, color scheme), andescapism (relax, escape 
from real life, avoiding real-life problems). In order to distinguish achievement goals with achievement 
player motivation, we will refer to achievement player motivation as accomplishment motivation. We examined 
the relationship of gaming achievement goals withfour accomplishment-related gaming preferences: Players 
motivated by accomplishment would be expected to preferpreferred hard over easy games, compete to earn 
the best scorerather than just play for fun at parties, enjoy time limits rather than say time limits 
interfere, and prefer to play with others ratherthan alone. One way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with 
post-hoc Tukey HSD analysis was used to compare different preference betweengaming achievement goal types. 
As predicted, super-achievers and performance-only had stronger preference for hard games and competing 
than mastery-only and non-achievers. Super-achievers and mastery-only players also enjoyed time limit 
more,interestingly performance-only players did not enjoy time limit.There was no significant difference 
in preference for playing withothers or along, more than half of respondents in all gaming achievement 
goal types preferred to play with others than alone. We used hierarchical multiple regression analysis 
to drill downand see whether gaming achievement goals have explanatorypower beyond what can be predicted 
by gender and gaming.Independent variables gender and gaming frequency were enteredinto the first block, 
and mastery and performance goals wereentered into the second block to predict each of the accomplishment 
-related gaming preferences. When controllingfor gender and gaming frequency, mastery goals predicted 
two accomplishment preferences (preferring hard over easy games [ß=.21, p<.001, adjusted R square=.16], 
enjoying time limits [ß=.19, p<.001, adjusted R square=.04]). And performance goalspredicted the fourth 
(competing at a party rather than playing just for fun [ß=.20, p<.001, adjusted R square=.09]). Gender 
and gaming were significant predictors for three of the four accomplishment-related gaming preferences. 
However,achievement goal orientation increased variance explained overand above gender and gaming frequency. 
Furthermore, in every case either mastery or else performance goals emerged as significant, but never 
both. This finding supports the importance of distinguishing between these two kinds of achievement goalorientations. 
 5.3 Gaming Achievement Goals and Exploration Our four gaming achievement player types are conceptuallyindependent 
of exploration motivations. In other words, playerscan have both achievement goals and exploration motivations. 
Weasked four forced choice questions that relate to exploration ingames. Our questions included whether 
they might enjoy a gamethat emphasize exploration without competition, like to explorethe game world 
beyond what is necessary to win the game, enjoyrealistic details about people and places or prefer no 
extraneousdetails, and enjoy playing the latest game rather than sticking with familiar games. These 
exploration preferences were summed to form an exploration variable whose value could range from zero 
to four.Exploration was significantly different by gaming achievementgoal player type. Non-achievers 
averaged 2.86 (s.d.=1.03) exploration points, performance-only types averaged 2.82 (s.d.=.81), mastery-only 
averaged 2.35 (s.d.=1.16), and super­achievers averaged 2.61 (s.d.=1.14) exploration points. One-wayANOVA 
showed that the differences were highly significant (F[3, 420]=4.05, p=.007). Players who had high mastery 
gaming achievement goals (super-achievers and mastery-only) were theones who were least likely to expect 
to enjoy exploration in games. Hierarchical multiple regression analysis confirmed that masterygaming 
achievement goals negate exploration in games. Mastery goals significantly predicted exploration, ß=-.14, 
p=.009, adjusted R square=.05, indicating that high mastery was associated with lower exploration. Performance 
achievement and gender did not predicting exploration. But interestingly, gaming frequency did predict 
exploration, ß=.17, p=007, suggesting that people who play more games prefer exploration more. Prior 
research on player types had assumed that achievers andexplorers were mutually exclusive player types. 
What we findhere is that all four gaming achievement player types engage in exploration. But those with 
mastery goals engage in significantlyless exploration than those who lack mastery goals. On the otherhand, 
performance goals do not appear to be at odds with exploration. Performance achievement player types 
were almostas high on exploration as were non-achievers.  6. CONCLUSIONS Our findings provide strong 
support for further investigation intothe construct of gaming achievement goals. Performance goals(the 
desire to play better than other players) were the predominantmotivation for most avid gamers and more 
important than thedesire to play well. Mastery approach and performance goals werecorrelated but appear 
to tap distinct and important dimensions ofgaming goal orientation. Mastery approach goals positively 
predicted players interest in accomplishment (prefer hard gamesand time limit), and negatively predicted 
interest in exploration.Performance goals predicted enjoyment of competing with others,but also playing 
easy games. Such preference may lead to dysfunctional learning because rather than challenging theirability, 
these players prefer to play casually to prevent losing.Non-achievers are also a key component of the 
gaming audience,particularly in the context of games for learning or cognitiveexercise which are not 
voluntarily played. The nature of forced play experience, as experienced when games are used in structured 
learning or training environments, is that the gamingexperience may be tailored towards specific kinds 
of players andnot others who are also forced to play the game. The next step inour research program will 
be to try to link gaming behaviors and outcomes with gaming achievement orientation. The findings in 
this work speak to the following revelations for the process ofdesigning forced play experiences: Know 
the gender and gaming experience of your audience. Game design for male-only audiences can safely emphasizeperformance 
and super-achievement. But design for mixed genderaudiences and female only populations should strongly 
considerthe needs of non-achievers and players with mastery-only goals.Our findings should definitely 
help focus design emphasisaccordingly on performance, mastery, or exploration. On average,females are 
more likely to be classified as non-achievers, with lowperformance and mastery gaming achievement goals. 
They arealso less motivated by exploration or achievement. Female are more likely to prefer to play alone, 
and dislike competing tooutplay other players. Non-gamers are the most difficult audienceto design for 
since they are less motivated by achievement orexploration. Super-achievers tend to enjoy both achievement 
andexploration. A single game design is unlikely to appeal equally tothese different audiences. Interest 
in achievement rarely co-occurs with an absence ofinterest in exploration. Achievers have typically been 
thought of as opposite to explorers. Our findings showed that most players are interested in bothachievement 
and exploration. A small minority of players (those interested in mastery goals but not performance goals) 
are the ones most likely to only achievement without exploration,however only 16% of our samples were 
mastery-only achieverswhile performance-only achievers also tend to enjoy exploration.The canonical achiever 
gamer type who eschews exploration isextremely rare compared to the existence of gamers who enjoyexploration 
either as part of pursuing achievement goals or in the absence of achievement goals. Achievement-oriented 
game elements (e.g. timers, scoring, leaderboards, etc.) have been common in digital games since their 
rise to popularity in the 1980 s. However based on our findings, their use in forced play experiences 
should be done much more deliberately. This begs the question of how do we design for non-achievers? 
which is beyond the scope of our current results. The construct of exploration goals in gaming is underexplored. 
Research into underlying dimensions of enjoyment of exploration in games iswarranted. Introduce gameplay 
by presenting the game as a meaningfultask, in which how well players play will influence receivedbenefits 
(such as learning or cognitive exercise). It is clear from our results what in hindsight is obvious, 
thatgames are played within a motivational context (or lack thereof).Simply forcing people to play a 
game which is well designed forlearning does not mean the game will achieve the desired result. Players 
need to engage with the game, and how the game isintroduced can help or hurt that engagement.   7. 
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS Jennifer Mangels, Associate Professor of Psychology at BaruchCollege &#38; Graduate 
Center, City University of New York, servedas a consultant. This research is partially supported by grant#0943064 
from the National Science Foundation. The opinionsexpressed are those of the authors and do not represent 
MichiganState University, Georgia Institute of Technology, or the NationalScience Foundation. 8. REFERENCES 
[1] Bartle, R. A. 1996. Hearts, clubs, diamonds, spades: Players who suit MUDs. Journal of MUD Research, 
1, 1. [2] Butler, R., and Neuman, O. 1995. Effects of task and egoachievement goals on help-seeking behaviors 
and attitudes.Journal of Educational Psychology, 87, 261 271. [3] Dweck, C. S., and Elliott, E. S. 1983. 
Achievementmotivation. In Handbook of child psychology, P. Mussen and E. M. Hetherington, Ed. Wiley, 
New York, 643 691 [4] Dweck, C. S., and Leggett, E. L. 1988. A social-cognitive approach to motivation 
and personality. Psychological Review, 95, 256-273. [5] Elliot, A. J. 2005. A conceptual history of the 
achievementgoal construct. In, Handbook of competence and motivation, A. Elliot and C. Dweck, Ed. Guilford 
Press, New York, 52 72. [6] Elliott, E. S., and Dweck, C. S. 1988. Goals: An approach tomotivation and 
achievement. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 54, 5 12. [7] Elliot, A., and McGregor, H. 
2001. A 2 X 2 AchievementGoal Framework. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 80, 3, 501-519. 
[8] Elliot, A. J., and Thrash, T. M. 2001. Achievement goals andthe hierarchical model of achievement 
motivation. Educational Psychology Review, 13, 139 156. [9] Erdley, C., Cain, K., Loomis, C., Dumas-Hines, 
F., andDweck, C.S. 1997. The relations among children s socialgoals, implicit personality theories and 
response to socialfailure. Developmental Psychology, 33, 263-272. [10] Grant. H. and Dweck, C. 2003. 
Clarifying achievement goalsand their impact. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 85, 3, 541-553. 
[11] Heeter, C., Lee, Y. H, Medler, B., and Magerko. B. in press.Impacts of forced serious game play 
on vulnerablesubgroups. International Journal of Games and Computer-Mediated Simulations. [12] Henderlong, 
J., and Lepper, M. 2002. The effects of praiseon children's intrinsic motivation: A review and synthesis.Psychological 
Bulletin, 128, 774-795. [13] Lepper, M. R., and Henderlong, J. 2000. Turning play into work and work 
into play : 25 years of research on intrinsic versus extrinsic motivation. In Intrinsic and extrinsic 
motivation: the search for optimal motivation andperformance. C. Sansone and J. M. Harackiewicz Eds. 
Academic Press: San Diego. 257-307 [14] Magerko, B., Heeter, C., and Medler, B. 2010. Tapping intothe 
hidden potential of serious games: Accommodatingindividual differences. In Interdisciplinary models and 
toolsfor serious games: Emerging concepts and future directions. R. Van Eck Ed., IGI Global. [15] Mahncke 
H.W., Bronstone, A., and Merzenich, M.M. 2006.Brain plasticity and functional losses in the aged: Scientificbases 
for a novel intervention. Program Brain Research, 157, 81 109. [16] Yee, N. 2006. Motivations of Play 
in Online Games.CyberPsychology and Behavior, 9, 6, 772-775. [17] Yee, N. 2008. Maps of digital desires: 
Exploring the topography of gender and play in online games. In Beyondbarbie and mortal kombat: New perspectives 
in gender and gaming. Kafai, Y., Heeter, C., Denner, J. and Sun, J. Eds., MIT Press: Boston, MA.  
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<article_sponsors>
			<funding_agency>National Science Foundation</funding_agency>
			<grant_numbers>
				<grant_number>0943064</grant_number>
			</grant_numbers>
		</article_sponsors>
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	<article_rec>
		<article_id>2037702</article_id>
		<sort_key>100</sort_key>
		<display_label>Article No.</display_label>
		<pages>5</pages>
		<display_no>8</display_no>
		<article_publication_date>08-07-2011</article_publication_date>
		<seq_no>4</seq_no>
		<title><![CDATA[Modeling play]]></title>
		<subtitle><![CDATA[re-casting expertise in MMOGs]]></subtitle>
		<page_from>1</page_from>
		<page_to>6</page_to>
		<doi_number>10.1145/2037692.2037702</doi_number>
		<url>http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2037702</url>
		<abstract>
			<par><![CDATA[<p>With the increasing popularity of massively multiplayer online games (MMOGs) such as <i>World of Warcraft, EVE Online</i>, and <i>Maple Story</i>, attempts have been made to define and measure player expertise both within and across online games. Apart from nuanced ethnographic accounts of elite players, which are deliberately localized and small-scale, studies of MMOG expertise to date have either deployed one-dimensional variables such time spent playing and in-game titles and accomplishments, or a combination of the these. These approaches risk obscuring a host of complex considerations, such as players' prior experience with the game or genre, their relationships to other players, and the ludic affordances and limitations of specific games. And they are also significantly less sophisticated than the criteria and tools players themselves use to measure expertise.</p> <p>Our study of expertise in online games is guided by Bruno Latour's injunction to "follow the actors"---which for us in this case meant paying careful attention to how players themselves characterize and pursue 'expertise' in the everyday realities of their everyday/everynight MMOG lives. Drawing from a multisite, mixed-methods study of 250 MMOG players in 8 sites (both university laboratory and public LAN events), this paper proposes a model for identifying and assessing expertise that is better able to take into consideration the multiple forms, components and expressions of 'expert' game playing that players themselves are guided by. This model divides expertise into four inter-related modalities, each addressing a different set of competencies: investment, skill, discourse, and game knowledge. Reviewing each modality in turn, the paper frames this model as an attempt to preserve the complexity of qualitatively-driven, ethnographic accounts of expertise, mobilized in a quantifiable and measurable way.</p>]]></par>
		</abstract>
		<keywords>
			<kw><![CDATA[MMOGs]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[expertise]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[massively multiplayer online role-playing games]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[qualitative research]]></kw>
			<kw><![CDATA[quantitative research]]></kw>
		</keywords>
		<categories>
			<primary_category>
				<cat_node>K.8.0</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Games</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</primary_category>
			<other_category>
				<cat_node>J.4</cat_node>
				<descriptor>Sociology</descriptor>
				<type>S</type>
			</other_category>
		</categories>
		<ccs2012>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010455.10010461</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Law, social and behavioral sciences->Sociology</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>100</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10002951.10003227.10003251.10003258</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Information systems->Information systems applications->Multimedia information systems->Massively multiplayer online games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10011007.10010940.10010941.10010969.10010970</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Software and its engineering->Software organization and properties->Contextual software domains->Virtual worlds software->Interactive games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
			<concept>
				<concept_id>0.10010405.10010476.10011187.10011190</concept_id>
				<concept_desc>CCS->Applied computing->Computers in other domains->Personal computers and PC applications->Computer games</concept_desc>
				<concept_significance>500</concept_significance>
			</concept>
		</ccs2012>
		<authors>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809226</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81330499191]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>1</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Nicholas]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Taylor]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[York University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[nickttaylor@gmail.com]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809227</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81100489557]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>2</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Suzanne]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[de Castell]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Simon Fraser University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809228</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81435596928]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>3</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Jennifer]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Jenson]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[York University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
			<au>
				<person_id>P2809229</person_id>
				<author_profile_id><![CDATA[81487645575]]></author_profile_id>
				<orcid_id></orcid_id>
				<seq_no>4</seq_no>
				<first_name><![CDATA[Megan]]></first_name>
				<middle_name><![CDATA[]]></middle_name>
				<last_name><![CDATA[Humphrey]]></last_name>
				<suffix><![CDATA[]]></suffix>
				<affiliation><![CDATA[Simon Fraser University]]></affiliation>
				<role><![CDATA[Author]]></role>
				<email_address><![CDATA[]]></email_address>
			</au>
		</authors>
		<references>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>1</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Bakhtin, M. 1986. <i>Speech Genres and Other Late Essays</i>. Trans. by Vern W. McGee. University of Texas Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>2</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Bjork, S. and Linderoth, J. 2010. Pickup Groups as Situated Activity Systems, Game Design and Social Rules in <i>Left 4 Dead</i>. Paper presented at the 2010 Association of Internet Researchers (AoIR), Gothenburg, Sweden, October 20--23.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1633613</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1632710</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>3</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Huffaker, D., Wang, J., Treem, J., Ahmad, M., Fullerton, L., Williams, D., Poole, M., and Contractor, N. 2009. The Social Behaviors of Experts in Massive Multiplayer Online Role-playing Games. In <i>Proceedings of the 2009 IEEE International Conference on Computational Science and Engineering</i>, IEEE.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>4</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Latour, B. 2005. <i>Re-assembling the Social: An Introduction to Actor Network Theory</i>. Oxford University Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>5</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Linderoth, J., and Bennerstedt, U. 2007. This is Not a Door: An Ecological Approach to Computer Games. In <i>Situated Play: Proceedings of the 2007 Digital Games Research Association Conference, Tokyo, Japan</i>, A. Baba, Ed. Japax, 600--609.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>6</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[McGonigal, J. 2010. Gaming Can Make a Better World. Presented at TED: Ideas Worth Spreading, Longbeach, California, February 2010. Accessed Jan 12, 2010 at http://www.ted.com/talks/jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world.html]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>7</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Reeves, S., Brown, B., and Laurier, E. 2009. Experts at Play: Understanding Skilled Expertise. <i>Games and Culture</i>, 4, 3, 205--227.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1633701</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1632710</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>8</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Shim, K. J., Ahmad, M. A., Pathak, N, and Srivastava, J. 2009. Inferring Player Rating from Performance Data in Massively Multiplayer Online Role-Playing Games (MMORPGs). In <i>Proceedings of the 2009 IEEE International Conference on Computational Science and Engineering</i>, IEEE, 1199--1204.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>9</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Steinkuehler, C. A. 2006. Massively Multiplayer Online Videogames as Participation in a Discourse. <i>Mind, Culture and Activity</i>, 3, 1, 38--52.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>10</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Taylor, N. 2008. Periscopic Play: Re-positioning 'the Field' in MMO Studies. <i>Loading... 2</i>, 3. Accessed January 10, 2011, from http://journals.sfu.ca/loading/index.php/loading/article/viewArticle/43.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>11</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Taylor, T. L. 2006. <i>Play Between Worlds</i>. MIT Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_seq_no>12</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Thomas, D. 2005. 2, 443 Quenkers and Counting, or What in Us Really Wants to Grind? Examining the Grind in <i>Star Wars Galaxies: An Empire Divided. In Changing Views -- Worlds in Play: Proceedings of the 2005 Digital Games Research Association (DiGRA) Conference, Vancouver, BC</i>, S. de Castell, Ed. SFU Press.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
			<ref>
				<ref_obj_id>1159988</ref_obj_id>
				<ref_obj_pid>1159982</ref_obj_pid>
				<ref_seq_no>13</ref_seq_no>
				<ref_text><![CDATA[Yee, N. 2006. The Demographics, Motivations and Derived Experiences of Users of Massively-multiuser Online Graphical Environments. <i>PRESENCE: Teleoperators and Virtual Environments</i>, 15, 309--329.]]></ref_text>
				<ref_id></ref_id>
			</ref>
		</references>
		<fulltext>
			<file>
				<seq_no></seq_no>
				<fname></fname>
			</file>
			<ft_body><![CDATA[
			]]></ft_body>
		</fulltext>
		<article_type art_type="regular_article" />
		<ccc>
			<copyright_holder>
				<copyright_holder_name>ACM</copyright_holder_name>
				<copyright_holder_year>2011</copyright_holder_year>
			</copyright_holder>
		</ccc>
	</article_rec>
	</section>
</content>
</proceeding>
